<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A review of the grand case of the present ministry whether they may lawfully declare and subscribe as by the late act of uniformity is required? : in reply to a book entitled A short surveigh of the grand case, &amp;c. : wherein all their objections against both the declarations are considered and answered / by the same hand.</title>
            <author>Fullwood, Francis, d. 1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 233 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 120 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40719</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2514</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20121</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12258931</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12258931</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57726</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40719)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57726)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 915:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A review of the grand case of the present ministry whether they may lawfully declare and subscribe as by the late act of uniformity is required? : in reply to a book entitled A short surveigh of the grand case, &amp;c. : wherein all their objections against both the declarations are considered and answered / by the same hand.</title>
                  <author>Fullwood, Francis, d. 1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 160 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Dring, and are to be sold ... by M. Mitchel ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Francis Fullwood. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Pages 100 to the end are filmed from the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York copy and are spliced at the end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Customs and practices.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57726:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57726:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A REVIEW OF THE GRAND CASE OF THE Preſent Miniſtry, Whether they may <hi>Lawfully Declare</hi> and <hi>Subſcribe</hi> as by the late <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> is required? In Reply to a Book Entituled; <hi>A Short Surveigh of the Grand Caſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein <hi>all</hi> their <hi>Objections</hi> againſt <hi>both</hi> the <hi>Declarations</hi> are <hi>Conſidered</hi> and <hi>Anſwered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the <hi>ſame Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Job. 4. 2.</bibl> 
               <hi>If we aſſay</hi> to <hi>commune with thee, wilt thou be grieved? but who can withold himſelf from ſpeaking?</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Dring,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> and by <hi>M. Mitchel,</hi> at the firſt Shop in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Hall. 1663.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:57726:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57726:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PREFACE <hi>To my Reverend</hi> Brethren, <hi>the</hi> Surveighers <hi>of the</hi> Grand Caſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. I <hi>Find ſome</hi> Learned Men <hi>have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jackſon</hi> on the Creed.</note> 
               <hi>both an</hi> Equivalency of Errours <hi>throughout moſt</hi> Ages <hi>and Nations; and alſo, an</hi> Equivalency <hi>of</hi> means <hi>to</hi> evince <hi>and to</hi> vindicate <hi>the</hi> truth; <hi>by the</hi> wiſdom of God, <hi>ſo</hi> propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd <hi>to the diverſity of</hi> times, <hi>as no</hi> Age <hi>could have</hi> better <hi>then the</hi> preſent.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>May I obſerve, that our</hi> preſent Age <hi>and the</hi> differences <hi>of it, are of that</hi> ſtrange <hi>and ſingular</hi> Humour, <hi>that they need an</hi> Exception <hi>from that Learned</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation <hi>in</hi> both Reſpects.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>As for the things in</hi> Controverſie <hi>betwixt</hi> us, <hi>though, haply, they may be</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:57726:3"/> reduced <hi>to ſome</hi> Ancient Topicks, <hi>yet the</hi> Mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Caſes, <hi>as they</hi> now ariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>from the force of the</hi> New Law, <hi>the</hi> Act for Uniformity, <hi>they have much of</hi> pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity <hi>and</hi> newneſs <hi>in them: and whilſt the</hi> Burthen <hi>of</hi> Reſolving <hi>them remaines</hi> upon <hi>ſo</hi> weak a ſhoulder, <hi>the</hi> means <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> juſtly be</hi> Cenſured, <hi>as</hi> inequivalent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>what ſo ever the</hi> bleſſing of God <hi>may be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Yet, conſidering, the Diſcuſſion of the</hi> preſent Debates <hi>depends more upon a due</hi> examining <hi>of Rationall</hi> Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, <hi>then upon</hi> Authority's <hi>of</hi> Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, <hi>or any</hi> other <hi>Learning, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires long</hi> Experience <hi>and</hi> Obſervation, <hi>I am</hi> not much <hi>diſcouraged: yea ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng, upon the</hi> Review <hi>(you have occaſioned me to make) I</hi> my ſelf <hi>do</hi> diſcern ſome things <hi>betwixt us</hi> more clearly <hi>then before, I take encouragement to</hi> hope <hi>(as I heartily</hi> wiſh) <hi>that</hi> you, <hi>my</hi> Brethren, <hi>may do</hi> ſo <hi>too.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>I am ſure my</hi> Aim <hi>is</hi> good, <hi>as, I I know, 'tis</hi> great. <hi>I could not hope to</hi> hit <hi>it, at the</hi> firſt <hi>or</hi> ſecond <hi>ſhoot: but, through</hi> your Invitation, <hi>I venture</hi> again; <hi>that, if poſſible, by any means, I might at length</hi> attain <hi>it: However, I ſhall reckon the</hi> ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs <hi>far</hi> more worthy <hi>then</hi> all <hi>my</hi> abours, <hi>if I onely</hi> gain <hi>a</hi> little ground
<pb facs="tcp:57726:3"/> 
               <hi>in what I</hi> proſecute, <hi>and come</hi> nearer <hi>and</hi> nearer <hi>to my deſired</hi> end, <hi>for my</hi> Bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hrens ſake, <hi>and the</hi> peace of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>You do</hi> quicken <hi>this</hi> expectation <hi>in me, while you,</hi> modeſtly <hi>indeed (as you ſay) ſignifie to me, that, though my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the</hi> Grand Caſe <hi>hath not made</hi> on you <hi>that</hi> impreſſion, <hi>nor produced that</hi> effect <hi>I might</hi> Rationally <hi>promiſe to</hi> my Self; <hi>yet your</hi> ſelves cannot but obſerve, it hath effected it in many others. <hi>What, you think, I might</hi> rationally ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect before, <hi>I</hi> hope, <hi>I may more</hi> chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully pray <hi>for,</hi> now: <hi>For without</hi> Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance, <hi>I</hi> preſume <hi>to commend to your</hi> own reaſon, <hi>whether</hi> moſt, <hi>if not</hi> all, <hi>of your</hi> main exceptions <hi>are not</hi> blown <hi>quite</hi> off, <hi>by this</hi> Second Ventilation <hi>of the matters in difference.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>I cannot doubt, but that you will eaſily be</hi> ſatisfied, <hi>that a</hi> Comparative Approbation <hi>is a</hi> ſufficient <hi>ground for</hi> unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent <hi>according to the</hi> Act.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Alſo, that ſeeing you intimate, you</hi> could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear the particulars you except againſt <hi>in the</hi> Common-Prayer Book, <hi>which cannot be without</hi> ſome Aſſent <hi>and</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:57726:4"/> Conſent; <hi>and ſeeing, that no</hi> Aſſent <hi>and</hi> Conſent <hi>cannot be other then</hi> Real; <hi>and ſeeing, all</hi> Real Aſſent <hi>and</hi> Conſent, <hi>is, therefore,</hi> unfeigned; <hi>that you will not find</hi> further <hi>reaſon to</hi> ſcruple, <hi>to give your</hi> unfeigned Aſſent <hi>and</hi> Conſent <hi>to the</hi> ſame.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>For the matter of the</hi> Govenant, <hi>I hope you will</hi> better <hi>conſider that the</hi> great hinge <hi>upon whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that</hi> Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie turnes, <hi>is not the</hi> neceſſity <hi>of</hi> Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Government, <hi>but the lawfulneſs of it: For, though you think it</hi> not neceſſary in it ſelf, <hi>or by the</hi> Word of God; <hi>yet if it be</hi> lawful, <hi>that is, not</hi> ſinful, <hi>it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes</hi> neceſſary <hi>upon us, by the</hi> Laws of the Land, <hi>and may not be</hi> ſworn againſt.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Moreover, I would fain believe, that the great</hi> ſtones <hi>of the</hi> Reality <hi>and</hi> Nationality <hi>of the</hi> Covenant <hi>(it being</hi> eſſentiall <hi>to</hi> Oaths, <hi>in the judgement of the Reverend Caſuiſt Biſhop</hi> Sanderſon, <hi>to be</hi> perſonal, <hi>and to</hi> bind <hi>but the</hi> Takers onely:) <hi>as alſo, that, about</hi> Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment eſtabliſhed by Law; <hi>and the</hi> diſſolution <hi>of the Long</hi>-Parliament, <hi>are</hi> perfectly removed <hi>out of your way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>But I ſhall not</hi> Anticipate: <hi>I leave</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:57726:4"/> 
               <hi>the</hi> Book <hi>to your</hi> Chriſtian <hi>and candid</hi> peruſal; <hi>accounting it no mean</hi> felicity, <hi>that it hath to do with perſons</hi> Ingenuous <hi>and</hi> Learned, <hi>and</hi> truly deſirous <hi>of</hi> ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Yet, I muſt tell you, it much</hi> troubled <hi>me, that you took thoſe</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions <hi>of</hi> felones, ſures, &amp; proditores de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, <hi>ſo</hi> tenderly <hi>to</hi> your <hi>ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>I told you, they were the words of</hi> Dr. Donne, <hi>and</hi> wiſh'd <hi>they were not</hi> applicable <hi>in our</hi> Caſe. <hi>Indeed, it was</hi> far <hi>from me, to</hi> conclude all <hi>diſſenters with</hi> them: <hi>nor dare I ſay,</hi> you <hi>deſerved the</hi> charge <hi>in the</hi> leaſt degree.</p>
            <p n="14">14. <hi>Yet I dare ſay,</hi> you <hi>will not</hi> plead <hi>for</hi> all diſſenters: <hi>yea, that you do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur with</hi> Caſſianus, <hi>that</hi> ſome <hi>men (he ſaith</hi> many) <hi>are carried to</hi> deſire ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings <hi>by</hi> humane reſpects, <hi>by the</hi> Spirit <hi>either of their</hi> Parents, <hi>or the Spirit of</hi> Levity, <hi>or the Spirit of</hi> Liberty; <hi>or, as I may add, the Spirit of a</hi> party: <hi>Yea, it is</hi> ſtoried <hi>of one</hi> Eulalia, <hi>a</hi> Maid <hi>of</hi> 12 years old, <hi>that came from her</hi> Fathers <hi>houſe, declared her ſelf to be a</hi> Chriſtian, ſpit <hi>in the</hi> Judges face, <hi>and</hi> provoked <hi>him to</hi> execute <hi>her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. <hi>Now, no doubt,</hi> my Brethren,
<pb facs="tcp:57726:5"/> 
               <hi>the</hi> ſame Spirit <hi>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eal <hi>may work</hi> irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, <hi>in</hi> any, <hi>and in</hi> our Age: <hi>eſpecially, when an</hi> opinion, <hi>that all the</hi> Godly, <hi>muſt</hi> ſuffer perſecution, <hi>is</hi> ſpread over <hi>the</hi> people.</p>
            <p n="16">16. <hi>It is noted by</hi> Bodin, <hi>that</hi> Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>in</hi> Tertullians <hi>time, were ſo</hi> pleaſed <hi>with</hi> ſuffering, <hi>that ſometimes</hi> Edicts <hi>wore made by their very</hi> perſecutors, <hi>that</hi> no more Chriſtians <hi>ſhould be</hi> executed, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they</hi> perceived; <hi>that the</hi> Marty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s delighted <hi>in</hi> dying; <hi>and, my</hi> Dear Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, <hi>(if Chriſtian</hi> Magiſtrates <hi>muſt be</hi> perſecutors, <hi>and the</hi> effect <hi>of the</hi> Law perſecution, <hi>and) if the</hi> readineſs of your numbers <hi>to ſuffer, or any other</hi> confidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>ſhould</hi> prevail <hi>for a</hi> like Edict <hi>to</hi> ſtop <hi>your</hi> ſufferings; <hi>I beſeech you, do not think,</hi> I ſhould be againſt it, <hi>I would not be thought your</hi> enemy, <hi>becauſe I would</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell you the truth, <hi>and</hi> earneſtly <hi>perſwade you to</hi> do <hi>your</hi> duty, <hi>and not to</hi> ſuffer <hi>when you</hi> need not.</p>
            <p n="17">17. <hi>I would rather</hi> ſtroak <hi>you with the</hi> ſeather, <hi>then</hi> prick <hi>you with the</hi> pen; <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to</hi> provoke <hi>you to</hi> good works, <hi>and to</hi> mind <hi>you of your</hi> danger. <hi>Indeed, I fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, at the time I wrote my</hi> laſt <hi>Book, that</hi> many <hi>of my</hi> worthy Brethren <hi>were</hi> fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling;
<pb facs="tcp:57726:5"/> 
               <hi>and I was (in my</hi> Epiſtle) <hi>ſomewhat</hi> earneſt <hi>to</hi> ſave <hi>them, and that,</hi> I hope, <hi>was</hi> all my Crime, <hi>and no more then</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous perſons <hi>are willing</hi> to <hi>pardon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Give me leave to</hi> conclude <hi>with thoſe notable words of Famous Doctor</hi> Collet, <hi>in his</hi> Sermon, <hi>p.</hi> 28. which <hi>I deſire to</hi> do <q>
                  <hi>with the</hi> ſame Spirit, <hi>that</hi> he <hi>ſpake them; if peradventure it be thought that I have</hi> paſſed my Bounds, <hi>or have ſaid anything</hi> out of temper, forgive it me, <hi>and ye ſhall</hi> forgive a man <hi>ſpeaking</hi> out of meer zeal; <hi>a man</hi> heartily lamenting <hi>the</hi> Decay <hi>of the</hi> Church: <hi>and conſider the</hi> thing it ſelf, <hi>not regarding</hi> my fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhneſs. <hi>Conſider the</hi> miſerable end <hi>and State of the</hi> Church, <hi>and</hi> endeavour your ſelves <hi>with</hi> all your Souls <hi>and</hi> Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities <hi>(as he, to</hi> reform it, <hi>ſo I) to</hi> ſave it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Lord of peace <hi>himſelf</hi> give you peace, alwayes, and by all means: <note place="margin">Job 29: 2.</note> 
               <hi>and O</hi> that you were as in moneths paſt, <hi>My dear Brethren,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:57726:6"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>CASE 1. <hi>WHether it be lawſul to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in the words of the</hi> firſt Declaration. Page 1</item>
               <item>CHAP. 1. <hi>Touching the Book of</hi> Ordination. 1.</item>
               <item>CHAP. 2: <hi>Touching the Book of Common-Prayer.</hi> 13</item>
               <item>SECT. 2. Of, <hi>let us beſeech him,</hi> &amp;c. 16</item>
               <item>SECT. 3. <hi>Of popular Reſponds.</hi> 21</item>
               <item>SECT. 4. <hi>Of the Holy Table.</hi> 22</item>
               <item>SECT. 5. <hi>Of the old Tranſlation of the Pſalmes.</hi> 28</item>
               <item>SECT. 6. <hi>Of the Salvation of Infants.</hi> 30</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:57726:6"/>
               <item>SECT. 7. <hi>Of Aſſent and Conſent unfeigned.</hi> 35</item>
               <item>SECT. 8. <hi>Of the phraſe in the Act, [the uſe of all things,</hi> &amp;c.] 43</item>
               <item>CASE 2. <hi>Whether it be lawful to Declare in the words of the</hi> ſecond Declaration. 51</item>
               <item>CASE 6. Whether we may lawfully declare in theſe words, <hi>I do hold there lies no Obligation on me, or any other perſon, from the Oath commonly called the</hi> Solemn League and Covenant, <hi>to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour any change or alteration of Government in the Church or State?</hi> 52</item>
               <item>CASE 7. <hi>Whether any private or ſingle perſon may lawfully endeavour the Alteration of</hi> Church-Government <hi>by virtue of the</hi> Covenant. 51</item>
               <item>SECT. 1. <hi>Of the diſſolving the long Parliament.</hi> 59</item>
               <item>SECT. 2. <hi>Of the Reality and Nationality of the Covenant.</hi> 66</item>
               <item>SECT 3. <hi>Of the capacity of all Covenanters.</hi> 68</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:57726:7"/>
               <item>CASE 8. <hi>Whether to endeavour to alter the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church be againſt the Right of the King.</hi> 76</item>
               <item>CASE 9. <hi>Whether to violate the Kings Right be not ſinful.</hi> 77</item>
               <item>SECT. 1. <hi>Of the Kings Right as Supreme Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor of the Laws.</hi> 78</item>
               <item>SECT. 2. <hi>Of the King Right in the Government of the Church.</hi> 79</item>
               <item>SECT. 3. <hi>Of the Kings Right as Legiſlator.</hi> 80</item>
               <item>SECT. 4. <hi>Of the Kings Proclamation againſt the Covenent.</hi> 89</item>
               <item>CASE 10. <hi>Whether the</hi> Covenant <hi>to endeavour the Extirpation of</hi> Epiſcopacy <hi>be againſt the</hi> Laws, <hi>and conſequently</hi> ſinful. 95</item>
               <item>CASE 11. <hi>Whether the preſent Church-Government was eſtabliſhed by</hi> Law <hi>before the</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant <hi>was taken?</hi> 99</item>
               <item>SECT. 1. <hi>Church Government is fixed by</hi> Law. ibid:</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:57726:7"/>
               <item>SECT. 2. <hi>The</hi> Original <hi>of</hi> Prelacy <hi>is not to be ſought in</hi> Law. 100</item>
               <item>SECT. 3. <hi>Church-Government is eſtabliſhed by Law.</hi> 102</item>
               <item>CASE 12. <hi>Whether the Covenant can oblige againſt a Future Law.</hi> 114</item>
               <item>CASE 15. <hi>Touching the word</hi> [Endeavour] <hi>and the</hi> ſence <hi>and</hi> force <hi>of it, in the</hi> Covenant, <hi>and in the</hi> Act. 118</item>
               <item>SECT. 1 Endeavour <hi>is diſtinguiſhed.</hi> 120</item>
               <item>SECT. 2. <hi>Of the Acts of</hi> Endeavour <hi>juſtified by my Brethren.</hi> 122</item>
               <item>SECT. 3. <hi>Of</hi> Endeavour <hi>by popular groans and complaints.</hi> 127</item>
               <item>SECT. 4. <hi>Of</hi> Endeavour <hi>by Diſputations.</hi> 128</item>
               <item>SECT. 5. <hi>Whether to petition be to</hi> Endeavour <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, and in the</hi> Act. 131</item>
               <item>SECT. 6. <hi>Whether to</hi> Endeavour, <hi>&amp;c. be at all</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:57726:8"/> 
                  <hi>times</hi> ſui Juris <hi>to every Subject, &amp;c.</hi> 135</item>
               <item>CASE. 16. <hi>Whether the</hi> Covenant <hi>be not againſt the Liberty of the</hi> Subject. 143</item>
               <item>CASE. 17. <hi>Whether the</hi> Covenant <hi>be not againſt former Obligations.</hi> 145</item>
               <item>SECT 1. <hi>Whether the</hi> Covenant <hi>be not againſt the</hi> Law <hi>of</hi> Obedience <hi>to Authority.</hi> 146</item>
               <item>SECT. 2. <hi>Whether the</hi> Covenant <hi>be not againſt</hi> former Oaths <hi>and</hi> Promiſes. 152</item>
               <item>SECT. 3. <hi>Whether the</hi> Covenant <hi>can oblige to the laying down of the Miniſtry.</hi> 155</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="case">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57726:8"/>
            <head>CASE I. Whether it be lawful to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in the words of the <hi>firſt</hi> Declaration.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CAP. I. <hi>Touching the Book of</hi> Ordination.</head>
               <p n="1">1. I Find my ſelf <hi>inclined,</hi> (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the <hi>eaſineſs</hi> of my Nature, or a <hi>love</hi> of Peace) to all juſt means of a good <hi>accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> eſpecially with Brethren: And confeſs in a <hi>Temptation</hi> upon me to uſe ſuch <hi>Mediums,</hi> as in my <hi>own</hi> obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion are <hi>leaſt diſputed</hi> by my <hi>opponents:</hi> becauſe it is the eaſieſt way to <hi>encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and the likelieſt to <hi>reconcile</hi> them.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>nearer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> I am to my <hi>adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> the <hi>fairer</hi> is my advantage to lay
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57726:9"/> 
                  <hi>hold</hi> upon him; and when we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed in the <hi>premiſes,</hi> I cannot but hope for a good <hi>Concluſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Such as are friends to <hi>Conformity</hi> could not chooſe but diſcover this peaceable deſign of my laſt <hi>Book; viz.</hi> the <hi>Grand-Caſe,</hi> &amp;c. Though give me leave to Note, that you my diſſenting <hi>Surveyers</hi> of it ſeem <hi>not</hi> to apprehend it, by your great miſtake even of the <hi>firſt Argument</hi> therein improved; by which miſtake alone you labour to <hi>avoid</hi> the <hi>Conſequence</hi> of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I diſtribute the firſt of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations</hi> into <hi>two</hi> parts. The firſt part concerns the <hi>Liturgy.</hi> The ſecond, the Book of <hi>Ordination.</hi> I begin with this ſecond part, touching the Book of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination,</hi> and determine thus.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is lawful to <hi>declare our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned aſſent</hi> and <hi>conſent</hi> to the form and manner of Making, Ordaining, and Conſecrating <hi>Biſhops, Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Deacons:</hi> and I do indeed conclude this, partly, from the practice of many of your <hi>ſelves,</hi> who had formerly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed as much in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our ſubſcriptions to the 39. <hi>Articles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:57726:9"/>5. This you ſay, is an Argument <hi>à facto ad jus,</hi> and not concluding; and if it be <hi>abſolutely</hi> conſidered, as it is by you, I confeſs as much; but if it be <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentum ad homines,</hi> and bear open reſpect to the perſons with whom I diſpute, as I plainly intended it; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks it carrieth force enough.</p>
               <p n="6">6. For, in <hi>Charity</hi> we reckon, that ſuch as did formerly ſubſcribe, did it <hi>in judgement</hi> and Conſcience: neither have we r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſon to believe, that they are diſſatisfied with their former ſubſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in point of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> until they have told the world ſo much, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us the <hi>grounds</hi> of ſuch their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction; and till then, why may we not conclude <hi>à facto ad jus,</hi> againſt ſuch as have formerly ſubſcribed, what they now refuſe. <hi>Viz.</hi> That by their former<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>practice</hi> not yet diſclaimed; as againſt their Conſcience, themſelves conceive this <hi>part</hi> of the declaration to be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and that they may lawfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare accordingly.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Moſt have done a thing, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all may lawfully do it, is indeed <hi>bad Logick.</hi> But that which you judge,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57726:10"/> you may lawfully do, you cannot ſay you may not do it. Now I only aſſume, that you judge you may lawfully do that which you have formerly done; and if this fail, I think it yet lies upon you to ſhew us and the world the <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. But a little more plainly, my <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument</hi> lay thus; Thoſe that have ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed this part of the Declaration al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, in the 39. <hi>Articles,</hi> and read their <hi>allowance</hi> of it openly to their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Congregations; and that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, that had not this been required in the <hi>new Declaration,</hi> no <hi>Conformity,</hi> without ſubſcribing the 39. <hi>Articles,</hi> of which this is one, could <hi>legally ſuffice;</hi> and yet affirm, that had not theſe <hi>new</hi> Declarations been required, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have <hi>Conformed;</hi> may doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, lawfully, as to their <hi>own</hi> principles (for you could not chooſe but ſee that my Argument was <hi>ad homines)</hi> declare their unfeigned aſſent and conſent to the book of <hi>Ordination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. But you venture alſo to gainſay my <hi>Aſſumption,</hi> which you pleaſe to term a <hi>confident aſſertion,</hi> and ſay, you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57726:10"/> cannot but conceive ſtrangely of it. I ſhall not be moved to ſay this is ſtrange <hi>confidence;</hi> only I humbly conceive, you may well <hi>abate</hi> ſomwhat of it by a <hi>new</hi> ſurvey and <hi>ſecond thoughts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. My Aſſertion, (as you have col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected it) is this; that the <hi>moſt</hi> who had Livings, had, at the writing my Book, <hi>ſubſcribed</hi> the form and manner of Mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Ordaining, and Conſecrating of Biſhops, Prieſts, and Deacons, required by this <hi>Article.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Aſſertion you aſſault after this manner. We do not know, ſay you, the moſt that then had Livings; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot ask them the queſtion; but <hi>we think they muſt be moſt of them reor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained according to the new form.</hi> Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterial <hi>Ordination had ſure be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n very Active and Extenſive, and</hi> Presbyters <hi>were eaſie wheelers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. But pray conſider, why muſt the moſt of the Miniſters that poſſeſſed Livings before the 24, of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, be Reordained according to the new form? were there not many that enjoyed their Livings to that <hi>very day</hi> that were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Epiſcopally ordained?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:57726:11"/>
               <p>But your thoughts ſpent upon <hi>Re-or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination</hi> had been better improved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Ejection of thoſe Miniſters that were found in other mens Livings; this might have rendred my Aſſertion leſs ſtrange to you.</p>
               <p n="12">12. I do not ſay that the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> were eaſie wheelers; yet you know they were upon the wheel; and very many of them were by vertue of a <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Act</hi> of Parliament <hi>turned off,</hi> and others that were <hi>Epiſcopally Ordained,</hi> and had been <hi>Legally inducted</hi> into the <hi>ſame</hi> places long before, had the <hi>better turn</hi> of being reſtored.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Now I hope I may have leave to conclude, that the many Ancient Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that were <hi>thus</hi> reſtored, added to the number of <hi>ſuch,</hi> both <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and others, as had continued in their places, during all the time of our great <hi>Diſtractions,</hi> may eaſily make the <hi>Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> of <hi>Subſcribers,</hi> even at the time of writing my <hi>Book,</hi> to exceed the number of Miniſters that then enjoyed their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, and had <hi>not ſubſcribed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Your next <hi>Objection</hi> is, that it was <hi>not</hi> the ſame Book of <hi>Ordination,</hi> which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57726:11"/> was ſubſcribed before, it being in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral things altered.</p>
               <p n="14">14. But, my <hi>dear Brethren,</hi> do not let us <hi>quibble</hi> away our <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> and <hi>Peace. Can</hi> you ſay, I am ſure you <hi>do</hi> not ſay, that theſe books are not the <hi>ſame</hi> for <hi>ſubſtance?</hi> Can you believe that any can <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> the <hi>Old,</hi> that can refuſe the <hi>New?</hi> Yea, is not the book altered for the better in your own apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? and cannot your ſelves rather ſubſcribe the <hi>New</hi> one?</p>
               <p n="15">15. You, indeed, offer that <hi>ſome Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions</hi> and <hi>alterations</hi> made <hi>may bar</hi> your ſubſcriptions: but certainly, if any ſuch there be, it is but fair, either to diſcover them, or not to argue from them.</p>
               <p n="16">16. I ſhall not ask you, whether every <hi>accidental alteration</hi> doth change the <hi>individual</hi> Subject? Whether the paring of your <hi>Nails,</hi> or the ſuffering the <hi>Alteration</hi> of every dayes <hi>Nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> render you not the ſame men? if ſo, <hi>whom</hi> do I reply unto? or where ſhall I find my Surveyers?</p>
               <p n="17">17. But your next <hi>Item</hi> calls me to be more ſerious, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>black</hi> mark
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57726:12"/> your pen hath caſt upon ſome <hi>Cheſhire</hi> Miniſters; to which I have onely this to ſay, that though I dare not <hi>approve,</hi> but did <hi>perſonally diſſwade</hi> ſome bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren from the <hi>ſame</hi> Action; yet [give me-thinks the <hi>Love</hi> of Brethren] might have had a better interpretation, or at leaſt a milder reprehenſion, if not a more private one for it; eſpecially conſidering the <hi>reaſon</hi> of <hi>State</hi> that prevailed for ſuch alterations in order; Mainly for the <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> of <hi>ſuch</hi> as are <hi>unwilling</hi> to <hi>conform</hi> without a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; and therefore not likely to give any <hi>diſſatisfaction</hi> to ſuch as could <hi>Conform</hi> before; yet I would not plead for a ſcandalous practice, as I fear that was.</p>
               <p n="18">18. You do further object, That the <hi>Law</hi> might be ſatisfied with read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſubſcribing ſo many of the <hi>thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty nine Articles</hi> as contain only the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Faith,</hi> and of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> with an omiſſion of that which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Book of <hi>Conſecration,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Statute.</p>
               <p n="19">19. I know this hath been the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of many; yet I ever thought it a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57726:12"/> miſtake, grounded upon a miſ-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Statute.</p>
               <p n="20">20. The words of the Statute are theſe, <hi>[And ſubſcribe to all the Articles of Religion which only contain the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>[which only]</hi> refers to the antecedent <hi>[all the Articles]</hi> and ſerves by way of explication of the Nature of all the Articles, and not by way of excluſion of any of the number; the ſence is this; <hi>which,</hi> that is, <hi>all which Articles contain only</hi> the Doctrine of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Sacraments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="21">21. It is not ſaid, <hi>All thoſe Articles only which contain;</hi> or, <hi>Thoſe Articles which only contain;</hi> but, <hi>All the Articles which contain only;</hi> explaining the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the whole, and not excluding any one of the number; the Statute requires ſubſcription to the whole num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, which are all of that nature.</p>
               <p n="22">22. Here is the Continent: <hi>All the Articles of Religion,</hi> which we know are <hi>nine and thirty;</hi> the thing contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that is, <hi>only</hi> the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Sacraments;</hi> there is not one excepted, either from this Nature, or from our Subſcriptions: beſides, if we
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57726:13"/> exclude an Article after this manner, we fail in Arithmetick as well as Grammar; and while we have but thirty eight, we cannot be ſaid to read or ſubſcribe the nine and thirty <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="23">23. You intimate, That the <hi>Artcile</hi> touching the Book of <hi>Conſecration</hi> is no Doctrine of <hi>Faith,</hi> or of the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="24">24. I anſwer firſt, This is only to quarrel with the fitneſs of the explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the Parliament that gave it us, who, ſurely, did ill to tell us; That <hi>all</hi> theſe Articles contain only ſuch Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine as is not to be found in <hi>one</hi> of them: But the Grammatical conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the words will ſtand well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and carry it, That all the <hi>thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty nine Articles</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> contain on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch Doctrine, in the judgment of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arliament that made that Statute, unleſs you can ſhew us the exception of any one of thoſe Articles, made by the ſame Authority, either in <hi>this</hi> or ſome other <hi>Law. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hi Lex non diſtinguit,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="25">25. Beſides, Who knows not that the Doctrine of Diſcipline, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:57726:13"/> and Worſhip, and the Doctrine of <hi>Impoſition of hands</hi> and <hi>Ordination</hi> is to be believed, and in a large ſence is a Doctrine of <hi>Faith;</hi> in which ſence, if the <hi>thirty nine Articles</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> are ſaid by the Statute to contain <hi>only</hi> the Doctrine of <hi>Faith,</hi> and of the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="26">26. However the Article touching the Doctrine of <hi>Ordination</hi> be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood to be a Doctrine of <hi>Faith,</hi> or not, it matters nothing as to our queſtion, or to the unreſerved ſubſcriptions of moſt of the Miniſters to all the nine and thirty Articles, of which this is one.</p>
               <p n="27">27. Laſtly, you ſay, That the <hi>form of ſubſeription</hi> required in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, by the new Statute of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> is ſuch as was never required by Law before, this requiring an <hi>unfeigned af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and Conſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="28">28. But give me leave to ask you, Did you not ſubſcribe to the <hi>thirty nine Articles,</hi> before, <hi>ex animo?</hi> And were you not required ſo to do? Now what act of your Mind was exerciſed in that your ſubſcription, if you did not <hi>aſſent?</hi> And if you did aſſent, did you not aſſent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57726:14"/> 
                  <hi>unfeignedly,</hi> but hypocritically? Or if you did aſſent unfeignedly, did you not <hi>conſent</hi> alſo thereunto?</p>
               <p n="29">29. I need not tell you, that very learned men judg, that there is very little or no difference betwixt <hi>Adſentire</hi> and <hi>Conſentire;</hi> and, doubtleſs, if the object of both be the uſe of things, as it is in the preſent Caſe, they are all one, though, if there ſeem any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between them, <hi>aſſent</hi> hath the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, <hi>conſent</hi> ſeeming, of the two, to be the <hi>weaker,</hi> and the leſs free ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of our ſelves.</p>
               <p n="30">30. Therefore, let the Statute it ſelf decide the difference, <hi>viz.</hi> that of 13 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 12. which hath rendred the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, <hi>ex animo,</hi> by the very term in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, an <hi>unfeigned aſſent,</hi> clearly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating, That all that have ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the <hi>thirty nine Articles ex animo,</hi> have already given to the form and manner of Mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng, Ordaining, and Conſecrating Biſhops, Prieſts, and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, their <hi>unfeigned aſſent,</hi> and, by conſequence, their <hi>conſent</hi> too, and need not, without ſome other reaſon to the contrary, ſcruple to do it again.</p>
               <p n="31">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:57726:14"/>31. But I haſten to the Caſe ariſing from the firſt part of this firſt Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which concerns the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> againſt which you grant, that there li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the greateſt burthen of exception.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Touching the Book of Common-Prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 1.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. WE come now to review the ſecond Caſe, ariſing from this firſt Declaration, which is this.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whether it be lawful to declare our unfeigned aſſent and conſent to all and every thing contained and preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in and by the Book Entituled, <hi>The Book of Common Prayer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. This I affirm, and in the defence of my Aſſertion, <hi>ſtill</hi> ſtand upon my former ground, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>ſuppoſition,</hi> that I deal with perſons that intended to have <hi>conformed,</hi> had not theſe <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations</hi> been required.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. To this you alſo encourage me
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:57726:15"/> while you ſay, that though you <hi>could</hi> have conformed, yet you <hi>cannot</hi> make and ſubſcribe this Declaration.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. But, my dear brethren, give me leave to demand once more, <hi>What hath hindred you?</hi> cannot you <hi>aſsent</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> to <hi>that</hi> which your ſelves can pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice? or cannot you do it unfeignedly? or cannot you declare ſo much?</p>
                  <p n="5">5. You ſay, I tell you the <hi>Object</hi> of our Aſſent and Conſent is not the <hi>words</hi> but <hi>things:</hi> There are ſeveral Expreſſions, which though we could ſafely read, yet we do not ſo heartily approve them, as we ſeem to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: not every thing, as there expreſſed, but every thing contained in the Expreſſions muſt have our <hi>Aſſent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. Here pardon me, if I fear you were ſomwhat in haſte, when you took your <hi>ſurvey</hi> by <hi>Review;</hi> you will find you have (may I ſay, too careleſly) ſhuffled in an <hi>Objection</hi> I made betwixt the parts of my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to it: and ſo force me to ſpeak your own ſence, or indeed Non-ſence.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. But, I am about <hi>things</hi> and not
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:57726:15"/> 
                     <hi>words,</hi> though I cannot but note, that all you ſay about your wordy <hi>things</hi> are <hi>words</hi> that ſignifie <hi>nothing</hi> as to your <hi>own Caſe,</hi> who ſay you could Conform to the book of Common Prayer, and conſequently, I hope, read the words thereof with your <hi>unfeigned aſſent and conſent</hi> to the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> of the <hi>ſame.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. This was the cloſe of my former Anſwer to the <hi>Objection</hi> propoſed; and though you could not but think your ſelves <hi>obliged</hi> thereunto, yet you have taken no <hi>notice</hi> of it in your ſurvey at all.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. But, at laſt, you come home and object, that there are <hi>ſome things</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Expreſſions, which you cannot aſſent and conſent unto: but what are they?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:57726:16"/>
                  <head>SECT. 2. Of, <hi>let us beſeech him, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. FIrſt you are ſcandalized at that alteration in the <hi>Abſolution,</hi> Wherefore <hi>we beſeech him,</hi> is now ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, wherefore <hi>let us beſeech him to grant us true Repentance,</hi> &amp;c. It now ſeemeth (you ſay) to be an <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative Sacerdotal Abſolution.</hi> But tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if you <hi>think</hi> again, I am very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident you will change your mind, and judge, with me, that as the words are now altered, they do not look ſo like an <hi>Authoritative Sacerdotal Abſolution,</hi> as they did before.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Beſides, when you have well conſidered, that we have conſtant and daily need to beg <hi>pardon</hi> and mercy, and to receive <hi>Abſolution,</hi> for ſafety and Comfort, from the Word of God: I believe you will not much object a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the declaring the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>mercy</hi> to the penitent by the Miniſter of the ſame; though it <hi>ſhould</hi> have been (as
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57726:16"/> now it is not) made a ſtanding piece of ſolemn worſhip in every approach to God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. But you add, if it be not a form of <hi>Authoritative Abſolution,</hi> yet it is a <hi>Miniſterial Exhortation</hi> of the people. But what then? methinks that ſhould paſs well enough with <hi>us;</hi> it being not refuſed, but conſtantly practiſed in <hi>Scotland</hi> it ſelf; yea it is the ſubſtance of all our Sermons.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. But then you intimate, that the <hi>Amen</hi> of the people thereto ſubjoyned, is impertinent.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Pray, why <hi>impertinent,</hi> ſubjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to an <hi>Exhortation,</hi> more then to the <hi>Creed,</hi> a Confeſſion of our Faith; or the <hi>Denuntiation of the Curſes?</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 27.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let us not diſcourage the people to declare their <hi>unfeigned aſſent and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> to an Exhortation to their <hi>duty,</hi> though it be with an <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. But this, you hint, you ſtick not at. Ah, what then? You add, we are to be convinced, <hi>that the Words of the Lords Prayer are the Neceſſary and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lawful Petition for pardon of ſin in every approach to God;</hi> yet that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57726:17"/> ſubjoyned.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Pray reflect a little upon theſe words of yours, and I hope you will pardon me. if I ſay you miſtake.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. What can the force of theſe words be, but that if you aſſent to the book of <hi>Common-prayer,</hi> you muſt aſſent to <hi>that</hi> of which you are yet to be convinced; <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>the Lords Prayer is the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and only lawful Petition for pardon of ſin in every approach.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. Firſt, I deſire you to conſider, upon <hi>what occaſion</hi> you utter <hi>this:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Lords Prayer is ſubjoyned to the Exhortation in the Abſolution. Now, if you obſerve, you will find, we are not here exhorted to pray for <hi>pardon</hi> expreſly and directly, but for true <hi>Repentance,</hi> acceptance of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Duties,</hi> the holy <hi>Spirit,</hi> a <hi>holy</hi> Life, and <hi>Eternal</hi> Joy; as the words of the Exhortation plainly import.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Again, if this be granted to be a Miniſterial <hi>Exhortation;</hi> to pray for pardon of ſin, how doth it follow that the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> is accounted the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and only lawful Petition for this mercy in every approach to God?
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57726:17"/> is the <hi>Abſolution</hi> in every approach to God? Or if the Lords Prayer be, muſt it therefore be accounted the <hi>only law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful petition</hi> of pardon of ſin?</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Laſtly, all the reaſon you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs, to inforce this Concluſion, is in your laſt words [that the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> is conſtantly ſubjoyned;] but that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is <hi>no reaſon</hi> at all: for though it be <hi>conſtantly,</hi> it is not <hi>only</hi> enjoyned as a Petition for pardon of ſin; and therefore, you cannot ſay that it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted or enjoyned as the <hi>only lawful Petition</hi> for that end, and conſequently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>our Objection vaniſheth.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Can it be affirmed by any that converſe with the <hi>Book</hi> of <hi>Common-prayer,</hi> that if we do aſſent unto it, we aſſent that the Lords Prayer is the <hi>only lawful P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tition</hi> for <hi>pardon</hi> of ſin, while we find ſo frequent and ſo various forms to <hi>that</hi> purpoſe, even from the <hi>begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> to the <hi>end</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Book</hi> beſides that of the <hi>Lords Prayer?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="13">13. What do thoſe words in the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> ſignifie? But <hi>thou O Lord, have mercy upon us miſerable offenders; ſpare thou them that confeſs their faults,</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:57726:18"/> 
                     <hi>Reſtore thou them that be penitent?</hi> How often do we meet with, <hi>Lord have mercy upon us,</hi> have mercy upon'u <hi>miſerable ſinners.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="14">14. Again, more expreſly, <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not Lord our offences, nor the offence of our forefathers, neither take tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> vengeance of our ſins; Deal not thou with us after our ſins, nor reward us af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our iniquities; mercifully forgive the ſins of thy people,</hi> and abundance more in the Office of <hi>Communion,</hi> the viſitation of the <hi>Sick, Commination;</hi> and indeed, either more expreſly, or implicitely, in every approach to God by the book of Common Prayer, we have other Petitions of pardon of ſin, beſides the words of the Lords Prayer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p n="13">13. Thus we ſee, that wiſe and good men may have cauſe to <hi>joyn with us,</hi> in the words of our Liturgy, that it <hi>may pleaſe thee to forgive us all our ſins, negligences, and ignorances.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:57726:18"/>
                  <head>SECT. 3. <hi>Of popular Reſponds.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. SEcondly, you complain that you cannot <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> to the word [Anſwer] and the other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections for popular Reſponds; for theſe are, you ſay, in Mr. <hi>Croftons Dialect,</hi> Repugnant to the <hi>Apoſtles Rule, Let all things be done decently and in Order.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. My <hi>dear brethren,</hi> pray conſider, that though theſe things ſeem ſo <hi>direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> repugnant to the Apoſtles rule of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and order with <hi>you</hi> &amp; Mr. <hi>Crofton;</hi> yet they did not ſeem ſo, to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Governours. What Order can be prudently expected in <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> if every private ſpirit ſhould be <hi>Judge</hi> thereof; and accordingly, <hi>Act</hi> or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in <hi>publick Adminiſtrations?</hi> Yea, I dare in <hi>this</hi> thing appeal to your ſelves; were you in the place of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, durſt you <hi>truſt</hi> the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>all</hi> indifferent things, and all external Circumſtances about Gods Worſhip, to every private Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? I am ſure the Apoſtles did not.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:57726:19"/>3. However, you ſay in your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, that you have admitted and could admit many <hi>inexpediencies</hi> for the <hi>liberty of your Miniſtry.</hi> Now I am confident you will not ſay theſe are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then <hi>inexpediencies</hi> in your own judgments; and the reaſon of this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence your ſelves have given me, <hi>page</hi> 15. where, referring to theſe things, you ſay, you could <hi>ſubmiſſively bear theſe things;</hi> which cannot be underſtood, but in the uſe of them, and conformity to them: Now how you can admit <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expediencies</hi> in your practice, and bear with theſe things, and yet not give ſome aſſent and conſent thereunto, I am ſtill to learn, eſpecially that they are <hi>indifferent,</hi> and not <hi>ſimply ſinful,</hi> though perhaps <hi>inexpedient</hi> in your opinion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. 4. <hi>Of the Holy Table.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. AGain, you are offended at the word <hi>[Holy]</hi> as an <hi>Adjunct</hi> to <hi>Table,</hi> frequent in this Book; for you
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:57726:19"/> 
                     <hi>know no holineſs of Places or Inſtruments under the Goſpel.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. For anſwer hereunto, pray ask your ſelves in what ſence <hi>Places</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments</hi> might be ſaid to be <hi>holy</hi> in the time of the <hi>Law,</hi> that the <hi>Goſpel</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation cannot bear, as you ſeem to intimate.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Nay rather, is not that holineſs that was reſtrained to ſome places and ſome things in the time of the <hi>Law,</hi> now ſpread, by the coming of Chriſt, over all places and all things; <hi>To the pure all things are pure. What God hath ſanctified, call not thou common or unclean.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. So that any place or any thing that is capable of uſe, in order to <hi>Gods Service,</hi> by this grace of the Goſpel we have liberty to uſe it, and to <hi>ſet it apart</hi> for that peculiar uſe about the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God; as this publick houſe and not another, this particular Table and not another, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. This, I know, neither you nor M. <hi>Crofton</hi> will ſcruple at; and this granted, you muſt needs confeſs that the exception againſt the word <hi>Holy,</hi> as given to the <hi>Table,</hi> is only a ſtrife a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:57726:20"/> a word; for indeed you allow the thing, and all the thing which this word, as applied to the <hi>Table,</hi> intends to ſignifie.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Neither can you reply, that it is improper to call a Table, in this ſence, <hi>Holy;</hi> ſeeing you may eaſily know, the Church doth not intend by calling the Table <hi>Holy,</hi> a <hi>proper</hi> but a <hi>figurative</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, or a holineſs not <hi>inherent</hi> in the thing, but <hi>predicated</hi> of it, with reſpect to the <hi>end</hi> and <hi>uſe</hi> for which it is ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part; which diſtinction (I need not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form you) hath undeniable ground in Scripture.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Yet, ſeeing you ſay you know no holineſs of places under the Goſpel, give me leave to remember you of the <hi>Holieſt of all, Heb.</hi> 9. 3. and that peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar to the Goſpel-ſtate; the Holy Ghoſt ſignifying that the way into the <hi>Holieſt of all was not yet made manifeſt, while the firſt Tabernacle</hi> was yet ſtanding, <hi>v.</hi> 8.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Yea, this ſeems to be a place to be entred into even in this life. <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving therefore boldneſs to enter into the Holieſt by a new and living way</hi>—<hi>And having a High Prieſt over the Houſe of</hi>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:57726:20"/> 
                     <hi>God. Let us draw near with a true heart</hi>—not <hi>forſaking the aſsembling</hi> of ourſelves together, as the manner of ſome is, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 19 to 26. To this the <hi>Holy Citie</hi> anſwereth, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11. 2. &amp; 21. 2. &amp; 22. 9.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. But I am afraid of being miſtak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en; let me therefore have leave to add, that the end of my alledging theſe <hi>Scriptures</hi> is only to let you know, that <hi>Holineſs</hi> is attributed to places un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> Contenting my ſelf with my former <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>Objection,</hi> without any ſtrict Application of the Scriptures pointed at to that end and purpoſe.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Howbeit, if you acknowledge, as I know you do, with the Apoſtle, that there is <hi>ſuch a thing</hi> as <hi>Sacriledge</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> under the Goſpel; you may eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade your ſelves that ſome <hi>things</hi> may warrantably bear the <hi>Attribute</hi> of <hi>Holy,</hi> even under the Goſpel: for what is Sacriledge? <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; it unqueſtionably imports, that either the <hi>things</hi> that are <hi>ſtoln,</hi> or the place out of which they are ſtoln, are called <hi>Holy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">11. In a ſtrict ſence, <hi>Sacriledge</hi> is a
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:57726:21"/> 
                     <hi>Robbing</hi> or ſtealing things out of the <hi>Church,</hi> or any <hi>Holy</hi> or Conſecrated place; and then <hi>Sacrum in Sacrilegium, &amp;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>in</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſignifies the <hi>Church;</hi> which very words carry <hi>Conſecration</hi> or <hi>Holineſs</hi> in them. For <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is properly <hi>quid ſacrum:</hi> As <hi>ſacrum</hi> is that which Is <hi>Holy,</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> is therefore cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>both,</hi> becauſe it is <hi>Holy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">12. Yet in very <hi>uſual,</hi> and general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly allowed ſpeaking, <hi>Sacriledge</hi> is a larger <hi>Notion,</hi> and intends any <hi>ſpoiling</hi> or <hi>alienating</hi> any thing devoted or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to God in order to his Service. Thus the <hi>things</hi> are called <hi>Holy,</hi> that are given to an <hi>Holy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe,</hi> or the ſervice of the <hi>Holy God,</hi> and ſeparated from common uſe to that ſpecial purpoſe; and he that ſteals and ſpoils the <hi>Church</hi> of the ſame, is <hi>Sacrilegius,</hi> or one that <hi>Robs</hi> God, and commits Sacriledge.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Thus <hi>Churches, Lands, Table, Chalice, Cup,</hi> may be ſaid to be <hi>Holy;</hi> not in themſelves, but their end and uſe. Therefore, to dedicate a thing after this manner, is by the <hi>Latines</hi> called <hi>Sacrare,</hi> by the <hi>Greeks</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and may in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> I think without any
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:57726:21"/> juſt offence, if well underſtood, be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by <hi>Conſecrating</hi> or making <hi>Holy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="14">14. I am ſure the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> word is, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; and that hath <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum</hi> in it, which from the <hi>Caldie</hi> is rendred <hi>diripis aedem ſacram,</hi> making an <hi>houſe Holy.</hi> The <hi>Syriac, furaberis vaſa Templi,</hi> intimating that either the <hi>Temple</hi> or the <hi>Veſſels</hi> thereof, or <hi>both,</hi> are <hi>Holy.</hi> The <hi>Aethiopic. Expilus Domum Dei?</hi> calling the place of Worſhip, the <hi>Houſe of God,</hi> and conſequently, <hi>Holy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="15">15. What rema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ins, but that you no longer ſtartle at the <hi>Holy Table</hi> which you know is ſet apart for the <hi>Supper</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> to bear the <hi>Cup</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> to ſerve the <hi>Communion</hi> of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and the <hi>Holy</hi> Communion, or the Communion of <hi>Saints.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:57726:22"/>
                  <head>SECT 5. Of <hi>the old Tranſlation of the Pſalms.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. AS to your <hi>Exceptions</hi> to the <hi>old</hi> Tranſlation of the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and the <hi>pointing of it,</hi> they are not ſtrengthned with any proof at all; nor ſo much as an <hi>Inſtance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. It yet lies on you to evince that <hi>this Tranſlation</hi> is corrupt, as you have aſſerted, that the <hi>pointing</hi> makes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Non-ſenſe, (which indeed ſerves not the ſence at all, but only the <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick)</hi> that it varieth the <hi>Text</hi> from the <hi>Original,</hi> yea, from <hi>Truth</hi> it ſelf.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. I confeſs, that ſuch ſtrange excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions have been thrown againſt it here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, by the old Non-conformiſts; but, I ſuppoſe, you know they never wanted Anſwers.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Yoy add the corrupt Tranſlation of the <hi>fourth Commandment,</hi> where in the cloſe of it, the <hi>ſeventh</hi> day is put for the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. But though I do not vindicate
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:57726:22"/> this <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> yet I cannot but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the extream emptineſs of this <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</hi> Was not the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day then the ſeventh day? It is ſaid, <hi>God reſted the ſeventh day, and bleſſed the Sabbath:</hi> Yea, was not the ſeventh day the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> day? it is alſo ſaid, <hi>the ſeventh day is the Sabbath of the Lord thy God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. Beſides the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bic,</hi> and the <hi>Syriac,</hi> do all agree in the ſame <hi>Rendition.</hi> with our own <hi>Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> ſo that if it be ſo groſs an errour as you pretend, it is a very old one. But indeed, whether the not altering of the word, were an overfight in the Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miners, or not, the ſence muſt needs be yielded by you to be the ſame either way.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. However, here again, I muſt needs remember you; that you could ſubmiſſively bear theſe things; that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, by conforming to uſe them as Miniſters; and that this your <hi>bearing</hi> of them doth undeniably ſuppoſe <hi>ſuch</hi> an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and Conſent unto them as the Law requires; which I doubt not to Evidence in its due place.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:57726:23"/>
                  <head>SECT. 6. <hi>Of the Salvation of Infants.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. I Am now arrived at the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of your exceptions of this <hi>kind;</hi> and that is taken from thoſe words in the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> touching the <hi>Salvation of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants. It is certain by the Word of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that Children being baptized, dying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they commit Actual ſin, are undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly ſaved.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. You ſay you can Chriſtianly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the <hi>Regenerating Nature and Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy of Baptiſm:</hi> but, that the <hi>undoubted Salvation of all baptized infants dying before they commit Actual Sin, is certain by the Scriptures you ſay you cannot ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. But truly, my brother; I cannot ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, that <hi>So much</hi> is required of you: And therefore I muſt be bold to minde you that the univerſal Note [All] is of your own inſerting. It is not ſaid <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll Children,</hi> but <hi>Children.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. It is an <hi>indifinite Propoſition;</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it is a <hi>Propoſition,</hi> and conſequently, neither
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:57726:23"/> 
                     <hi>Rubrick</hi> for direction, nor any part of <hi>Adminiſtration,</hi> it is not of a practicable Nature; and I humbly conceive, it will appear anon, we are not required by the <hi>Act</hi> to ſubſcribe to it; the <hi>Act</hi> makes the <hi>Object</hi> of our <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> in the Declaration, to the uſe of the things contained and preſcribed in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Again, as it is an <hi>Indefinite Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,</hi> I conceive you need not ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple it, ſeeing you allow, and believe with a <hi>Chriſtian belief,</hi> the Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting nature, uſe and efficacy, of <hi>Baptiſm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. For upon this belief, we muſt agree thus far: that this <hi>Efficacy of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme</hi> hath its Effects upon ſome of its <hi>Subject;</hi> and if this belief be grounded upon the <hi>Word</hi> of God, then ſo much is certain from the <hi>Word</hi> of God, that ſome Children being <hi>Regenerated,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> put in a ſtate of <hi>Salvation</hi> by Baptiſmes and therefore, dying before they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit <hi>Actual ſin</hi> are undoubtedly ſaved.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. But you reply, it is not ſaid, ſome <hi>Children,</hi> but that is <hi>Children, all</hi> Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. I therefore proceed upon <hi>this</hi>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:57726:24"/> 
                     <hi>Foundation</hi> to inquire, whether the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition</hi> in Controverſie be to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in a Univerſal ſence, or <hi>not.</hi> This is indeed the <hi>Queſtion;</hi> yet by my conſent, you have liberty to <hi>Anſwer</hi> it your ſelves.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. For firſt, if this Propoſition be to be underſtood Univerſally as to <hi>all</hi> ſuch Children that are mentioned in it, the matter of it muſt be neceſſary. For the <hi>form</hi> of the Propoſition is indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, and an indefinite Propoſition is not equipollent with an Univerſal, but in <hi>Materiâ Neceſſariâ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10. You have yet your choice to ſay, whether the <hi>Matter</hi> of this Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition be neceſſary or <hi>not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">11. If you ſay the <hi>Matter</hi> of it is not neceſſary, then the meaning of the Propoſition is not Univerſal, and the difficulty is over, ſeeing it is agreed, that <hi>Baptiſme is regenerating,</hi> and <hi>ſome ſuch Children</hi> are ſaved. For if ſome <hi>Children,</hi> then <hi>Children, thus dying, are ſaved;</hi> and that is ſufficient, if the <hi>Matter</hi> be not neceſſary; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Propoſition not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood Univerſally.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:57726:24"/>12. Again, if you urge that the matter of this indefinite <hi>Propoſition</hi> is neceſſary; then I am content you conclude it <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally,</hi> &amp; extend it to <hi>all</hi> ſuch children.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. For what is the matter of the <hi>preſent propoſition,</hi> but the <hi>ſalvation of baptized Children; dying before they commit actual ſin.</hi> Now this is granted to be true of ſome, elſe the Promiſe is of none effect to the Children, and Baptiſme of no efficacy; and if it be ſaid to be neceſſary, it muſt be true of <hi>all;</hi> and you need not doubt to <hi>Aſſent</hi> unto it in a <hi>univerſal</hi> Propoſition.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Thus <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Text ſaith, <hi>Came into the world to ſave ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</hi> This is a true Propoſition, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the matter be neceſſary or not; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it it is <hi>certain</hi> that he came into the world to <hi>ſave ſome ſinners.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="15">15. For if the matter be neceſſary, then it is Univerſally true, if not <hi>neceſsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> then it is <hi>indefinitely true;</hi> if he came with a purpoſe to ſave <hi>all,</hi> he came to ſave <hi>ſinners:</hi> and if he came <hi>not</hi> with a purpoſe to ſave <hi>all,</hi> yet he came to ſave ſome <hi>ſinners;</hi> and therefore <hi>ſinners.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="16">16. Once more, that <hi>Baptiſme is for the Remiſſion of ſins,</hi> is a certain Truth,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:57726:25"/> or an undoubted propoſition, ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Scripture, be <hi>Baptized for</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Acts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>the Remiſſion of ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="17">17. This is a Propoſition of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definite Nature; if the matter of it be neceſſary, it is true, as I have ſaid, U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally; (where its efficacy is not impeded by the <hi>incapacity</hi> of the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>)</hi> as it is not in Children:) but if the matter be not neceſſary, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is ſtill true, that is, indefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. To conclude, either <hi>all</hi> ſuch <hi>Children</hi> are ſaved, or <hi>ſome</hi> only; in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, the Propoſition being but indefinite is true; if all ſuch Children are ſaved, then the Matter is neceſſary, and the Propoſition equipollent with an Univerſal Propoſition: if <hi>ſome</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, then the Matter is not neceſſary; and conſequently, there is no neceſſity, yea, no liberty left us, to ſtretch the Propoſition which is indefinite, both in its <hi>Form</hi> and <hi>Matter,</hi> unto an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal ſignification.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:57726:25"/>
                  <head>SECT. 7. Of <hi>Aſſent and Conſent unfeigned.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p n="1">1. HAving diſpatcht your excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions againſt the <hi>Objects</hi> of your <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> required by the <hi>Act. viz.</hi> The book of <hi>Ordination,</hi> and the book of <hi>Common-Prayer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. We proceed to review theſe <hi>Acts</hi> themſelves, this unfeigned <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent;</hi> upon which a greater ſtreſs of Controverſie yet remains.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. An <hi>Objection</hi> that I propoſed and Anſwered in my laſt book, ſeemed, if not to create, yet to provoke and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much to heighten this part of the quarrel.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The <hi>Objection</hi> that I propoſed, was this: I ſuppoſe it might be ſaid by ſome, that though we could uſe the things, it is only for Peace ſake, and in Obedience to Authority; not that we would <hi>chooſe</hi> or can abſolutely approve of the things in themſelves.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Hereunto, I anſwered, as you well note, that we may approve a thing abſolutely, or comparatively, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively, and conſequently, ſo give our <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> unto it, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:57726:26"/> that the <hi>Act</hi> cannot be thought ſo ſtrict as to allow of no <hi>Aſſent</hi> or <hi>Conſent</hi> but ſuch as ariſeth from an abſolute ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of the things themſelves, without any other extrinſiek conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, that may move and ſway us to ſuch an Approbation.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The <hi>Act</hi> requires but an unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Aſsent</hi> and <hi>Conſent;</hi> and an unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> may ariſe from ſuch a comparative Approbation, as a man may unfeignedly Aſſent and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to his Childs Marriage, though he like not the Match very well, for the avoiding of ſome greater inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies that otherwiſe might happen.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. I further obſerved, that to <hi>interpret</hi> the <hi>Act</hi> into ſuch an abſolute approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is againſt charity to our ſelves and our <hi>Governours,</hi> and againſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reaſon; ſeeing it is a moral im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibility, that <hi>all</hi> men ſhould be <hi>exactly</hi> of <hi>one minde</hi> in <hi>ſo many</hi> particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars required of us; ſeeing alſo the <hi>grounds</hi> of this Aſſent and Conſent are not <hi>ſpecified in the Act,</hi> but left to our ſelves; and laſtly, ſeeing that the <hi>very Act it ſelf</hi> brings motives with it to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o Conformity, which would
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:57726:26"/> ſignifie <hi>nothing,</hi> if <hi>no conſideration</hi> of the Caſe; beſides, the <hi>abſolute goodneſs</hi> of the things themſelves is allowed any force to prevail upon us.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. I therefore conclude, that we are left <hi>at liberty</hi> by the ſaid <hi>Act,</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the Conſequences of <hi>obedience</hi> with thoſe of <hi>dibedience,</hi> and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly to approve <hi>ſo</hi> and <hi>declare,</hi> or not.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Now let us examine <hi>what you ſay to theſe</hi> things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To my argument from <hi>charity,</hi> you anſwer it, only, with leſs <hi>Charity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. To my augment, that the <hi>grounds of Aſſent and Conſent</hi> are not <hi>ſpecified in the Act,</hi> but left to our ſelves you anſwer <hi>nothing,</hi> becauſe you <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take</hi> it.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. You obſerve well, that I ſay, the grounds of this <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> are not <hi>ſpecified</hi> in the <hi>Act,</hi> But how ſtrangely do you Comment upon it?</p>
                  <p n="11">11. If <hi>by ground</hi> (ſay you) I mean the <hi>reaſons inducing the Legiſlators to require ſuch an Aſſent and Conſent</hi> you muſt be bold to <hi>deny</hi> what I affirm. Then you ſhew the <hi>grounds</hi> in the <hi>Act,</hi> for <hi>enjoyning ſuch a declaration</hi> of Aſſent and Conſent: And this is <hi>all</hi> you <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:57726:27"/>12. Now had I meant as you <hi>ſuppoſe,</hi> I confeſs you had <hi>anſwered</hi> me. But if my <hi>words</hi> could not ſignifie any ſuch <hi>thing,</hi> as upon <hi>review</hi> you will be eaſily convinced, you have anſwer'd <hi>your ſelves,</hi> and not <hi>me</hi> at all.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Pray then Conſider, is there not a difference betwixt the <hi>grounds</hi> of <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and Conſent,</hi> and the <hi>grounds</hi> of the Governours to <hi>enjoyn a declaration of Aſſent and Conſent?</hi> could the <hi>ſcope</hi> of my argument, or the very words of my propoſition, intend the latter, or not the former?</p>
                  <p n="14">14. The <hi>grounds</hi> of <hi>enjoyning</hi> ſuch a declaration are in the <hi>Legiſlators;</hi> and are the <hi>grounds</hi> of the <hi>Act requiring:</hi> theſe, indeed, are ſpecified in the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>uniformity:</hi> But the <hi>grounds</hi> of <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent,</hi> or of <hi>declaring</hi> the ſame, are in the <hi>Subjects;</hi> and are <hi>properly</hi> the <hi>grounds</hi> of <hi>obedience</hi> to that <hi>Act;</hi> which, I muſt ſtill ſay, are not at all ſpecified in it.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. To my other argument, taken from the motives which the <hi>Act</hi> it ſelf affords us, you only ſay, that <hi>ſuch</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, as the <hi>avoiding a ſevere penalty,</hi> a legal <hi>opportunity</hi> of ſerving the <hi>Church;</hi>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:57726:27"/> not ſhewing our ſelves croſſe to autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, &amp;c. are bad inducements to an unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. But, upon ſecond thoughts, I cannot believe you will <hi>maintain</hi> the <hi>Quarrel</hi> with ſuch motives as theſe; which have, doubtleſs, a <hi>divine ſanction;</hi> what more familiar, with the <hi>Spirit</hi> of Scripture, then to uſe ſuch <hi>Topicks</hi> of <hi>wrath, threats, curſes, death,</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> it ſelf, to diſſwade from <hi>ſin,</hi> and to <hi>move</hi> towards <hi>Heaven;</hi> and yet, I hope, the <hi>Aſſent and Conſent, wrought</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, is not alwayes <hi>feigned,</hi> or alwayes a <hi>faint unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="17">17. Neither, can I believe, that you are <hi>tenacious</hi> in this; becauſe you ſay <hi>it might ſomwhat ſatisfie us, if we had aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance from our Legiſlators that ſuch a comparative approbation would ſatisfy the Law.</hi> For I conclude from hence, that what ever you ſay, there is not, even in your apprehenſions, <hi>any inconſiſtency or contradiction</hi> betwixt ſuch a <hi>comparative approbation</hi> and an <hi>unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent.</hi> Though I can ſee no reaſon, in the world, why the Legiſlators ſhould expreſly declare ſo much.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. We have the intention of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:57726:28"/> 
                     <hi>Act,</hi> and why ſhould we further trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble our ſelves about the intention of the makers of it: The <hi>Act</hi> intends, and therefore requires uniformity, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereunto; conformity, and ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thereof, by this <hi>declaration</hi> of an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Aſſent and Conſent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="19">19. So that, it is the intention of our Governours, that we ſhould aſſure them, as much as in us lies, as to <hi>uniformity</hi> in practice, by giving our <hi>unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; it is not ſaid upon an abſolute or upon a comparative approbation: If it be unfeigned, that is the <hi>very thing required,</hi> and therefore, intended. Then the great <hi>Queſtion</hi> is, that which is indeed <hi>beyond all queſtion. viz.</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we may be <hi>drawn</hi> to give <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent,</hi> and that <hi>unfeignedly,</hi> from <hi>other conſiderations</hi> beſides the <hi>very good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of the <hi>thing it ſelf, abſolutely,</hi> and in it ſelf alone, conſidered.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. If it be granted, as it cannot be queſtioned, then our Governours have already <hi>declared,</hi> that ſuch a compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive approbation doth ſatisfie the Law.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. For if there be an <hi>univerſal agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in the worſhip of God, though
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:57726:28"/> upon <hi>differing motives,</hi> and uniformity be effected, though not from an <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act unanimity</hi> in every particular reaſon or <hi>ground</hi> thereof, the <hi>Law</hi> hath its end <hi>quoad executionem,</hi> which, I conceive, is the beſt meaſure of its end <hi>quoad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionem,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="22">22. I ſay, indeed, had the word [Free] been uſed in the place of <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned,</hi> there had been were <hi>colour</hi> of <hi>objection.</hi> And for this you take me up, and learn me, that <hi>Freedom is eſſential to unfeigned.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="23">23. But what then? might there not be <hi>more colour</hi> of objection, if not more <hi>reality?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="24">24 I thought, I might have bin eaſily underſtood according to that <hi>vulgar</hi> uſe of the word <hi>free,</hi> wherein the <hi>objectors uſed,</hi> and I <hi>interpreted</hi> it. viz. When we do <hi>chooſe a thing of our own accord,</hi> and Aſſent and Conſent unt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it <hi>for it ſelf,</hi> without any further <hi>inducement</hi> thereunto from the <hi>laws enjoyning</hi> it.</p>
                  <p n="25">25. Moreover, take <hi>Freedom</hi> in its <hi>ſtrict</hi> and proper ſence, as <hi>moraliſts</hi> uſe it and doubtleſs, it is as <hi>Eſſential</hi> to <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> as it is to <hi>unfeigned;</hi> yea <hi>unfeignedneſs</hi> is as <hi>Eſſential</hi> to <hi>Aſſent,</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:57726:29"/> and <hi>Conſent,</hi> as Freedome is to <hi>unfeign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;</hi> and then what have you gained by this interruption?</p>
                  <p n="26">26. Therefore unfeigned, the word ſo much ſtuck at, that bears the very burthen of general complaint, gives on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the colour, nothing of the truth of the weakeſt objection.</p>
                  <p n="27">27. For it really adds nothing to Aſſent or Conſent, or to the declaration at all for all; Aſſent and Conſent, as ſuch, is both unfeigned and free. And tis a plain contradiction, to ſay a feigned, Aſſent and Conſent; we may indeed, make a feigned Declaration of our Aſſent and Conſent, but we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not declare a feign'd Aſſent or Conſent; for there is no ſuch thing.</p>
                  <p n="28">28. What remains, but that we lift out <hi>foot</hi> over the word unfeigned, and <hi>ſtumble</hi> no longer at it; but proceed to Aſſent and Conſent, which ever carry the thing of <hi>unfeignedneſs</hi> with them. So that, if we can truly Aſſent and Conſent, we do it unfeignedly. And if we do Aſſent and Conſent, unfeignedly, let the grounds and motives be what they will, the Law is ſatisfied, and ſo may we.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:57726:29"/>
                  <head>SECT. 8. <hi>Of the phraſe in the Act, [the uſe of all things,</hi> &amp;c.]</head>
                  <p n="1">1. BUt I humbly conceive the, mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is yet more eaſie to our Affent and Conſent, if it be confide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not in its ſpeculative but practical capacity; or with reſpect to Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, and our uſe thereof in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, as the <hi>Act moſt plainly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth</hi> us to do.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Indeed, if you demand, what we muſt yield our unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent unto; the declaration tells you, <hi>to all and every thing contained and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in the Book of Common-prayer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. But if you again demand, in what reſpect, or after what manner, you muſt Aſſent &amp; Conſent to the ſame; The <hi>Act</hi> interprets as they are practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally confidered, or with reſpect to their uſe, in order to publick uniformity in the worſhip of God.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Therefore the words immediately foregoing this declaration, I have noted, are theſe; every Miniſter ſhall <hi>declare his unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent, to the uſe of all things in the ſaid Book contained,</hi>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:57726:30"/> and <hi>preſcribed in theſe words,</hi> and no otherwiſe they are the words of this <hi>Declaration.</hi> It is further to be obſerved, that whereſoever this <hi>Act</hi> doth any time mention the ſaid <hi>Declaration,</hi> it puts this very meaning upon it; that thereby we are to declare our unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent to the uſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer, and that is <hi>all</hi> is intended by the <hi>words</hi> of this Declaration.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The ſum is this; in theſe words, as the <hi>Act</hi> interprets them, we do but declare our unfeigned Aſſent and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the uſe of <hi>common-Prayer;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever there is an Aſſent and Conſent to the uſe of <hi>common-Prayer,</hi> there is an unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: and where there is a purpoſe to Conforme were not this Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration required, there is doubtleſs an Aſſent and Conſent, yea an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned Aſſent and Conſent to the uſe of Common-prayer, which is all in this <hi>particular,</hi> we are deſired to <hi>declare,</hi> and what yet can hinder us?</p>
                  <p n="6">6. You ſay, that this refers our <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſem</hi> and Conſent to the <hi>uſing Act,</hi> and that only: you cannot ſee, neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed can I ſee how you inſer it from
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:57726:30"/> my words immediatly repeated by your ſelves: <hi>All things with reſpect to their uſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. The <hi>uſing Act,</hi> and a thing with reſpect to its uſe, are not all one; they differ formally: the one is the <hi>Act,</hi> as you expreſs it, the other the <hi>Object</hi> of that <hi>Act,</hi> as I muſt needs intend it; one would think beyond all poſſibility of miſapprehenſion.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Yet, <hi>upon this</hi> miſapprehenſion, you proceed and enlarge your ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove one page, anſwering your own <hi>Suppoſition,</hi> not my <hi>Propoſition</hi> at all.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. I do clearly <hi>grant,</hi> that we do <hi>not</hi> Aſſent and Conſent to the uſe of the things <hi>excluſively</hi> to the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, which <hi>ſounds</hi> to me an impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility in it ſelf, yet we Aſſent and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to theſe things <hi>only;</hi> (I mean, we need do no more) as they are practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable; or as I plainly expreſſed it at firſt, <hi>with reſpect to their uſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10. So that all the <hi>Duſt</hi> you raiſed upon this falſe <hi>ground,</hi> about <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity,</hi> with its ſpurre, Unanimitie is <hi>fallen</hi> to nothing; ſeeing my firſt Expreſſion about it, which your ſelves alſo noted, that alloweth the <hi>Object</hi> of Aſſent, and Conſent, to be <hi>all</hi>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:57726:31"/> 
                     <hi>things</hi> with reſpect to their uſe, carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth both <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> &amp; <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimity</hi> in it.</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Only let me enter this <hi>caveat;</hi> let not <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimity</hi> outſtretch <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity;</hi> while we Aſſent to the uſe of <hi>all things</hi> in the <hi>book,</hi> we aſſent to thoſe things tht are to be uſed, and to no more. 12. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> is reſtrained to the publique <hi>Worſhip</hi> of God; ſo far, a Univerſal agreement therein by Aſſent and Conſent is to be allowed; to be the ſence of the <hi>Law;</hi> that is, to the uſe of <hi>all things</hi> in the <hi>Book</hi> of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer; and to the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as they are <hi>practicable,</hi> or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be <hi>uſed,</hi> or, as before, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their <hi>uſe</hi> in the worſhip of God.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Hence appears the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>two Declarations</hi> eaſily e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. In the firſt, we conſent to the uſe, and the <hi>things</hi> to be uſed: in the Second, we move then Conſent, we promiſe that we our ſelves will <hi>uſe</hi> them, or conform unto them.</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Give me leave to ſubjoyn two <hi>advantages,</hi> which offer themſelves from <hi>this</hi> interpretation, towards a good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodation betwixt us.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. 1. Then if there be any <hi>ſuch</hi>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:57726:31"/> thing found in the <hi>book</hi> of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prayer, as is not of a practical Nature, as a port of a publick <hi>Liturgy,</hi> or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of uſe in publick Worſhip, (and I humbly offer whether <hi>that</hi> touching Children dying Baptized is not <hi>ſuch)</hi> it need not be concerned in our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration or Subſcription.</p>
                  <p n="16">16. 2. Things, with reſpect to their <hi>uſe,</hi> are properly, and more immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to be conſidered, as <hi>fit,</hi> not as <hi>good</hi> in themſelves, but as fit for the ſervices for which they are intended: yea, it is not neceſſary that <hi>this filneſs</hi> be referred to the <hi>things</hi> to be uſed, but rather, the perſon that is to uſe them, and our uſe of them.</p>
                  <p n="17">17. So that, upon the <hi>juſt</hi> weighing of all Circumſtances, if we <hi>can</hi> conſent, that for the avoyding of certain great inconveniences, the <hi>uſe</hi> of theſe things (not <hi>ſinful</hi> in themſelves) is a <hi>thing</hi> to be choſen, that this, Conformity is to be practiſed, we have ſufficient <hi>ground</hi> according to the <hi>Act,</hi> to declare our Aſſent and Conſent thereunto.</p>
                  <p n="18">18. What remains, but that we are yet allowed <hi>thus</hi> to reaſon. Here is ſuch a Declaration required by <hi>Law,</hi> and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:57726:32"/> ſuch a ſevere <hi>Penalty</hi> annexed, for all that diſobey it: though I could rather have <hi>liked</hi> the <hi>book</hi> of Common-prayer, if <hi>ſuch</hi> and <hi>ſuch</hi> things had been alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; yet rather then loſe my <hi>Living,</hi> and therewith all <hi>legal Opportunity</hi> of ſerving the Church, rather then ſhew my ſelf <hi>croſs</hi> and diſobedient to Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in <hi>lawful things,</hi> rather then <hi>Ruine</hi> my ſelf and Family, for a thing indifferent, though in it ſelf I judge it inconvenient; I do <hi>chooſe</hi> to be obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and conformable; and in order thereunto, upon theſe grounds, <hi>I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent unfeignedly to every thing to be conformed unto.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="19">19. Give me leave to add the <hi>Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of others, which you mention not. They ſay, if it had been ſaid that we muſt aſſent to all things prſecribed <hi>only,</hi> it might have ſerved my interpretation well enough; but it is all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, as well as preſcribed, muſt be conſented unto.</p>
                  <p n="20">20. I anſwer, Firſt, it is contained and preſcribed. Not preſcribed and contained; ſo that preſcribed ſeems to bound contained. 2 'tis contained and preſcribed, not, <hi>or</hi> preſcribed; ſo that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:57726:32"/> what is contained, if not alſo preſcribed; we need not give our aſſent unto it: it muſt be both contained and preſcribed.</p>
                  <p n="21">21. But, if there yet remain any <hi>doubt,</hi> about the <hi>legal</hi> meaning of theſe words, the <hi>Act</hi> it ſelf explains it beyond all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute: You ſee in the words before ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that both the words <hi>[Contained</hi> and <hi>Preſcribed]</hi> are referred to the <hi>uſe</hi> of the things: <hi>[to the uſe of all things contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and preſcribed]</hi> ſo that the <hi>Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is nice and verbal only, and thus va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth.</p>
                  <p n="22">22. If you ſhould deſire to have <hi>your own</hi> ſence yet more ſecured; I humbly conceive there would be no offence done to the <hi>law,</hi> if you expreſs your ſelves af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>this manner.</hi> Having read the <hi>Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>Evening</hi> Prayer—according to the <hi>Book</hi> of Common-Prayer, at the times thereby appointed; and being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by the <hi>Act</hi> of Parliament, after <hi>ſuch</hi> reading thereof, openly and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely before the Congregation to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare my unfeigned Aſſent and Conſent to the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of all things in the ſaid book <hi>contained</hi> and <hi>preſcribed,</hi> in theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing <hi>words</hi> and no other; According<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I do declare my unfeigned Aſſent
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:57726:33"/> and Conſent to the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of all things in the ſaid <hi>book</hi> contained and preſcribed in theſe words and no other, <hi>I. A. B.</hi> do here declare, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="23">23. What poſſible Exception can lie againſt ſuch a recital of the words of the <hi>Act</hi> which are ſet immediatly before the <hi>Declaration,</hi> in order to the making and ſubſcribing of it, while we add no <hi>words</hi> of <hi>our own,</hi> nor <hi>take</hi> any from the <hi>Act,</hi> or from the <hi>Declaration?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="24">24. If it be ſaid you fear that a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration</hi> will not be accepted, that is thus exclaimed and conditioned.</p>
                  <p n="25">25. Give me leave to ſay, I cannot but believe there is no reaſon to <hi>doubt</hi> it; or to deſire it as a favour from <hi>any:</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you <hi>add</hi> no words, nor put any ſence upon the <hi>Declaration;</hi> only reciting the words of the <hi>Act,</hi> requiring and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, according as is required, in theſe words of the <hi>Declaration,</hi> and none other.</p>
                  <p n="26">26. However, ſuppoſe (that that is not to be ſuppoſed) that ſuch a <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> ſhould be refuſed; and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch a kind of <hi>explaining</hi> your ſelf, you are reſolved <hi>not</hi> to declare or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe at all. Yet conſider by ſo doing,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:57726:33"/> though <hi>not</hi> accepted, you are not the <hi>worſe,</hi> or further off from your <hi>Living</hi> then you were before: and now you may fit down quiet with this reflection; that however you have done your ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to ſatisfie the <hi>Law,</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> and your <hi>own Conſcience.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="case">
            <head>CASE the Second. <hi>Whether it be lawful to Declare in the words of the</hi> ſecond Declaration.</head>
            <p n="1">1. YOu conſent to the <hi>diſtribution</hi> I made of the <hi>ſecond Declaration</hi> into 3 parts: That which concerns the <hi>taking Arms</hi> againſt the <hi>King, Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and the <hi>Oath</hi> called the ſolemn <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The two Caſes ariſing from the <hi>firſt</hi> part, <hi>taking Arms againſt the King,</hi> you ſay, do not much concern you; and give me leave to return, that I am not concerned to anſwer others.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To the Caſe about <hi>Conformity,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing from the <hi>ſecond</hi>-part, you add no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, out ſeem in haſte to get into your <hi>ſtrong hold,</hi> in the <hi>laſt</hi> part of this <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</hi> touching the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I am ready to attend you, and to engage with you.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:57726:34"/>4. We are therefore fallen upon the main <hi>Caſe,</hi> which was the <hi>ſixth</hi> in order in my <hi>laſt</hi> book it is;</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="case">
            <head>CASE VI. Whether we may lawfully declare in theſe words; <hi>I do hold there lies no Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation on me, or any other perſon, from the Oath commonly; called the</hi> ſolemn League and Covenant, <hi>to endeavour any change or alteration of Government in the Church or State?</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>THis</hi> I affirm, and undertook to prove it by an <hi>Argument</hi> taken from the matter of the Covenant, as is here ſpecified: not with reſpect to the Government of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> there we are agreed; but with reſpect to <hi>that</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> wherein we differ.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You alſo grant my Conſequence; that if this part of the matter of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant appear to be <hi>ſinful,</hi> the Covenant is ſo <hi>far,</hi> void of it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The very Queſtion then is, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>endeavour a change of Church-Government be ſinful or not.</hi> I affirm it, and give you my Arguments once again for it; and heartily wiſh, <hi>they</hi> may find, in their new attire, better entertainment with you.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:57726:34"/>4. You obſerve, I make my firſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet by Doctor <hi>Sanderſon</hi>'s diſtinction of <hi>Juramentum illicitum de ſe, &amp; per acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens.</hi> You farther ſay, I grant that the matter of the Covenant is not ſimply, and of it ſelf unlawful; you intimate, that I hold it only ſinful by accident.</p>
            <p n="5">5. My dear Brethren, I cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to tell you, that you make too much haſte, &amp; ſtumble at the threſhold; you fall both upon that Reverend Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and my ſelf with too plain miſtakes.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Biſhops diſtinction which you intend, is not that of <hi>illicitum per ſe vel per accidens;</hi> I do not here uſe that diſtinction; I do not grant that the matter of the Covenant is not ſimply and of it ſelf unlawful; much leſs, that the matter of the Covenant is ſinful <hi>per accidens</hi> only: The truth is, both the Biſhop and my ſelf, in the very places your words refer to, do more then once ſay quite contrary to what you affirm; in all which, will you but take the pains to read over again that Chapter in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Sanderſon</hi>'s Book, and in mine, that are here concern'd, your own eyes ſhall judg betwixt us.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The place you intend in Biſhop
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:57726:35"/> 
               <hi>Sanderſon</hi>'s Book is, <hi>Pag. 71, 72. Sect. 9.</hi> the Caſe is, <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re illicitâ Secundariò,</hi> wherein, indeed, he is ſo directly againſt you, that it is much ſo many eyes ſhould not obſerve it.</p>
            <p n="8">8. A thing (ſaith he) is unlawful <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundarîo,</hi> when it is not ſo in its own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or to all perſons: <hi>Sed quibuſdam tantùm pro</hi> conditione <hi>fuarum perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, prout ſunt membra alio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tatis, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ins: certo aliqua vitae gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re verſanturie illicitum enim idque</hi> ex ſe non ex accidente <hi>tantùm his qui ſunt membra alicujus communitatis, quicquid legibus illius communitatis repugnat:</hi> His reaſon there is, becauſe it is forbidden by God, though not <hi>primario,</hi> yet <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundariò;</hi> that is, in the command of obedience to our Governours, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the Laws of the Land.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Now, that your diſcourſe of this diſtinction intends this very place of the Biſhops Book, you give us a full demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration in your next words following.</p>
            <p n="10">10. You ſay, you muſt make bold to mind me, that the Learned Caſuiſt hath determined the Caſe with an <hi>Ordinariè; Haec juramenta ordinariè non obligant;</hi> meaning, ſuch Oaths as are taken to do
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:57726:35"/> a thing that is thus evil, not ſimply, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, or to all perſons; but to us, that by reaſon of our places are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to do it, they ordinarily do not bind.</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>I</hi> acknowledg he ſubjoyns (though nothing to your advantage) <hi>Ordinariè dico, quia fortaſſe poſſunt dari caſus in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus juramentum quod videtur alicui legi communitatis aut vocationis adverſari, &amp; ſi non debuerit ſuſcipi, ſuſceptum tamen poteſt obligari.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. You add, That the Advocates of the <hi>Covenant</hi> think they may bring the <hi>Covenant</hi> within our Caſuiſt's excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but upon an unbiaſſed reading our Caſuiſt's following explication of himſelf, there is nothing more evident then the contrary; herein alſo your ſelves ſhall be Judges.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Yet, firſt, give me leave to note, our Caſuiſt's Caution is with a <hi>fortaſſis;</hi> perhaps ſuch a Caſe may be; he never thought, you know he never ſaid the Caſe of the <hi>Covenant</hi> was ſuch; yea, his <hi>[videtur]</hi> adds no ſtrength to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, that is, when the Oath ſeems, but ſeems to be againſt the Laws of Community; but that he might leave
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:57726:36"/> no room for the ſcruple, he hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained himſelf in his own <hi>Inſtance</hi> in a disjunctive penal <hi>Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. His <hi>Caſe</hi> is <hi>this;</hi> Let the Law of the City be (ſaith he) that no <hi>man being choſen to the Office of a Pretor ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it:</hi> or if he do, he ſhall find ſuch a <hi>ſum</hi> of <hi>Mony, Caius</hi> ſwears he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be Pretor: but after his Oath, he is choſen to that Office. The Queſtion our Caſuiſt puts hereupon is, <hi>Whether</hi> Caius <hi>be bound to keep his Oath or not:</hi> and anſwer it thus he ought not to have ſworn; but having ſworn, he ought to keep his <hi>Oath,</hi> and pay the <hi>Fine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. Now, how far this is from the <hi>Caſe</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> in it ſelf, <hi>I</hi> need not ſay; and how far it was <hi>ſo</hi> in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our great <hi>caſuiſt,</hi> his following Diſcourſe doth ſufficiently Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
            <p n="16">16. I would here (ſaith he) be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood <hi>Praecisè in quantum adverſatur legi Civitatis. Nam reſpectu finis aut alterius cauſae, imo reſpectu ipſius etiam Materiae quatenus eſt impeditiva majoris boni pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lici, aut aliunde, poteſt juſta ſubeſſe ratio quae Obligationem tollat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. Now admitting this exception of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:57726:36"/> the Rule, it is not poſſible to apply it to the <hi>Covenant;</hi> however, if the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> could be granted by ſome thing extraordinary in it to be excepted alſo, yet you ſee the Caſuiſt hath provided ſeveral other <hi>Topicks</hi> to render it <hi>non-ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging;</hi> from the <hi>end,</hi> or the very <hi>matter</hi> it ſelf, if it may hinder a greater pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good; <hi>aut aliunde poteſt juſta ſubeſſe ratio quae obligationem tollat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. Give me leave alſo to remember you, that I made my meaning touching the ſaid diſtinction plain enough. I did not diſtinguiſh, as you aſſert I did, That the thing ſworn might be <hi>illicitum per ſe vel per accidens;</hi> but I rather diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd of <hi>illicitum per ſe</hi> as to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and that was either <hi>ſimply</hi> and <hi>primarily</hi> evil, or <hi>ſecondarily</hi> and <hi>quoad nos;</hi> when though it be not ſinful in the <hi>primary</hi> conſideration of it, yet to <hi>ſuch</hi> and <hi>ſuch perſons</hi> it is ſinful, that is, forbidden by God, as I did ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently explain my ſelf.</p>
            <p n="19">19. I did further conclude, that a thing thus ſinful, <hi>quoad nos,</hi> as being ſome way or other prohibited us to meddle with, is <hi>illicitum per ſe ſecunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riò,</hi> and therefore not only ſo <hi>per acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens.</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:57726:37"/> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe are my words: To <hi>them</hi> to whom a thing is <hi>forbidden</hi> it is as it were <hi>unlawful in it ſelf,</hi> (as the <hi>Apple</hi> to our <hi>firſt Parents)</hi> and as it is unlawful for us it goes into the matter of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which we take; and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, that which is only unlawful to us, if ſworn, doth make that Oath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful in it ſelf, that is, in the very mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it.</p>
            <p n="20">20. So that the Conſequence being granted, if this be proved, that it is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful in either ſence, either <hi>ſimply</hi> or <hi>quoad nos,</hi> to endeavour the <hi>Extirpation</hi> of Church-Government, we may bring the difference to an happy concluſion.</p>
            <p n="21">21. But I rather choſe to argue upon the latter branch, that to <hi>alter the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church</hi> is unlawful <hi>quoad nos;</hi> and that becauſe it is againſt the <hi>Rights</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> the <hi>Priviledges</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Subject,</hi> and the <hi>former Obligations</hi> that lay upon the <hi>Nations;</hi> all which I am bound to defend.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="case">
            <head>CASE VII.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Whether any private or ſingle perſon may lawfully endeavour the Alteration of</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:57726:37"/> Church-Government <hi>by virtue of the</hi> Covenant.</p>
            <p n="1">1. TO that which I have ſaid upon this Caſe you only return a diſcovery of three Principles, which you affirm I take for granted, though they are denied by my Adverſaries.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Long Parliament is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That the <hi>Covenant is only private and perſonal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That <hi>each ſingle perſon is concluded by my ſubſequent Arguments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe you call <hi>ungranted Principles;</hi> but if they may not be <hi>granted,</hi> though they are <hi>Principles,</hi> I ſhall endeavour that they may be <hi>proved;</hi> though, <hi>I</hi> hope, very few of the people of <hi>England</hi> need ſatisfaction in ſuch points as theſe.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 1. Of the <hi>diſſolution of the long Parliament.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. TOuching the <hi>Diſſolution</hi> of the <hi>Long Parliament,</hi> I could not dream, that ſo ingenuous perſons had any ſcruple: I would fain hope that you want a <hi>Refuge,</hi> when I find you in ſo bad a <hi>Sanctuary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Yet when <hi>I</hi> read your words, ſo
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:57726:38"/> warily conditioned in this great parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, I find ſome <hi>ſmall</hi> encouragement to think, that though you now ſtumble at <hi>this ſtone;</hi> if every other <hi>ſtone</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, you would ſtumble over it. You ſay it hath been ſaid, you <hi>dare not ſay it, and in obedience to preſent laws you are ſubmiſſively ſilent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Are you indeed Obedient? to what? to the preſent <hi>Lawes?</hi> Who <hi>made</hi> them? the <hi>Parliament.</hi> How comes this to be a <hi>Parliament,</hi> if the <hi>Long Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> be not diſſolv'd.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If the <hi>Long Parliament</hi> be yet in being, the <hi>Preſent</hi> is <hi>none,</hi> their <hi>Laws</hi> are <hi>none,</hi> your <hi>Obedience</hi> is <hi>none:</hi> if you <hi>acknowledge</hi> the <hi>preſent Laws,</hi> you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the <hi>preſent Parliament;</hi> and thereby you are over the ſtone of ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling before you are aware; for you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the <hi>Long Parliament</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd</p>
               <p n="5">5. Now there are but two ungran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>principles;</hi> for <hi>one</hi> you have gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon a better Argument then <hi>I</hi> had thought of, your own <hi>Obedience</hi> to the preſent Laws.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Truly, <hi>I</hi> took you to be ſo ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous before hand, and therefore <hi>I</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:57726:38"/> to take this for granted, and thought <hi>I might</hi> do it <hi>without</hi> offence. For it is not only the <hi>ground</hi> of <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> to the preſent <hi>Laws,</hi> but the <hi>Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> of our <hi>Peace,</hi> our <hi>Liberty,</hi> our <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> our <hi>Lives,</hi> and indeed of all we are worth in this world; and ſuch a ſtone, (not of ſtumbling, but) of the Comer, that it is hardly ſafe to <hi>touch</hi> it, though with an intent to faſten it. But, bleſſed be <hi>God,</hi> it is faſt enough already in our <hi>conſtitution,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> hope not much <hi>looſned</hi> in your <hi>opinions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Yet, if you are in <hi>doubt</hi> of what diſeaſe that great body died: <hi>I</hi> refer you to Judge <hi>Jenkins</hi> and Mr. <hi>Prin;</hi> who, though in other things they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered <hi>too</hi> much, agree very well in <hi>this</hi> great <hi>point.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Indeed the Name, <hi>Parliam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t,</hi> which ſignifies to conſult and treat; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the <hi>Writ</hi> whereby the <hi>two Houſes</hi> are <hi>Aſſembled,</hi> are a full <hi>Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration</hi> of its departure or diſſolution long agon. They are thereby called to conſult and treat with the <hi>King:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it ſignified that <hi>Rex eſt habiturus Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquium &amp; Tractatum cum praelatis, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natibus, &amp; proceribus. Rex in hoc indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:57726:39"/>9. Hence Judge <hi>Jinkins</hi> argues, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> diſſolved upon the <hi>Kings</hi> being forced from them, and put into an <hi>incapacity</hi> of Treating with them; however at his death they died on courſe.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The <hi>King</hi> dying, with whom they are to Treat, and for which end they have their <hi>being,</hi> the <hi>end</hi> of their <hi>aſſembling,</hi> and conſequently of their <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> is gon with <hi>him,</hi> and they are no longer a <hi>Parliament.</hi> A <hi>Parliament</hi> is a Relative term; the Relate and Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late <hi>die</hi> together. Therefore, the <hi>King,</hi> in our Laws, is <hi>Principium, Caput, &amp; finis Parliamenti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. It may be ſaid, the <hi>Act</hi> ſecured them againſt the <hi>Kings death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. 'Tis plainly otherwiſe; indeed, it ſecured themſelves from any violence to be done to that end, by the <hi>King</hi> himſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f: there is no ſuch clauſe in the <hi>Act,</hi> that they ſhould not be capable of diſſolving any other way, much leſs, in particular, by the <hi>Kings</hi> death, no ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to ſave the <hi>Body</hi> when the <hi>Head</hi> was off.</p>
               <p n="13">13. But a <hi>Parliament</hi> may be <hi>diſſolved,</hi> or <hi>diſſolve: die,</hi> or be <hi>kill'd:</hi> the <hi>Act</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:57726:39"/> ſecured them from being diſſolved by the <hi>Kings</hi> power, without their Conſent; not againſt the <hi>law</hi> of <hi>Mortality,</hi> or their diſſolving on courſe at his deceaſe.</p>
               <p n="14">14. This is very evident in <hi>ull Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments:</hi> if the <hi>Kings</hi> favour ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue a <hi>Parliament</hi> his whole time, that <hi>Parliament</hi> hath <hi>all</hi> that the long <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament</hi> deſired or obtained, by the <hi>Act</hi> ſpecified: yet upon the <hi>Kings</hi> death, ſuch a <hi>Parliament</hi> diſſolves, according to the nature of the thing and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Nation.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Who can be ſo <hi>fond,</hi> as to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that it was ever intended, either by the <hi>King,</hi> or both <hi>Houſes,</hi> (eſpecially if the Reaſons be weighed, with which this <hi>Act</hi> was proſecuted,) that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Nation, or the nature of a <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſhould be altered by it; or more, then that the <hi>King</hi> ſhould not diſſolve them by violence; that is, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their own conſent.</p>
               <p n="16">16. 'Tis as <hi>frivolous</hi> to mention, that the <hi>King</hi> never dies in this <hi>reſpect;</hi> For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is evident, that as the <hi>King</hi> is the <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the Relate &amp; Reaſons of a particular <hi>Parliament,</hi> ſo he doth die. For, as was ſaid, a <hi>Parliament</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:57726:40"/> 
                  <hi>diſſolv'd</hi> by the <hi>King</hi> in his life time, diſſolves of it ſelf, at his death, and why, but becauſe in this ſence the <hi>King</hi> dies?</p>
               <p n="17">17. I never heard ſuch Arguments as theſe following anſwered, though indeed we need them not. They are Judge <hi>Jenkin's.</hi> He affirms that the <hi>Act</hi> for the continuance of the long <hi>Parliament</hi> is Repugnant to thoſe for Annual and Triennial <hi>Parliaments;</hi> which being all <hi>Acts</hi> of one Seſſion, are all <hi>Acts</hi> of one day, and repugnant to common Right and common Reaſon; and impoſſible by the <hi>Kings</hi> Mortality: and maintains, that when an Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> is thus againſt common Right and Reaſon, and repugnant and impoſſible to be perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the <hi>common Law</hi> ſhall control, and adjudge ſuch an <hi>Act</hi> to be void, and that theſe are the <hi>words of the Law.</hi> 1. Par. D. <hi>Downhams</hi> Caſe, fol. 11S. 8E. 3. 3. 30. 33. E. <hi>Ceſſavit.</hi> 32. 37. H. O. <hi>Annuity</hi> 41. 1. Eliz. Dier. 313.</p>
               <p n="18">18. I hope, you will not demand who ſhall judge of ſuch a Caſe, ſince <hi>all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> have practically reſolved this long agon.</p>
               <p n="19">19. The <hi>Rump thought</hi> that <hi>Parliament too long;</hi> the <hi>whole Nation</hi> were offended
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:57726:40"/> at the <hi>Rump:</hi> The <hi>Long-Parliament</hi> men themſelves, when they were toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther again, in order to the bleſſed <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> had a deſire to be <hi>diſſolv'd,</hi> and did what they could themſelves to do it: and you know, that both <hi>King, Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> have <hi>ſince</hi> made a <hi>Law,</hi> to which you ſay you yield <hi>Obedience,</hi> that brandeth it for an high offence, for any to ſay that the <hi>Long Parliament is not diſſolv'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20. But my <hi>dear brethren,</hi> becauſe you intimate that you are not fully ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in this <hi>point;</hi> out of my hearty deſire to do you any ſervice, I have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed with a very learned <hi>Sergeant</hi> in the <hi>Laws,</hi> from whom I received theſe 3. <hi>Reaſons:</hi> every one of which, he affirms, demonſtrates that <hi>Parliament</hi> to be <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd; in ſua arte credend.</hi> &amp;c. and I hope you will be fully ſatisfied with them: they are theſe.</p>
               <p n="21">21. 1. By the <hi>death</hi> of the <hi>King;</hi> there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing in the Act <hi>of continuance</hi> that doth or can ſecure them againſt <hi>that.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Becauſe every Court in <hi>England</hi> diſſolves on courſe, if it riſes without adjourning, or doth not meet <hi>again,</hi> at the time and place appointed.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:57726:41"/>3. Becauſe, when a <hi>Parliament Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedes,</hi> and the Electors chuſe <hi>new Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives,</hi> the firſt are diſſolv'd thereby,</p>
               <p>I need not <hi>apply</hi> theſe <hi>Rules;</hi> onely, if you yet doubt the force of them, and deſire, as I know you will do, more <hi>full</hi> ſatisfaction; you will certainly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out my advice confer with ſome able Lawyer, whom you may ſafer in your own apprehenſions con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ide in. In ſuch a caſe we muſt take things upon <hi>truſt;</hi> and if we will be ſatisfied, we muſt truſt ſome <hi>body,</hi> chooſe your Friend.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 2. Of the <hi>Reality</hi> and <hi>Nationality</hi> of the <hi>Covenant.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. IN the ſecond place, you intimate that I take it for granted, that the Covenant was perſonal, and not Real or National. But Maſter <hi>Crof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> hath affirmed it is real and Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, <hi>Obliging all the Nation, and all after Generations,</hi> ſide Anglorum, <hi>thereby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged.</hi> This, you ſay, he hath enforced beyond all capacity of <hi>Contradiction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Truly, <hi>I</hi> confeſs, <hi>I</hi> did not ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine (however confident <hi>I</hi> find you to the contrary) that ſuch a principle had
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:57726:41"/> needed proof, with <hi>ſuch</hi> as <hi>I</hi> propoſed to deal with: but <hi>I</hi> ſee the <hi>Foundations</hi> are yet out of Courſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Much leſs, could <hi>I</hi> divine, that whether the <hi>Covenant</hi> be perſonal or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l, it could any way concern me in my preſent Deſign to trouble myſelf; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it was <hi>my work</hi> only to prove that the matter of the <hi>Covenant</hi> was ſinful; and then, whether it be a real or a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal <hi>Covenant, I</hi> think it comes all to one, <hi>viz.</hi> A <hi>ſinful</hi> Covenant, <hi>and not Obliging.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Beſides, upon your ſecond Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey, you will eaſily diſcern, that <hi>I</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed ſingle and private perſons, from the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and not from the <hi>Nation;</hi> and conſidered both Members of my diſtinction; as taking the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;</hi> And did not find my ſelf obliged to ſay, that <hi>ſome not:</hi> but rather, that none at all were ſo far bound by vertue of it, as to endeavour any alteration or change of <hi>Government:</hi> ſo that your ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception here, If it have any weight, it is impertinent and ill placed.</p>
               <p n="5">5. But ſeeing <hi>I</hi> muſt be aſſaulted with Mr. <hi>Croſtons authority.</hi> give me leave to
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:57726:42"/> oppoſe <hi>it,</hi> with <hi>Authority</hi> as valid, <hi>I</hi> hope, without any diſparagement to <hi>him,</hi> in your own apprehenſions: it is that <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Caſuiſt</hi> Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> aſſerts, that it is eſſential to an <hi>Oath</hi> to be perſonal; and conſequently, that there is no ſuch thing as <hi>Juramentum reale,</hi> ſuch a Real Oath as you have pretended.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Non tantùm (inquit ille vir Magnus) tenetùr Haeres vi Juramenti defuncto prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiti. It a ut ſi non ſolverit, injuſtus tantùm ſit, non item perjurus: cujus ratio eſt, quia Juramentum eſt vinculum perſonale, &amp; inducit Obligationem Spiritualem tantùm, &amp;c. At in perſonalibus nemo ligatur fine proprio conſenſu.</hi> p. 115.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Again, he adds, <hi>At non poteſt quis alteri inducere Obligationem niſi ipſe quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que volverit, &amp; proinde non poteſt Actu ſuo ſpiritualiter niſi ſeipſum tantùm—Obligatio Juramenti non tranſit ad ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſores,</hi> p, 117. 118. nothing can be more plain.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Therefore, <hi>I</hi> muſt have leave to demand, what <hi>Caſuiſt, Authour</hi> of Note, or <hi>Learned Man</hi> unintereſted in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Controverſie hath uſed or allowed this diſtinction, beſides Maſter <hi>Croſton.</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:57726:42"/> Thus his <hi>authority</hi> is <hi>matcht;</hi> what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons you hint for it, <hi>I</hi> proceed to give reaſon to Anſwer.</p>
               <p n="10">10. You add no reaſons in <hi>this</hi> place, yet becauſe <hi>I</hi> ſhall make but one work of it, <hi>I</hi> ſhall gather the reaſons that ſerve to this purpoſe from the other parts of your <hi>book</hi> where <hi>I</hi> find them; they are but two, to the beſt of my Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, both received from Maſter <hi>Crofton:</hi> and <hi>I</hi> preſume the beſt he <hi>hath,</hi> for that you improve no other.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The firſt <hi>I</hi> find upon Caſe the 14. by way of Expoſtulation, thus. Was the law of <hi>Saul,</hi> the Princes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> againſt the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> to be juſtified? Why <hi>ſhould they and all other</hi> Conventions <hi>of them be bound by the Oath of</hi> Joſhua, <hi>and the Princes with him?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. The anſwer is at hand, in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Biſhops words: <hi>Saul, Injuſtus tantùm ſit, non item perjurus. Pauls</hi> ſin was <hi>cruelty</hi> and <hi>injuſtice,</hi> and not <hi>perju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> Not the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but the <hi>Law</hi> of Righteouſneſs bound <hi>Saul</hi> to the contrary.</p>
               <p n="13">13. If any <hi>Obligation</hi> lay upon <hi>Saul</hi> rom <hi>Joſhua's Oath,</hi> it was not <hi>formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> but <hi>effectivè</hi> only; not as an <hi>Oath,</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:57726:43"/> but in the effects of it: which was to preſerve and maintain <hi>Juſtice</hi> and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans right; even that right of the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> which they had obtained, by vertue indeed of their Covenant with <hi>Joſhua</hi> long before.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Methinks, it may thus be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled; a <hi>Parliament</hi> in <hi>England</hi> is not obliged; to continue all the <hi>Acts</hi> of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent <hi>Parliaments,</hi> but hath power to alter them as they think fit; yet no <hi>Parliament</hi> can <hi>void</hi> an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>pardon</hi> made by any former <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. The <hi>Reaſon</hi> is, not that one <hi>Parliament</hi> hath not power to undo what another hath done abſtractly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidered; but becauſe a <hi>Parliament</hi> it ſelf may not be unrighteous and do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice.</p>
               <p n="16">16. But, why is it injuſtice from a <hi>Parliament</hi> to <hi>void</hi> an <hi>Act</hi> of pardon? the Reaſon ſeems to be this: An <hi>Act</hi> of pardon hath its effect the firſt day of its being, and gives actual Right to every one concerned in the mercy granted; they are <hi>actually</hi> pardoned, and the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence forgiven and done away. And now, if this pardon ſhould be taken off again, <hi>Right</hi> is <hi>violated</hi> and <hi>puniſhment</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:57726:43"/> inflicted where there is no Crime.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Thus was it in the <hi>Caſe</hi> of the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beonites;</hi> they had received an <hi>Act</hi> of pardon long before, a Legal reſtitution to the priviledges they enjoy'd by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Joſhua,</hi> and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and the <hi>violation</hi> of their <hi>Rights,</hi> ſo long after, with the taking away of their lives, by <hi>Saul,</hi> was iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and cruelty in him, and moſt juſtly, though ſeverely, puniſhed by the <hi>God</hi> of Righteouſneſs.</p>
               <p n="18">18. This Anſwer is plainly gathered from the <hi>Holy</hi> Scripture, whence the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi> it ſelf is framed.</p>
               <p n="19">19. The <hi>Famine</hi> (ſaith the Lord to <hi>David) is for</hi> Saul, <hi>and for his bloody houſe,</hi> becauſe he <hi>ſlew</hi> the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> 2 Sam. 21. 11.</p>
               <p n="20">20. It is rendred, in ſeveral of the <hi>Oriental</hi> Tongues, <hi>Houſe of bloods;</hi> and ſo it is in the <hi>Hebrew:</hi> it was not perjury but <hi>blood</hi> fill'd his <hi>houſe,</hi> becauſe he <hi>ſlew the Gibeonites,</hi> and broke the <hi>Act</hi> of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, not the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Joſhua</hi> formally conſidered.</p>
               <p n="21">21. It is ſaid, that the <hi>children of</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael <hi>had ſworn to them,</hi> v. 2. but not <hi>Saul:</hi> yea the <hi>children</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in oppoſition
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:57726:44"/> to <hi>Saul:</hi> the <hi>children</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had ſworn unto them, and <hi>Saul</hi> ſought to <hi>ſlay</hi> them in zeal to the <hi>children</hi> of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Therefore, in the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> we read <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, upon <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>upon his houſe; Injuſtitia in morte ſanguinum ejus pro eo. quod morti. tradidit</hi> Gibeonitas, for that he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> to <hi>death: Injuſtice,</hi> it is not ſaid Perjury, but <hi>injuſtice,</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> is laid upon <hi>him</hi> and his <hi>houſe,</hi> and ſo ſeverely puniſhed.</p>
               <p n="22">22. Secondly, the <hi>Covenant</hi> was ſworn (ſay you, in Mr. <hi>Croftons</hi> words) by thoſe <note place="margin">P. 45.</note> 
                  <hi>Real capacities, Noble Men, Knights, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, Citizens, Miniſters of the Goſpel, and Commons of all ſorts, which paſs and will paſs to our Succeſſours, whileſt</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>is</hi> England; and therefore it is <hi>Juramentum reale,</hi> and obligeth the <hi>whole Nation for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="23">23. But it is to be remembred, before we conclude ſo confidently, that though the Proem runs thus, <hi>We Noblemen, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, Knights, Gentlemen, Citizens, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſſes, and Miniſters of the Goſpel, as well as Commons of all ſorts, have ſo Reſolved and Determined;</hi> yet moſt <hi>Noblemen, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, Knights, Citizens, Burgeſſes, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:57726:44"/> and Commons of all ſorts,</hi> had not thus Reſolved and Determined when the <hi>Covenant</hi> was penn'd or publiſh'd.</p>
               <p n="24">24. For it was brought from <hi>Seot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and by a few men, at firſt, a little altered in <hi>England,</hi> and then, by an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſome of the Commons, printed and publiſhed.</p>
               <p n="25">25. Now, if this be to make a Real and <hi>National Covenant,</hi> three or four private perſons may as eaſily write over theſe great words, and as eaſily oblige the whole Nation and Poſterity for ever; but this is ridiculous.</p>
               <p n="26">26. Again, 'tis certain that many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividual Perſons, from the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Nobles, Barons, Knights, Burgeſſes, Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, Miniſters, and Commons of all ſorts,</hi> never took the Covenant, but ever, as occaſion was offered, declared their abhorrency of it.</p>
               <p n="27">27. Yea, the <hi>Popiſh,</hi> the <hi>Milignant,</hi> and the <hi>Prelatical</hi> Parties, which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly were then no mean part of the Nation, if not the greateſt, are ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Covenant it ſelf to be enemies to it, and are, indeed, ſworn againſt it. And are theſe obliged by the ſame Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and their Poſterities after them?
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:57726:45"/> Are they ſworn to oppoſe and deſtroy themſelves? You will not ſay it.</p>
               <p n="28">28. Again, if theſe words can create a <hi>Real Covenant</hi> in your ſence, not only <hi>Scotland,</hi> who framed it, and <hi>England,</hi> who knew not of it for the moſt part till it was taken, but <hi>Ireland</hi> too, and its Poſterity, are obliged by it; and all the Rebels there are taken into Confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and thouſands of people there, that never ſaw it, or perhaps never heard ſo much as that there was any ſuch thing in the world for divers years after this their pretended Obligation by it.</p>
               <p n="29">29. Truly I thought the Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Party would not have entred into ſo Solemn a <hi>League</hi> with a <hi>Prelatical, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant</hi> Party, much leſs with <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh Rebels;</hi> yet ſuch is the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of your Notion of a <hi>Real Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="30">30. Moreover, this Argument is confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the very <hi>Proem</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi> it ſelf, ſo plainly and evidently, that I muſt needs wonder that ſo many quick and perceiving eyes ſhould not have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered it: Wherein it ſaith (ſpeaking of the form and manner of giving and taking the Covenant) wherein <hi>we all</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:57726:45"/> 
                  <hi>ſubſcribe,</hi> (therefore, no more do <hi>take</hi> the Covenant then do <hi>ſubſcribe</hi> it) and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all contradiction adds, <hi>[and each one of us for himſelf]</hi> then no <hi>one</hi> for another, much leſs for ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands as your <hi>Real Notion</hi> would infer.</p>
               <p n="31">31. Therefore the preſſers of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant durſt not truſt your Logick, but would have not only Parents, but their Children; not only Maſters, but Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants; not only Tutors, but Pupils, and ſuch as were under the tuition of others, to ſubſcribe for themſelves, according to the phraſe, <hi>Every one for himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="32">32. But, to conclude, if it be againſt the very Nature and Eſſence of an Oath to be any more then <hi>perſonal,</hi> to binde <hi>ſucceſſion</hi> or <hi>poſterity,</hi> or to be <hi>National</hi> and <hi>Real,</hi> as you pretend; alas! what can words do more then to make a noiſe, to trouble mens minds, and to beget trouble in the Church by needleſs Diſputation? But that it is ſo, I hope our Caſuiſt (whom your ſelves and all men elſe admire) hath put it out of doubt, to your full ſatisfaction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:57726:46"/>
               <head>SECT. 3. <hi>Of the capacity of all Covenanters.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. THe third Principle which you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate I take for granted, is, <hi>That all Perſons that took the</hi> Covenant <hi>are in the ſame capacity with our ſelves.</hi> You ſay, you cannot yield unto it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. I have laboured to find out your meaning, and cannot diſcover any thing, but the exception of the <hi>ſingle perſon,</hi> that you can ſtand upon.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But if you pleaſe to review what I ſaid from <hi>pag.</hi> 93. to <hi>pag.</hi> 97. you will ſee your overſight, and grant that I did not take it for granted.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And until you give Anſwer to the reaſon there offered, as alſo in ſome other places of my Book, I think I am not at all concerned to trouble you further about it, but ſhall now take up my <hi>ſhield,</hi> and appear in defence of my particular Arguments.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="case">
            <p>CASE VIII. <hi>Whether to endeavour to alter the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church be againſt the Right of the King.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="case">
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:57726:46"/>
            <head>CASE IX. <hi>Whether to violate the Kings Right be not ſinful.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. YOu well obſerve, that theſe two Caſes contain my firſt Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to prove the matter of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, ſinful. My <hi>major Propoſition,</hi> you ſay, is determined in the ſecond of theſe Caſes: This you grant, in Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi>'s words. <hi>The proper and adequate Act of Juſtice is</hi> Jus ſuum cuique; <hi>the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Power, and Liberty of King, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>minor</hi> then contained in the firſt of theſe Caſes is the thing in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, <hi>viz.</hi> whether the <hi>Covenant</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging againſt the <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> or to endeavour to extirpate the ſame, do not <hi>violate the Kings Right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. This I affirm; for by ſuch Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours the King is injured, firſt, as he is the <hi>Executor</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> and in all Cauſes and over all Perſons Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Supreme Governour, both with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his Officers and to his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſecondly, as <hi>Legiſlator.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:57726:47"/>
               <head>SECT. 1. <hi>Of the Kings Right as Supreme Executor of the Laws.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. I Do ſtill affirm, That the King is the Supreme Executor of the Law, and all inferiour Officers are his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, to execute that Government under him, in which he is alone the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Governour, as we ſwear him to be in Church and State; for, <hi>Reges ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ro oleo uncti faut capaces ſpiritualis Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>isdictionis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Now, I ſay, take away the Body of Governours, and the Head muſt fall; and if all inferiours be removed, where will the Supreme be?</p>
               <p n="3">3. For Anſwer hereunto you onely deſire my <hi>clear Anſwer</hi> to two Enquiries.</p>
               <p>The firſt of your Queries is in theſe words:</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Are Eccleſiaſtical Officers eſſential to the Regality of the King?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. To this I return my <hi>clear Anſwer;</hi> No. Yet they are plainly eſſential to his being a Supreme Governour in all Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and over all Perſons Eccleſiaſtical.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Supream</hi> doth neceſſarily ſuppoſe and reſpect <hi>Inferiours;</hi> and <hi>Supream Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:57726:47"/> Inferiour Governours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Your ſecond Query is this: Are <hi>theſe ſpecifical Commiſſioners eſſential to the Kings Regality; that Archbiſhops, Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>taken away the head muſt needs fall?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. To this, I hope I may clearly An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that the removing of the <hi>inferiour</hi> Governours hath a <hi>Natural tendency</hi> to the falling of the <hi>Head,</hi> as ſuch, that is the <hi>Head of them,</hi> or the <hi>Supreme;</hi> but hath no <hi>natural ordination</hi> to the <hi>ſubſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> of other kind of Governours.</p>
               <p n="9">9. There is nothing in the <hi>pulling down</hi> of the <hi>walls</hi> that goeth into the <hi>ſupport</hi> of the <hi>roof;</hi> nothing in <hi>pulling down Arch-biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. that ſerves to <hi>uphold</hi> the <hi>Supremacy</hi> of the King in governing the Church, but to deſtroy it, as the <hi>twenty years</hi> experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence paſt doth ſadly demonſtrate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 2. Of <hi>the Kings Right in the Government of the Church.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. THe ſecond <hi>Medium I</hi> uſe to prove, that <hi>endeavours to extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate Epiſcopal Government</hi> you obſerve to be this; that <hi>thus</hi> to endeavour is not
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:57726:48"/> only againſt the Kings Right as Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the Laws, by oppoſing and ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to deſtroy his Commiſſioners, but his very government it ſelf; and this is the expreſs ſence of the <hi>Covenanters,</hi> that according to the <hi>Covenant</hi> they are bound in the whole courſe of their lives againſt that Government which they know is <hi>the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>This</hi> you grant: only you ſay the Covenanters do not mean <hi>ſuch</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours as I <hi>mention:</hi> Again, you plead that ſome others <hi>deny</hi> the <hi>Government</hi> of the Church to be the <hi>Kings Government,</hi> becauſe they find it not eſtabliſhed by the <hi>Laws of the Land,</hi> whereof it is his <hi>Right</hi> to be <hi>Executor,</hi> and this is all you ſay; only <hi>touching</hi> theſe things here, you refer their diſcuſſion to their proper pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; where I intend, God willing, to meet them again.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 3. <hi>Of the Kings Right as Legiſlator.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. AGain, you note that I argue, to endeavour the <hi>alteration of Church Government</hi> is againſt the Kings Right as Legiſlator, as the maker, as
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:57726:48"/> well as the <hi>Executor</hi> of the <hi>laws,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by that ſence of the Covenant which the practice of the Covenanters hath put upon it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To <hi>this</hi> you anſwer, that the <hi>terms</hi> do ſo <hi>condition</hi> it, that it doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to engage us to endeavour the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of Epiſcopacy without the Kings Conſent.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Here, I muſt have leave to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you, that though it be true the terms of the Covenant which you ſpecifie are ſoft and mild, <hi>viz.</hi> through the <hi>grace of God,</hi> in our places and callings; yet there are other expreſſions <hi>viſible</hi> in it, that do more then ſeem to exact ſuch proceedings as were ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y inconſiſtent with our places and callings; or the <hi>grace of God, viz.</hi> to our power, and with our lives and fortunes.</p>
               <p n="4">4. What need was there <hi>then</hi> of our power, or lives and fortunes, to be expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in ſuch endeavours, but in <hi>oppoſing</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and his <hi>Army?</hi> and how could that poſſibly be done in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent matter of endeavour to extirpate Prelacy; but by Acting therein without the <hi>Kings conſent,</hi> and againſt his <hi>expreſs mind to the contrary.</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:57726:49"/> ſo that take a true meaſure of the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> by all ſuch terms together, as in fair reaſoning we muſt needs do; and it is <hi>too too evident</hi> that it puts us on endeavours that have no regard to the <hi>Kings conſent</hi> at all.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Beſides, if the true <hi>extent</hi> of <hi>endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> covenanted be yet in doubt, you would force me to reſolve it by that black <hi>Comment</hi> of the <hi>ſtate</hi> of things when the <hi>Covenant</hi> was preſs'd at firſt: from the <hi>occaſion</hi> of it, which, as the <hi>King</hi> ſadly obſerv'd, was that <hi>fatal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy</hi> with the <hi>Scots,</hi> for their <hi>inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> this <hi>Kingdome</hi> with <hi>Arms.</hi> The obvious and declared judgement of the <hi>Scots,</hi> that created <hi>it,</hi> touching the place and power of <hi>publick conventions</hi> and <hi>private</hi> perſons in <hi>ſuch</hi> matters. The <hi>ſudden</hi> courſe which the <hi>two Houſes</hi> took to <hi>demoliſh this</hi> Government, (and that by virtue of the <hi>Covenant,)</hi> and to bring in another.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Theſe</hi> things I ſay, <hi>ſoberly</hi> conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and pondered upon, methinks ſhould rationally, and ſatisfactorily <hi>Evince</hi> to ſuch <hi>ſober</hi> perſons as I am Treating with, that <hi>endeavour</hi> in the ſence of the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> it ſelf, and the prime <hi>Covenanters,</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:57726:49"/> doth intrench ſouly upon the <hi>Kings Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative</hi> and Crown; Notwithſtanding thoſe other ſmall, ſaint, and after endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours with the <hi>King</hi> to ratifie what they had laboured with all their power, in a way of <hi>Hoſtility ſo long</hi> together <hi>to do without him,</hi> and againſt his moſt <hi>ſignal expreſs diſſent,</hi> ſo often reiterated.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Which <hi>little endeavours</hi> to procure his <hi>conſent,</hi> I imagine, you would hardly have mentioned, had you had in your mind, that at the ſame time the <hi>King</hi> was at leaſt <hi>quaſi</hi> a <hi>priſoner,</hi> and was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by the <hi>ſame</hi> perſons that treated <hi>him</hi> the liberty to repair to the place where, according to the Order of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> he uſeth to add his <hi>fiat</hi> to the <hi>making of Laws:</hi> I mean the <hi>Parliament Houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Further, I am loth to remember that even <hi>then,</hi> when the <hi>King</hi> (at the <hi>Ile of Wight)</hi> and his two Houſes were neereſt to an accommodation; the force of ſuch endeavours as the <hi>Covenant</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted provoked them to reply to his <hi>Majeſties</hi> papers, that they were yet <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied</hi> as to an agreement with, and reception of his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> becauſe he would <hi>only</hi> grant them a <hi>ſuſpenſion of</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:57726:50"/> 
                  <hi>Epiſcopal-Government</hi> for 3. yeers, and not an eternal extirpation of it, for which they had <hi>covenanted:</hi> vid. <hi>Bibli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth. Reg. p.</hi> 153.</p>
               <p n="9">9. But to return to the <hi>Covenant</hi> it ſelf; the cloſe of it doth effectually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that in its prime and native in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, <hi>it</hi> leaſt of all regarded the <hi>Conſent of the King;</hi> and as to any <hi>ſuch</hi> thing, it was utterly deſperate.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The words are theſe: <hi>We ſhall all the dayes of our lives zealouſly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly continue therein againſt all oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and <hi>promote the ſame according to our power againſt all lets and impediments whatſoever:</hi> and <hi>what we are not able our ſelves to ſuppreſs or over come, we ſhall r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal and make known, that it may be time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prevented or removed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. Now I beſeech you to conſider; here is a <hi>promiſe</hi> to continue in this cauſe; which refers, no doubt, to the <hi>whole</hi> or the <hi>main matter</hi> of the <hi>Covenant.</hi> Now as the Author of the <hi>Covenanters plea</hi> obſerves; the main ſcope of the <hi>Covenant</hi> is againſt <hi>Church-Government,</hi> to which all other things ſeem ſubordinate. Therefore, this ſame <hi>laſt Article</hi> repeats the <hi>beads</hi> of this <hi>common cauſe,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:57726:50"/> it with <hi>Religion;</hi> that is the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> of <hi>Doctrine, Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,</hi> and the <hi>extirpation of Epiſcopal Government.</hi> The words are this <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> Cauſe of <hi>Religion, Liberty,</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> of the <hi>Kingdomes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. Now, in this Cauſe, obſerve, They <hi>ſwear</hi> to <hi>continue zealouſly</hi> and <hi>conſtantly</hi> all the <hi>dayes</hi> of their <hi>lives:</hi> and what is the plain ſence of that, the <hi>King</hi> being known to be then in the <hi>fields.</hi> and in <hi>arms</hi> aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſt the <hi>Covenanters;</hi> I ſay, what can the plain ſence be; but that they would continue therein, though the King himſelf ſhould forbid. Though the King ſhould deny his <hi>Aſſent,</hi> and declare his moſt expreſs <hi>Diſſent</hi> and threats againſt it, yet they would perſiſt therein all <hi>the dayes of their lives.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. Yea, though King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (as is now come to paſs) ſhould make <hi>Laws</hi> againſt it, they muſt be zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and conſtant in this <hi>common Cauſe:</hi> ſo little regard will the <hi>Covenant</hi> allow, to this day, to the Kings Conſent.</p>
               <p n="14">14. Yet heed what follows; <hi>againſt all Oppoſition,</hi> and <hi>promote the ſame againſt all lets and impediments whatſoever;</hi> give me leave to ſay, though this Oppoſition,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:57726:51"/> theſe lets and impediments be from the King himſelf, as you know they were at this very ſame time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the <hi>two Houſes,</hi> and taken by the people; and the King himſelf in <hi>Arms</hi> to defend his <hi>own</hi> and the <hi>Churches</hi> Government.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Pray reſolve, where <hi>then</hi> was the <hi>King Conſent,</hi> or, <hi>if the King pleaſe,</hi> to be <hi>underſtood</hi> in the <hi>Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. Moreover, doth not <hi>this Article,</hi> which is the cloſe and perfection of the reſt, plainly engage to ſuch endeavours as carry oppoſition too? Be your ſelves the judges: the words are, againſt <hi>all oppoſition;</hi> how can you be engaged to endeavour againſt <hi>all oppoſition,</hi> but by <hi>oppoſition?</hi> againſt <hi>all oppoſition,</hi> but by oppoſing <hi>all oppoſitions?</hi> even that which the King himſelf <hi>ſhould</hi> make, or rather, indeed, <hi>did</hi> make.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Now, how you can <hi>oppoſe</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> or the <hi>oppoſition</hi> made by <hi>him</hi> and his <hi>commiſſion,</hi> and yet <hi>underſtand</hi> his <hi>conſent</hi> in the <hi>ſame matter,</hi> I think you will not go about to inform me.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Once more, that the endeavours of the <hi>Covenant</hi> carry force and <hi>oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in them, according to the <hi>Grammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:57726:51"/> Conſtruction and <hi>Logical</hi> reſolution of the ſame, appears in that <hi>[Power]</hi> is engaged to our <hi>Power:</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> in order to the ſuppreſſing and overcoming the <hi>oppoſers:</hi> for it is added, and what we are not <hi>able</hi> our ſelves to <hi>ſuppreſs,</hi> &amp;c. by our <hi>own power:</hi> and on the other hand, we ſhall <hi>aſſiſt</hi> and <hi>Defend</hi> all thoſe that enter into this <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> in the maintaining and purſuing thereof.</p>
               <p n="19">19. Which expreſſions (I ſhould abhor to infer it, did not my Argument force it) do beyond all capacity of Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction engage the <hi>Covenanters</hi> in a party to live and dy together in an hoſtile way of Oppoſition againſt the <hi>King,</hi> and his <hi>Armies</hi> and <hi>Friends,</hi> in a purſuit of the <hi>ends</hi> of the <hi>Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20. Which cannot conſiſt with the places of Subjects, or lawful endeavours; or Poſſibly ſuppoſe the Kings <hi>conſent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="21">21. I cannot rejoyce to conclude, that <hi>this</hi> meaning of the <hi>Covenant</hi> was expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at firſt, by the prime inventors and contrivers of the <hi>Covenant; ſuch</hi> words as theſe you find in a <hi>Declaration,</hi> called the <hi>Declaration of the convention of Eſtates of the Kingdom of</hi> Scotland.</p>
               <p n="22">
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:57726:52"/>22. To our knowledg, ſay they, upon ſwearing and ſubſcribing of this <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> the oppoſite <hi>Malignant</hi> partie will rage and Tumultuate more then ever: and therefore, unleſs we will either <hi>betray our Religion,</hi> Liberties and Law, and all that we and ours do poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs, and ſuffer our ſelves to be cut off and maſſacred by the bloody and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous cruelty of thoſe our enraged ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; <hi>There is a neceſſity of taking Arms for mutual defence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="23">23. Laſtly, That the <hi>Kings Conſent</hi> was little intended or underſtood in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> is yet more manifeſt, if it be conſidered, that it was not only made, and publiſhed, and preſſed, without no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice given him, and at <hi>ſuch a time too,</hi> and condition of affairs, as had ſerved the <hi>King</hi> from the <hi>Covenanting party,</hi> but it was ſtill carried on againſt the <hi>Kings diſlike,</hi> and expreſs <hi>diſſent</hi> and prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, in a timely and ſolemn <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation</hi> againſt it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:57726:52"/>
               <head>SECT. 4. <hi>Of the Kings Proclamation againſt the Covenant.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. THe <hi>King</hi> was pleaſed, upon the firſt hearing of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> publiſhed in <hi>Print</hi> by the <hi>Order</hi> of the <hi>Commons,</hi> (which I conceive was <hi>ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time</hi> before the <hi>Order</hi> of the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> for the tendring and taking of it;) to iſſue out his <hi>Proclamation</hi> from his <hi>Court</hi> at <hi>Oxford,</hi> entituled, <hi>His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Proclamation, forbidding the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring and taking of the</hi> Covenant, <hi>called the ſolemn</hi> League <hi>and</hi> Covenant <hi>for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of this <hi>Proclamation</hi> in the preſent <hi>controverſie,</hi> is two-fold. <hi>Firſt,</hi> it Demonſtrates beyond all contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the <hi>intention</hi> of the <hi>Covenanters</hi> did not regard the <hi>conſent</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> which runs clearly againſt the <hi>Kings Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy.</hi> Secondly, It renders the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant void,</hi> even from its <hi>creation,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ever it was <hi>ordered to be taken.</hi> For <hi>Datur irritatio Juramenti aliquando per ſuperiores, ſi in illa ipſa materia ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periores cirea quam Juramentum verſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:57726:53"/>3. Now ſo far as the <hi>Gover<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ment</hi> of <hi>the Church</hi> cannot be altered but by <hi>Law,</hi> it is under the <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> at leaſt <hi>not</hi> to alter it: He having a <hi>Negative</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both <hi>Houſes,</hi> and the <hi>Kings Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> having denied his Aſſent there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and proclaimed his prohibition of it, thereby voided it long agon, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Rule.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A <hi>Rule</hi> never <hi>diſputed,</hi> grounded evidently upon <hi>Scripture</hi> and Natural <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and indeed I find not, that your ſelves do queſtion the <hi>Propoſition;</hi> though I confeſs you put me to a task that I little expected, by doubting the <hi>Aſſumption.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. You ſay, <hi>It remaineth upon you a doubt, whether there ever were any ſuch</hi> Proclamation; <hi>you deſire me to help you to a Copy of this</hi> Proclamation, and inform you, where to find the <hi>Original:</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding, that the <hi>Obligation,</hi> without it, cannot be voided.</p>
               <p n="6">6. I hope you do hereby intimate, that upon the ſight of this <hi>Proclamation</hi> you will be ſatisfied, that the <hi>Obligation</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi> was voided at the firſt; therefore I am much encouraged to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe it, and to inform you where you may find it.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:57726:53"/>7. It is indeed in <hi>Print,</hi> in more <hi>books</hi> then one, of unqueſtionable credit; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, you have it in a <hi>Book</hi> called, <hi>Bibliotheca Regia in terminis,</hi> thus, p. 332.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Whereas there is a Printed paper, entituled,</hi> A ſolemn League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for Reformation and defence of Religion, the Honour and happineſs of the King, and the Peace and ſafety of the Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland: Pretended to be ordered by the</hi> Commons <hi>in Parliament, on the 21. day of</hi> September <hi>laſt, to be Printed and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed: which</hi> Covenant, <hi>though it ſeems to make ſpecious pretences of</hi> Piety <hi>and</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <hi>is in Truth nothing elſe but a Traiterous and Seditious Combination a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, and the eſtabliſhed Religion and Laws of this Kingdome, in purſuance of a Traiterous deſign and endeavours to bring in Forreign forces to invade this Kingdom: We do therefore ſtraitly charge and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all our loving Subjects, of what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree or quality ſoever, upon their Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, that they preſume not to take the ſaid Seditious and Traiterous</hi> Covenant. <hi>And we do likewiſe hereby forbid and inhibit all our Subjects to impoſe, adminiſter or tender the ſaid</hi> Covenant, <hi>as they and</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:57726:54"/> 
                  <hi>every of them will anſwer the contrary to their utmoſt and extreameſt perils.</hi> Given at our Court at <hi>Oxon, Oct. 9.</hi> in the 19. year of our Reign.</p>
               <p n="9">9. If you will caſt the Controverſie upon the ſight of the very <hi>Original, I</hi> do not deſpair to effect it for you: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided I may know <hi>whom</hi> I may pleaſure with it, and where; for it is not poſſible I ſhould print the <hi>Original.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. However, I ſhall offer you ſuch Evidence, that this is a <hi>true copy;</hi> that I verily believe ingenuous perſons will receive it as next to <hi>demonſtration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. Note firſt, that the Covenant was ordered to be printed by the Commons, <hi>Sep. 21. An. Dom.</hi> 1643. This Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſaid to be iſſued, <hi>Oct. 9. 1643.</hi> and I have a <hi>learned book</hi> by me, called the <hi>Anticonfederacy,</hi> that was printed the very next year, <hi>viz.</hi> 1644. that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours to invalidate the ſaid <hi>Covenant</hi> with the ſaid Proclamation.</p>
               <p n="12">12. He does not indeed tranſcribe the whole Proclamation, as I have done; yet ſo much of it, and of the moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial paſſages of it, as you cannot chuſe but know it to be the ſame; and to ſay, that he ſhould feign ſuch parts of a
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:57726:54"/> Proclamation, at ſuch a <hi>time</hi> as <hi>that;</hi> or that the King ſhould not be as quick to proclaim againſt the <hi>Covenant,</hi> as he had been a little before againſt the <hi>Aſsembly of Divines, June</hi> 22. 1663. are <hi>both</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and <hi>ridiculous</hi> to any <hi>ſober</hi> man.</p>
               <p n="13">13. The words of that <hi>book</hi> mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned are theſe; <hi>The true ſcope and aim of this League</hi> (ſpeaking of the Covenant) <hi>as it is declared by our moſt gracious</hi> King, (and we cannot receive it from a better hand,) is <hi>in purſuance of a Traiterous de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign and endeavour to bring in Forreign Forces to invade this Kingdome: and is therefore by his Majeſty juſtly ſentenced; notwithſtanding its ſpecious expreſſions of Piety</hi> and <hi>Religion, to be nothing elſe in Truth, but a Traiterous and ſeditious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination againſt him, and againſt the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Religion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd Laws of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which are the very words of the</hi> Proclamation it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="14">14. I hope you will now no longer doubt, whether there were indeed any ſuch <hi>Proclamation,</hi> or whether it be of force to void the <hi>Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. You ſay, you allow that Rule of <hi>Ames; datur irritatio aliquando per ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periores:</hi>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:57726:55"/> but you note it muſt be, <hi>ſi in illa ipſa materia ſint ſuperiores circa qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erſatur Juramentum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. But let me recommend it to your ſecond thoughts, whether endeavour ſimply conſidered, or endeavour with its object, extirpation of Prelacy, be the matter of the Covenant, and whether the King in this very matter of extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Prelacy, or endeavours to do it, be not allowed to be our Superiour.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Admit, there were a <hi>Covenant</hi> taken by private perſons, to <hi>Endeavor</hi> to bring in forreign forces; endeavor indeed is to every man, <hi>ſui juris;</hi> but that <hi>this</hi> endeavour, and conſequently, <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>Covenant,</hi> is not in a matter ſubordinate to the King, I think you will not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute.</p>
               <p n="18">18. Laſtly, you ſeem to wonder that I make it a Probleme, whether ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the <hi>Proclamation</hi> had voided the Covenant at firſt, the <hi>Kings</hi> after-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent could revive it.</p>
               <p n="19">19. If you underſtand <hi>my words,</hi> with reſpect to the firſt engagement actually made and voided by the Proclamation; I think yopu need not much wonder if I ſhould have affirmed, whereas I onely
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:57726:55"/> 
                  <hi>quaeried,</hi> Whether the ſame Act, made <hi>void</hi> could be made in force again? I am not afraid to write over the words once more: I think it may well be a <hi>Problem, Whether the Kings after-conſent could revive it, if it had indeed been dead and buried ſop many years before?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20. For the <hi>Covenant</hi> being voided by the Kings <hi>proteſt</hi> againſt it, and the <hi>Parliament</hi> diſſolved that promoted it, I think you would wonder more at it if I ſhould affirm, That the King hath pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, without a Bill to that purpoſe from the two Houſes, by His own <hi>ſingle</hi> Act to revive a matter of ſo high a nature to His Subjects, ſo long time after.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="case">
            <head>CASE X. <hi>Whether the</hi> Covenant <hi>to endeavour the Extirpation of</hi> Epiſcopacy <hi>be againſt the</hi> Laws, <hi>and conſequently</hi> ſinful.</head>
            <p n="1">1. I Proceed to argue, That ſeeing the ſtanding <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land are the expreſs and fix'd conſent of the King and Supream Authority, and this extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of <hi>Prelacy</hi> cannot be effected but by offering violence to the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land, which cannot be lawfully done
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:57726:56"/> without the Conſent and Act of the King and ſupream Authority; it is <hi>ſinful</hi> to ſwear to endeavour it, without ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to their will and pleaſhres.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This is evident by the former Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, by the rules of all <hi>Caſuiſts,</hi> and particularly of Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckludes, <hi>That a Covenant taken againſt the Laws of the Land is void of it ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. To apply this Argument to our Caſe, I obſerve, The great Objection of Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> the <hi>Covenanters-Plea,</hi> and you, my <hi>Surveyors,</hi> is this, That <hi>Epiſcopal Government</hi> is not <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> by <hi>Law</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. This Objection I labour, firſt, to avoid by a <hi>diſtinction</hi> in <hi>general;</hi> and then I argue the point particularly, <hi>That this Government is eſtabliſhed by Law in</hi> England.</p>
            <p n="5">5. My <hi>diſtinction</hi> is this: We may <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour</hi> againſt the <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>ſwear</hi> accordingly, two ways; either when the thing we ſwear againſt is expreſly eſtabliſhed by plain <hi>Law,</hi> or when the thing we ſwear againſt cannot be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed without the <hi>abolition</hi> or <hi>alteration</hi> of <hi>Law.</hi> Hence I argue, That admit there were no expreſs <hi>Law</hi> appointing
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:57726:56"/> this Form of Government ſworn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, yet how doth this clear the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters</hi> from ſwearing <hi>againſt Law,</hi> when they ſwear to <hi>extirpate</hi> that Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment which cannot be extirpated without the alteration of <hi>many Laws.</hi> So that this evaſion, I think, is perfectly obſtructed.</p>
            <p n="6">6. All that you anſwer is levelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this <hi>diſtinction;</hi> you ask, <hi>Is it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Law <hi>to endeavour the alteration, yea the abrogation of ſome</hi> Laws <hi>and things thereby eſtabliſhed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Now I beſeech you conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you have any thing at all in theſe words to enervate or avoid my diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or to render it poor as well as plain, as you ſeem to glory; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding your <hi>confidence,</hi> your <hi>ingenuity</hi> ſhall judge betwixt us.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Conſider therefore the end for which I propoſed it, and you will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs you have not evaded it; was it not in expreſs terms to obſtruct the Objection of Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> and the Author of the <hi>Covenanters Plea,</hi> viz. <hi>That Epiſcopal Government is not eſtabliſhed by Law;</hi> to which I ſaid, <hi>That it is all one whether it be eſtabliſhed by</hi> expreſs Law, <hi>or cannot be</hi>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:57726:57"/> 
               <hi>aboliſhed without the alteration of</hi> Law: Now to this uſe of my diſtinction you have yet anſwered nothing at all.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Beſides, in your <hi>Querie, Whether it be againſt</hi> Law <hi>to endeavour to abrogate</hi> Law? Unleſs you diſcover a <hi>double mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in <hi>acting againſt</hi> Law, you contradict your ſelves; and if you do diſcover it, you alſo diſcover a plain way for me to eſcape your Anſwer, and to defend and juſtifie my plain diſtinction.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Surely to endeavour the aboliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or deſtruction of <hi>Law,</hi> is to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour <hi>againſt Law.</hi> Now if you affirm, That it is not againſt Law thus to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, what remains, but that this term <hi>[againſt Law]</hi> in one Propoſition hath not the ſame ſence with <hi>[againſt Law]</hi> in the other; and there are four terms in the Argument, and nothing concluded, as yet, againſt my plain di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Give me leave to be plain, and the ſum is this; It is not <hi>againſt Law,</hi> that is, it is not <hi>unlawful</hi> to endeavour <hi>againſt Law;</hi> therefore, to endeavour againſt <hi>Law</hi> is not to endeavour againſt <hi>Law;</hi> and then my diſtinction of endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring againſt that which is eſtabliſhed
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:57726:57"/> by Law, or againſt that which cannot be aboliſhed without the alteration or abolition of Law, is a poor diſtinction.</p>
            <p n="12">12. But you call me off to prove, That ſuch an endeavour to extirpate Church-Government as was Covenant-ed, was againſt the <hi>Law,</hi> both antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and <hi>ſubſequent;</hi> this done, you ſay, would much avail; but you expect my evidence.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="case">
            <head>CASE XI. <hi>Whether the preſent Church-Government was eſtabliſhed by</hi> Law <hi>before the</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant <hi>was taken?</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe ſum of what I ſaid upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of this <hi>Caſe</hi> is reducible to three heads.</p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 1. <hi>Church-Government is fixed by</hi> Law.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, there is no need that we prove the Government to be eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Law</hi> in ſuch a manner as the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanters</hi> ſeek for, while we find it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all controverſie, that this Form is <hi>legal,</hi> and eſtabliſhed in the <hi>Laws,</hi> though no <hi>expreſs Statute</hi> ſhould be found ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:57726:58"/> it; and it is ſo much allowed, ſo far fixed and eſtabliſhed by the Laws, that he that ſhall any way engage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it doth ſo far engage againſt <hi>known Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Now until this be queſtioned, to what end do we trouble our ſelves any further? All that is more then this is <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ubundanti,</hi> and hath no neceſſary place left in the <hi>Argument.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Yet of this, whereon the very hinge of the Controverfie turns, you have ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the pains to take any notice at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 2. <hi>The</hi> Original <hi>of</hi> Prelacy <hi>is not to be ſought in</hi> Law.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IN the ſecond place I intimated, that it ſeems to me unreaſonable to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſuch proof, That the Government of the Church ſhould be eſtabliſhed by Law in ſuch a manner as you ſeek for, <hi>That it ſhould have its Original Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment in</hi> Law.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For before, and at the firſt making of Chriſtian Laws in this Kingdom, this <hi>Government</hi> was found <hi>exiſting;</hi> and to have firſt deſtroyed this <hi>Government,</hi> and then again to have eſtabliſhed the ſame
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:57726:58"/> by Law, would have been plainly <hi>ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous;</hi> which yet muſt have been done, in order to ſuch an eſtabliſhment as you require proof of.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is acknowledged by Mr. <hi>Fox,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Act. Mon. <hi>Tom. 1. pag. 148.</hi>
                  </note> that in <hi>Elutherius</hi> his time <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 180. when <hi>this Realm was firſt converted to Chriſtianity,</hi> there were appointed in the ſame three <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> and twenty eight <hi>Biſhops;</hi> and ſince that time the <hi>Government</hi> of the Church by <hi>Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. hath been further e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed by <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> which hath been confirmed above 30 times by Parliament; and by the Statute called <hi>Confirmatio Chartarum,</hi> ſtill in force, it was ordained, that <hi>all</hi> Laws <hi>contrary to that</hi> Charter <hi>ſhould be void;</hi> and that <hi>Biſhops,</hi> twice every year, ſhould <hi>excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate</hi> all that did, either do or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe contrary to it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The <hi>Government of the Church was at firſt founded in Prelacy;</hi> therefore ſo far as we are a <hi>Chriſtian Nation,</hi> and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Laws, <hi>Epiſcopal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> goes into our <hi>foundation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. I mean only it is ſo of the <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> as to be <hi>from</hi> and <hi>in the beginning</hi> of <hi>Church-Government</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian</hi>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:57726:59"/> 
                  <hi>Laws</hi> among us: I do not ſay, ſo of the <hi>foundation</hi> as to be <hi>unalterable,</hi> yet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do; however, it is not yet <hi>actually altered,</hi> and that is as much as the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument requires, and to warrant that expreſſion which I thought <hi>augmenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> though you paſs it by <hi>unnoted, viz.</hi> that there is the <hi>leſs reaſon</hi> to expect that the <hi>Power, Office,</hi> or <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> ſhould have their <hi>origen</hi> from the Laws of the Land, or that <hi>the Child ſhould beget the Father.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 3. <hi>Church-Government is eſtabliſhed by Law.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. THirdly, I laboured to prove, that ſo far as a <hi>Government,</hi> that was <hi>prae-exiſting</hi> before the Laws con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it, could be reaſonably expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be <hi>eſtabliſhed by Law,</hi> the <hi>preſent Church-Government</hi> is <hi>eſtabliſhed by Law:</hi> For,</p>
               <p n="2">2. Firſt, the Laws of this Land, ſince they were <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> have ever al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed it and taken it for granted (as having its foundation ſufficiently laid before) upon all occaſions; not only by thoſe <hi>ſpecial Laws</hi> that particularly relate unto it, but indeed in <hi>every</hi> Law
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:57726:59"/> which expreſſeth the Conſent of the <hi>Lords Spiritual.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Here you only catch at the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part about the Conſent of the <hi>Lords Spiritual</hi> to the Acts of <hi>Parliament,</hi> leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſtrength of the Argument grounded in thoſe many <hi>ſpecial</hi> Laws which relate to <hi>this Government,</hi> and apparently <hi>allow</hi> and <hi>continue</hi> it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any <hi>exception</hi> or <hi>obſervation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Yet I am not at all ſatisfied that the allowance and recording of their Conſent to every Law, by the King, Peers, and Commons, is not a plain ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of <hi>Epiſcopal Power</hi> and <hi>Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Secondly, I affirm, That the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Government</hi> is <hi>eſtabliſhed by Law,</hi> though not in its <hi>Office</hi> which was before the Law, yet in its <hi>Political Power,</hi> and the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of it, in this Kingdom.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Therefore the ſeveral <hi>Legal Names</hi> of <hi>Prelatical</hi> Governours, with their diſtinct <hi>Jurisdictions,</hi> and the <hi>Crimes</hi> puniſhable by them, and the <hi>Authority</hi> allowed ſo to puniſh, and the <hi>Fees</hi> of their <hi>Courts,</hi> and the <hi>Form</hi> and Manner of Conſecrating Biſhops are found and founded in the Laws of the Land.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:57726:60"/>7. In your Recital of this Argument you only mention the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of this Government, and take no notice of its <hi>Political Power</hi> given by Law; and therefore your Anſwer is ſhort.</p>
               <p n="8">8. But that this <hi>Political Power</hi> of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Governours is ſetled and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by the Laws of the Land is moſt evident in that of the 24 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 12. &amp; <hi>Eliz. An.</hi> 1. 2.</p>
               <p n="9">9. By 24 <hi>Hen. 8. c. 12. Jurisdiction</hi> touching <hi>Matrimony, Wills, Tithes, Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi> &amp;c. is expreſly given them; and it is added, that all ſuch Spiritual Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhall be from henceforth <hi>heard, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, diſcuſs'd,</hi> and cleerly, finally and <hi>definitively adjudged</hi> and determined within the <hi>Kings Jurisdiction</hi> and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and not elſewhere, in <hi>ſuch</hi> Courts <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal</hi> of the ſame as the natures of the Cauſes ſhall require.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Note, That if the <hi>Temporal</hi> Courts have any <hi>Authority</hi> given them by <hi>this Statute,</hi> ſo alſo have the <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al;</hi> they are joyned together; <hi>ſuch Courts Spiritual and Temporal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. The point of <hi>Appeals</hi> is alſo eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by the ſaid Statute; and <hi>Biſhops</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:57726:60"/> are expreſſy authorized to receive <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals</hi> from <hi>Arch-Deacons</hi> Courts; and the <hi>Arch-Biſhops</hi> from the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> with <hi>Authority hereby given them,</hi> or eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in them, to put a <hi>final end</hi> to all ſuch Controverſies. You may reade tho <hi>Statute</hi> at large.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Yet, I conceive, that of <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. c. 2. is more preciſe to our purpoſe, Where it is Ordained and Enacted, that all and ſingular <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> and <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,</hi> and every of their <hi>Chancellours, Commiſſaries, Archdeacons,</hi> and other <hi>Ordinaries,</hi> having any peculiar <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtiel Jurisdiction, ſhall</hi> have full <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> by <hi>Virtue</hi> of this <hi>Act,</hi> as well to inquire in their <hi>Viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Synods</hi> and <hi>elſewhere,</hi> to take <hi>Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations</hi> and <hi>Informations</hi> of all and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the things above mentioned within the Limits of their <hi>Jurisdiction;</hi> and to <hi>puniſh</hi> the ſame by <hi>Admonition, Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, Sequeſtratien,</hi> or <hi>Deprivation,</hi> and other <hi>Cenſures</hi> and <hi>Proceſs,</hi> in like Form as <hi>heretof ore</hi> hath been uſed in like Caſes by the <hi>Queens Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Laws.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Here, we cannot but ſee, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>legal Names of Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:57726:61"/> mentioned; but their politi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Power and Authority allowed, yea, formally inveſted and eſtabliſh't in them to inquire, and to puniſh. To <hi>puniſh</hi> with Admonition, Excommunication, Sequeſtration and Deprivation, and all this by <hi>Virtue</hi> of this <hi>Act.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. Had we nothing more to prove Epiſcopal Government to be eſtabliſhed by law, but this very Statute, <hi>I</hi> cannot apprehend but that the work is done, and all Objections to the contrary for ever ſuperſeded.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Is here only a liberty to exerciſe a power <hi>given them?</hi> is it not expreſs, that <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> is alſo <hi>given them?</hi> 'Tis not declared, that they have <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> by Virtue of <hi>their Office,</hi> or any other way; but it is <hi>enacted</hi> that they have Power and Authority to inquire and puniſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by <hi>Virtue</hi> of <hi>this</hi> very <hi>Act.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. Yea, though it is intimated, that the <hi>ſame</hi> Courſe had been uſed former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; it is not <hi>enacted only,</hi> that this ſhall <hi>continue;</hi> but as if <hi>ſuch</hi> a kind of <hi>Objection</hi> had been in proſpect; it is <hi>enacted,</hi> that by <hi>Virtue of this Statute</hi> all theſe Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, Governours ſhall have full
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:57726:61"/> Power and Authority to proceed in <hi>like Form as heretofore bath been uſed in like caſes by the Queens Eccleſiaſtical laws.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. While I read the Statute ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs and punctual in the Caſe, I know you will not blame me, if I wonder at your ſo frequent comparing the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> with Uſury, and her <hi>Governours</hi> with Uſurers.</p>
               <p n="18">18 I do not know of any Statute that gives ſo much countenance to Uſury and Uſurers, as to ſay, be <hi>it enacted that pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> and <hi>Authority be given to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurers,</hi> or that makes them a politick body, and inveſts them with <hi>Government</hi> over ſo much as their own <hi>Tribe,</hi> and in Caſes peculiar to their own way, abuſes and faults of Uſury: Do not reflect ſo unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemingly.</p>
               <p n="19">19. Thirdly, I affirm, that ſhould we yield unto you that there is <hi>no expreſs Statute immediatly Authorizing</hi> Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Governours; yet immediately it it cannot be denied, to be eſtabliſhed by Law: I mean ſuch Law as impowers the <hi>King</hi> to <hi>Commiſſion</hi> and Authorize the <hi>Governours</hi> in the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20. That the <hi>King</hi> hath ſuch a power in him is manifeſt from the <hi>Oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy.</hi>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:57726:62"/> For <hi>being ſupream Governour in all cauſes Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> he is ſo over all perſons Eccleſiaſtical, as to Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate all his inferiour Governours; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they all, either mediately or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, receive their Commiſſions from him; which is, no doubt, Legal, in the Judgement of all that underſtand theſe <hi>Proteſtant Laws,</hi> that revolve the power uſurped by the Pope, upon <hi>Henry</hi> the Eighth, and all his ſucceſſours, in the Crown of <hi>England</hi> for ever. v. 26. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. c. 1. <hi>&amp; Eliz.</hi> 1. where you reade thus:</p>
               <p n="21">21. All <hi>Jurisdictions</hi> heretofore <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> exerciſed by any <hi>Eccleſiaſtical power</hi> or <hi>Authority</hi> for <hi>Viſitation, Reformation,</hi> &amp;c. are <hi>united and annexed</hi> to the <hi>impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Crown of this Realm:</hi> and that your <hi>Highneſs,</hi> your <hi>Heirs</hi> and <hi>Succeſſors,</hi> ſhall have <hi>full power and Authority,</hi> by <hi>virtue of this Act,</hi> by Letters Patents under the great Seal of <hi>England</hi> to Aſſign, Name, and Authorize perſons to exerciſe all manner of <hi>Jurisdictions,</hi> and to <hi>Viſit, Reform, Redreſs, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="22">22. <hi>Your Anſwer</hi> is, <hi>this</hi> at moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes but for the Governours, and not for the Frame of Government.</p>
               <p n="23">
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:57726:62"/>23. But do you not hereby grant as much as my <hi>Argument</hi> needs? For if the <hi>Governours</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> are Authorized by Law; you ow them Obedience, and the Law in them; and your <hi>Covenant</hi> provokes you to diſobedience.</p>
               <p n="24">24. Again, How can all the <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> be Authorized by Law, and not the Frame of Government too? He that by Law Commiſſionates all the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, doth he not thereby eſtabliſh the Frame of Government?</p>
               <p n="25">25. Yea, where will you look for the Frame of Government, but in the Seat of Governours, and that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Covenant</hi> it ſelf? You there engage againſt <hi>Prelacy;</hi> that is the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the <hi>Church</hi> by <hi>Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Viz.</hi> the ſeveral Governours of it.</p>
               <p n="26">26. You add the <hi>Kings Supremacy</hi> may exiſt in, and operate by <hi>other</hi> Church Covernours, as well as theſe.</p>
               <p n="27">27. <hi>I</hi> anſwer eaſily; that admit what you ſay, yet as no other ſort of Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours can be Legally ſo, until the King Commiſſionate them as he hath done theſe; ſo this kind, <hi>viz.</hi> Epiſcopal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, muſt of neceſſity continue to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:57726:63"/> be Legal, until the <hi>King</hi> ſhall Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate others of another Method; or at leaſt <hi>withdraw</hi> his Commiſſion from theſe in the preſent form of Church-Government; if he hath power to do it by Law.</p>
               <p n="28">28. Laſtly, I urge you, that <hi>this</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is plainly eſtabliſhed by <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="29">29. To this you ſay, that <hi>Preſcription is a poor Fence to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation;</hi> Uſury hath preſcription.</p>
               <p n="30">30. But <hi>how</hi> doth it appear that the preſent Government is an Uſurpation: ſo weighty a charge deſerves <hi>proof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="31">31. <hi>Church Governours</hi> are the <hi>Kings</hi> Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Officers;</hi> they have their power and authority to Govern, given them by <hi>Act</hi> of Parliament: this appears, but that their Government is Uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, appears not.</p>
               <p n="32">32. To make <hi>good</hi> your charge, <hi>two things</hi> require <hi>proof.</hi> Firſt, that <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal Covernment</hi> was an Uſurpation at firſt. Secondly, that it is ſo ſtill, and that it hath not <hi>obtained a good Title in law,</hi> all this while.</p>
               <p>The Statutes now mentioned prove the preſent Title of it. And <hi>Magna</hi>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:57726:63"/> 
                  <hi>Charta</hi> is a ſufficient Evidence, that <hi>ſo long agon</hi> it had Legal Authority, and was no Uſurpation.</p>
               <p n="33">33. I rather mention <hi>Magna Charta</hi> here, becauſe, it is accounted <hi>Common Law,</hi> and adds much ſtrength to my Argument thence, and from long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance: Eſpecially, ſeeing there is much for the <hi>Church and Biſhops,</hi> but nothing for Uſurers and Uſury to be found in it.</p>
               <p n="34">34. The <hi>Plea,</hi> that <hi>Magna Charta</hi> is in behalf of the <hi>Abhots</hi> at well as <hi>Biſhops</hi> hath nothing at all againſt us.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Abbots</hi> were <hi>ſince aboliſhed</hi> by <hi>law,</hi> ſo were not <hi>Biſhops.</hi> We are not arguing that <hi>nothing</hi> confirmed by <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Charta</hi> can be <hi>lawfully altered:</hi> but that Epiſcopal Government confirmed by <hi>Magna Charta</hi> is eſtabliſhed by that Law, and not removed by any other.</p>
               <p n="35">35. Yea, <hi>this Objection</hi> anſwers it <hi>ſelf,</hi> and all the reſt of its Company; and yields us an Argument that might paſs for an <hi>Inſtar omnium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abbots</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> were both confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Law of this Land. <hi>Abbots</hi> are removed by Law and not <hi>Biſhops;</hi> and in the Law, <hi>exceptio firmat Regulam in non exceptis;</hi> and therefore the Law that
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:57726:64"/> removed the <hi>Abbots,</hi> did eſtabliſh the <hi>Biſhops:</hi> and thus Epiſcopacy is eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Law.</p>
               <p n="36">36. But are there not <hi>State-Officers</hi> that had not their <hi>original</hi> in the <hi>Statute-Laws,</hi> but only in the <hi>Common-Law</hi> of this Land, (as hundred-Conſtables and Crownets, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> will any ſay, that <hi>theſe</hi> are not <hi>eſtabliſhed by law?</hi> Theſe were before the known written ſtatute Laws, and ſo were <hi>Biſhops</hi> in <hi>England</hi> before any Chriſtian Laws.</p>
               <p n="37">37. Indeed, methinks, the very Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions of your ſelves, Mr. <hi>Crofton,</hi> yea and of the two Houſes of the Long Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, is as much as my Argument and the Government of the Church can ſtand in <hi>need</hi> of.</p>
               <p n="38">38. You grant in one place of your <note place="margin">P. 28. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Book,</hi> your <hi>ſelves,</hi> that the Government of the Church by Prelacy, is not onely limited, reſtrained, regulated, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected; yea, in ſome things authorized by the <hi>Kings</hi> Laws. <hi>I</hi> think you will hardly ſay Uſury is ſo; or that any thing <hi>Authorized by law</hi> can be deſtroyed, but <hi>by law:</hi> And that ſufficeth my <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="39">39. Again, methinks, Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:57726:64"/> the Controverſie againſt <hi>himſelf</hi> in his <hi>Berith. Anti-Baal.</hi> p. 25. There he chargeth the late <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Exon,</hi> becauſe he pleaded for the <hi>Jus Divinuin</hi> of <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy,</hi> that he did <hi>confront King</hi> and <hi>Parliament in what all their Statutes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare to be their own creature and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion even from the Statutes of</hi> Carlile, and the 25. of Ed. 3. declaring againſt the <hi>Pope,</hi> that <hi>Holy Church was founded in Prelacy by their own Donation, Power and Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="40">40. Now, <hi>I</hi> conceive, <hi>this</hi> was never ſaid of Uſury, or indeed, of any thing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>not</hi> eſtabliſhed by Law. For how is this <hi>Donation, Power</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> put forth in <hi>framing</hi> this <hi>Creature</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution</hi> of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> but in <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> that is, the <hi>laws of the land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="41">41. If there be any <hi>doubt,</hi> what judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the <hi>two Houſes</hi> that impoſed the Covenant, had touching the Legality of the Government of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> we are ſatisfied of that, by their Applications to his <hi>Majeſty</hi> for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of it, at the <hi>Ile of Wight.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="42">42. Their words are theſe: for the <hi>Aboliſhing</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> we take leave to ſay, that it is not the <hi>Apoſtolical Biſhop,</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:57726:65"/> which the <hi>Bill</hi> deſired of your <hi>Majeſty, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to remove;</hi> but that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly was eſtabliſhed by law in this <hi>Kingdom:</hi> Again, onely to <hi>put down him by law who was ſet up by law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="43">43. Note firſt, that the <hi>Long Parlia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment</hi> did not doubt, but that <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> was eſtabliſh'd by Law. Secondly, that the <hi>impoſens</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi> did extend the <hi>ſence</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi> againſt that which was eſtabliſhed by <hi>law.</hi> Thirdly, that yet in <hi>their own Judgment,</hi> that which is <hi>ſet up by law</hi> is not to be <hi>puld down without law.</hi> Theſe things they ſaw at laſt, though their many years <hi>practice</hi> before had contradicted them, <hi>vid. Biblioth. Regi. p. 350.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="case">
            <head>CASE XII. <hi>Whether the</hi> Covenant <hi>can oblige againſt a Future Law.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. YOu deny that <hi>Epiſcopal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> hath received any more expreſs Eſtabliſhment by the <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> ſince the <hi>Kings Return,</hi> then it had before; but I cannot find, that you ſay, it hath received no Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereby, onely that its eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not more expreſs in the new
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:57726:65"/> 
               <hi>laws,</hi> then it was in the <hi>Old;</hi> but that I need not diſpute.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Eſtabliſhment of Epiſcopacy was expreſs enough in my judgment <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore;</hi> and if the new <hi>laws</hi> be found to eſtabliſh it at all, my Argument is not interrupted.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And truly, methinks, after 20. <hi>years ſhaking,</hi> and almoſt <hi>Ruinating,</hi> we may fairly count the laws, that reſtore this Government upon its <hi>leggs again,</hi> and not only to its quiet and ſafety, but to its liberty and power of exerciſe, ſhould deſerve the name of Eſtabliſhing <hi>laws;</hi> and the Government be thought to be Eſtabliſhed by them, though it ſtand upon au elder <hi>Bottom,</hi> which I never denied.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Beſides, for a <hi>law</hi> ſo far to encourage and Countenance of Government that was troden under foot ſo long together, as to puniſh all kind of <hi>diſobedience</hi> to it, is plainly to re-eſtabliſh the ſame.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I might add, we ſee the <hi>King,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>law</hi> and his <hi>own Supremacy,</hi> hath fill'd the Church again with all the <hi>ſeveral ſorts</hi> of Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Officers,</hi> and hath <hi>ſet</hi> again the whole <hi>Frame of Government</hi> in the very <hi>terms</hi> of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:57726:66"/> over us: and thus the Government is Eſtabliſhed <hi>by law, diametrically a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> the Covenant: and <hi>then</hi> ſurely the Engagement of the Covenant is as <hi>oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite</hi> to the <hi>law</hi> as it is to <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Conſequently, whether the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> doth <hi>preciſely</hi> prohibit <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours</hi> againſt <hi>this</hi> Government, or not, (upon <hi>which</hi> Argument <hi>I</hi> cannot but acknowledge <hi>you</hi> are very <hi>ingenuous. Other laws</hi> require <hi>obedience</hi> to <hi>it,</hi> that were indeed made of <hi>old,</hi> but are <hi>now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newd</hi> and <hi>reinforced</hi> by theſe <hi>new laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Therefore, the Covenant cannot <hi>oblige</hi> us againſt <hi>this Government,</hi> but it doth <hi>equally</hi> oblige us againſt theſe new <hi>laws:</hi> which to do, <hi>I</hi> have at large pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be ſinful, and you have ſaid <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> at all to diſparage my <hi>Arguments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. You intimate, your labour is ſaved in that point; and you need not diſcuſs how <hi>far an Oath may bind againſt law.</hi> But truly, to me this ſeems to be your proper work; and that you have que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned the <hi>wrong Propoſition</hi> all this while. <hi>I</hi> cannot ſatisfie my ſelf, that what ever you pretend, that you <hi>doubt</hi> the <hi>legality</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopal Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. The Exceptions of the <hi>Antagoniſts</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:57726:66"/> you mention are anſwered before: and <hi>I</hi> have no <hi>more</hi> to do upon <hi>this</hi> Caſe, but to note <hi>one Expreſſion</hi> of <hi>your own</hi> in the <hi>cloſe</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="10">10. You ſeem to fear <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> in <hi>that</hi> which only ſerves to <hi>Vindicate God</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our <hi>ſelves.</hi> His Authority in his Sovereign <hi>pre-obligations</hi> upon us, againſt and <hi>after-Obligations</hi> contracted by our <hi>ſelves,</hi> though by way of <hi>Oath</hi> and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the contrary.</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>I</hi> cannot but believe that <hi>Gods preobligation</hi> upon us, to <hi>obey</hi> Authority in <hi>lawful</hi> things, is ſo firm and indiſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luble, that no <hi>Covenant</hi> of <hi>ours</hi> to the contrary can make thoſe things <hi>unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,</hi> or warrant <hi>diſobedience</hi> therein.</p>
            <p n="12">12. This <hi>I</hi> aſſert, though our Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant precede the <hi>laws,</hi> requiring <hi>ſuch lawful things,</hi> which needs muſt paſs with abundant Evidence; If theſe <hi>after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laws,</hi> as you affirm, do only revive and reinforce <hi>thoſe Ancient laws</hi> that had obliged us to the <hi>ſame things before</hi> we Covenanted to the contrary.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Now this methinks, ſhould have more <hi>Piety</hi> to <hi>God ſhining</hi> in it, upon the eyes of ſuch as read and conſider, then to be <hi>capable</hi> of the <hi>ſuſpition</hi> of
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:57726:67"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:57726:67"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:57726:68"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:57726:68"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:57726:69"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:57726:69"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:57726:70"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:57726:70"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:57726:71"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:57726:71"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:57726:72"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:57726:72"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:57726:73"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:57726:73"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:57726:74"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:57726:74"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:57726:75"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:57726:75"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:57726:76"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:57726:76"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:57726:77"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:57726:77"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:57726:78"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:57726:78"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:57726:79"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="143" facs="tcp:57726:79"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:57726:80"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:57726:80"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:57726:81"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:57726:81"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:57726:82"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:57726:82"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="150" facs="tcp:57726:83"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="351" facs="tcp:57726:83"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:57726:84"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="153" facs="tcp:57726:84"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:57726:85"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:57726:85"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:57726:86"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:57726:86"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:57726:87"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:57726:87"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:57726:88"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:57726:88"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:57726:89"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:57726:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:57726:90"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:57726:90"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:57726:91"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:57726:91"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:57726:92"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:57726:92"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:57726:93"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:57726:93"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:57726:94"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:57726:94"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:57726:95"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:57726:95"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:57726:96"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:57726:96"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:57726:97"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:57726:97"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:57726:98"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:57726:98"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:57726:99"/> 
               <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> or <hi>Irreligion,</hi> though I charge not the contrary with what you fear, <hi>Treaſon</hi> or <hi>Sedition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. There is nothing ſaid by you on the thirteenth and fourteenth Caſes that doth not either <hi>conſent</hi> with me, or is not anſwered already. I paſs to the fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Caſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="case">
            <head>CASE XV. <hi>Touching the word</hi> [Endeavour] <hi>and the</hi> ſence <hi>and</hi> force <hi>of it in the</hi> Covenant <hi>and in the</hi> Act.</head>
            <p n="1">1. TOuching the word <hi>[Endeavour]</hi> I conceive you ought to have <hi>ſweat more;</hi> for though you find much fault with my <hi>endeavours</hi> about it, yet I can find very little <hi>correction</hi> or amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I cannot think it my <hi>task</hi> to deal with you as <hi>Cenſors,</hi> but as <hi>Diſputants;</hi> or to anſwer your <hi>paſſion,</hi> but your <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon;</hi> now the ſum of what you ſay <hi>rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally</hi> hereupon is ſhortly this, That <hi>[en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour]</hi> is <hi>general</hi> and <hi>indefinite</hi> both in the <hi>Act,</hi> and in the <hi>Covenant;</hi> and that <hi>endeavour</hi> is <hi>ſui juris</hi> to the <hi>meaneſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And this you repeat only as the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:57726:99"/> 
               <hi>ſence</hi> of the <hi>Covenanters.,</hi> without any Anſwer to the Argumentative part of my Diſcourſe, which I cannot but mind you was your proper concern.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Indeed you chide me with ſome heat, that I had not given you any <hi>Ety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mology, acception,</hi> or <hi>interpretation</hi> of the word <hi>[endeavour];</hi> but if you meaſure the ſucceſs of your own attempt therein, you will eaſily excuſe my omiſſion of it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. For what degree of <hi>advantage</hi> hath accrued to your <hi>ſelves,</hi> your <hi>Cauſe,</hi> or your <hi>Reader,</hi> by your <hi>Latine, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Hebrew</hi> rendition of the word <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour?</hi> yea, your ſelves had juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore intimated, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> word <hi>[endeavour]</hi> is a word eaſie and plain to be underſtood; neither have you better explained it by its <hi>Latine, Greek,</hi> or <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew,</hi> or by any <hi>Etymology</hi> or <hi>Acception</hi> at all, more then I had done.</p>
            <p n="6">6. I confeſs you ſay ſomething as to the <hi>Interpretation</hi> of it; and ſo, I think, I did, beyond what you take notice of in your <hi>Surveigh,</hi> which provokes me to trouble you with a <hi>Review.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:57726:100"/>
               <head>SECT. 1. Endeavour <hi>is diſtinguiſhed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. YOu note (I ſay not with a <hi>black character)</hi> that I aſſign ſome <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Acts</hi> by which <hi>endeavour</hi> may ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; but to aſſert, that <hi>endeavour</hi> may be either <hi>private</hi> or <hi>publick:</hi> and <hi>theſe</hi> leſs or more publick; and to add expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and inſtances of all theſe (as you know I did) is doubtleſs more then only to pitch on ſome <hi>ſpecial acts of endeavou?</hi> for thus you have the <hi>kinds</hi> and the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification,</hi> as well as the <hi>acts</hi> or <hi>operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Moreover, you know I gave you the application of them alſo: I ſay, firſt, That though in a general and unuſual ſence our <hi>private Prayers</hi> to God may chance to called <hi>endeavours,</hi> yet they are not ſo, either <hi>properly,</hi> or in any uſual way of ſpeaking, by the <hi>Covenanters</hi> themſelves, nor to be preſumed to be ſtruck at, in the Act, by the Magiſtrate, who Governs <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and not <hi>Cloſets.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Again, I offer, That it is hard to aſſign any other kind of <hi>endeavour</hi> (if <hi>private Prayer</hi> be any) for the <hi>extirpation</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> that is pure and ſimple,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:57726:100"/> and without all <hi>tincture</hi> of <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Danger</hi> to the <hi>publick;</hi> or if there ſhould be <hi>any ſuch</hi> found, I humbly conceived the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate</hi> cannot be <hi>Rationally</hi> thought to <hi>intend them</hi> in the <hi>Act,</hi> there being no <hi>danger</hi> in them, and the <hi>Nature</hi> of them not <hi>properly</hi> under his <hi>Cogniſance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Now, <hi>my Brethren, judge</hi> whether it had not been <hi>fair</hi> for <hi>you,</hi> upon this <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table nick</hi> of <hi>Controverſie,</hi> to have <hi>entred</hi> into a <hi>clear Debate</hi> of theſe things? did it not become you, either to ſhew the <hi>Defect</hi> of my <hi>Enumeration,</hi> or at leaſt, to <hi>evince</hi> that <hi>ſome</hi> of the <hi>wayes</hi> of <hi>endeavour;</hi> by me pretended to be <hi>unlawful,</hi> to be <hi>good, juſt</hi> and <hi>lawful,</hi> and in our <hi>own power?</hi> and then to have <hi>convinc'd</hi> us, that <hi>ſome</hi> of <hi>thoſe</hi> lawful <hi>endeavours</hi> are <hi>ſuch</hi> as are <hi>plainly intended</hi> by the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament?</hi> this, I preſume, was <hi>your work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Indeed, <hi>skipping</hi> over what is <hi>neareſt,</hi> you ſay, you will go to the <hi>ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt:</hi> and here you demand, is it not <hi>poſſible for thoſe very Acts, which bear in my eyes the worſt Aſpect, to become lawful endeavours?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. But, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> is there no <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference</hi>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:57726:101"/> betwixt what is ſo, and what may become ſo? that which is <hi>poſſible</hi> only, is not ſo much as future much leſs preſent. It is certain, <hi>What may be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is not:</hi> and when it is affirmed, that ſuch a thing may become <hi>lawful,</hi> it is thereby granted, that that thing is <hi>now not Lawful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. To affirm therefore that <hi>ſuch En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours may</hi> become <hi>lawful,</hi> is to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn</hi> them as <hi>unlawful</hi> at <hi>preſent:</hi> and conſequently, that we <hi>cannot</hi> be <hi>bound</hi> unto <hi>them</hi> by the <hi>Covenant.</hi> Now ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, you are not required to <hi>declare</hi> that there <hi>never may,</hi> but for the <hi>preſent,</hi> there now <hi>lieth:</hi> or in the <hi>preſent tence</hi> there <hi>lieth no Obligation upon us</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 2. <hi>Of the Acts of</hi> Endeavour <hi>juſtified by my Brethren.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. GIve me leave alſo to <hi>come to the utmoſt</hi> with you; my Brethren; and to ask you, what thoſe endeavours or acts of endeavour are that you inſiſt on: I mean, that not only may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come lawful, but are ſo, as a <hi>preſent Bar</hi> againſt your Subſcription.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:57726:101"/>2. You ſeem to grant, that for a <hi>Miniſter</hi> to <hi>preach,</hi> a <hi>Lawyer</hi> to <hi>plead,</hi> and the <hi>Souldier</hi> to <hi>fight</hi> againſt <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy,</hi> are at <hi>preſent unlawful;</hi> for theſe, you ſay, <hi>may become</hi> lawful. If you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed think there are <hi>any ſuch</hi> as are <hi>ſquare</hi> to <hi>Rule, in all points juſtifiable</hi> and lawful, it is much you named them not; without this you have done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: <hi>In generalibus latet dolus;</hi> and the word <hi>Endèavour</hi> is but a <hi>Bug-bear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Is it not ſafe to mention them? however, it is <hi>duty</hi> and <hi>neceſſary;</hi> but ſurely that cannot be the reaſon, ſeeing you began with ſo much <hi>confidence</hi> in the <hi>Engliſh Genius;</hi> and have found out ways to <hi>inſinuate</hi> things <hi>more obnoxious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Therefore, though in this <hi>moſt fit</hi> and proper place you do it not, yet in another you make my <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> to <hi>ſerve</hi> the <hi>turn.</hi> In <hi>p.</hi> 28. I finde theſe words: <hi>The Covenanters</hi> (ſay you) <hi>will tell me, there are Acts of Endeavour for Extirpation other then what I mention;</hi> ſuch as <hi>Theological diſputation, ſubmiſs ſupplication, popular groans,</hi> or <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints</hi> of <hi>grievances, by and under</hi> it, which are <hi>conſiſtent with ſubmiſſion to it while exiſtent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:57726:102"/>5. My Brethren, <hi>I</hi> muſt needs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>I</hi> took great Content and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to my ſelf from <hi>theſe words;</hi> not <hi>doubting</hi> but you knew how to expreſs our <hi>Covenanting Brethrens</hi> minds, in the <hi>point,</hi> and that you do it <hi>truly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Their <hi>Judgment</hi> ſoberly, it ſeems is this; They hold themſelves bound by the Covenant to <hi>Endeavour</hi> to extirpate Epiſcopal Government, by no means that are inconſiſtent with ſubmiſſion <hi>to it,</hi> whiles exiſtent.</p>
               <p n="7">7. This <hi>I</hi> look upon as a very great Conceſſion from the rigour of <hi>former Principles</hi> and <hi>Practices;</hi> and a fair ſtep to a good agreement betwixt us which the <hi>Good Lord proſper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. For, hereby, you ſeem to grant 3. <hi>things</hi> of no <hi>ſmall</hi> concern in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That they can <hi>ſubmit</hi> unto <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Government,</hi> notwithſtanding the Covenant: That is, <hi>I</hi> preſume, they can <hi>Act under</hi> it in ſeveral places, and <hi>obey</hi> it in things <hi>lawful:</hi> otherwiſe, they do not ſubmit unto it, as a <hi>Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Therefore, they grant, that <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Government</hi> is not an unlawful Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or ſinful of <hi>it ſelf,</hi> or by the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:57726:102"/> 
                  <hi>Word of God;</hi> otherwiſe, I believe you would not ſo far own it, as to obey it, or ſubmit unto it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That if they can find out no ſuch Endeavours againſt <hi>this</hi> Government, <hi>intended</hi> by the <hi>Act,</hi> as are <hi>conſiſtent</hi> with <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> to it while <hi>exiſtent,</hi> and <hi>liable</hi> to no <hi>other</hi> juſt exception, we are agreed. For then you may declare there lies no Obligation to <hi>ſuch Endeavours</hi> as are not; <hi>de non ente non eſt Obligatio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Now, we are ſo near; ſuffer me to <hi>reach you</hi> with a word or two of <hi>ſerious advice,</hi> that you would beſtow a few thoughts upon the following <hi>inquiries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether, if the <hi>Government</hi> of the Church be not <hi>ſinful,</hi> by the Word of God, it be not <hi>neceſſary</hi> to <hi>us,</hi> by the <hi>laws</hi> of the <hi>land,</hi> the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and <hi>ſecundariò,</hi> by the Laws of God?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Hereupon, it is <hi>further</hi> worthy our <hi>inquiry, what Endeavours</hi> to <hi>extirpate this</hi> Government thus <hi>neceſſary</hi> are <hi>ſui Juris</hi> to every Subject? <hi>I</hi> do not ſay to <hi>Reform,</hi> but to <hi>extirpate</hi> it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thirdly, Admitting the <hi>Moderate ſence of ſome</hi> Covenanters, that the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant doth not intend an <hi>Extirpation,</hi> but a <hi>Regulation</hi> of this Government;
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:57726:103"/> whether the Declaration be not recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilable with the Obligation hereunto: ſeeing there we declare that we are not, <hi>obliged</hi> to change or alter, not to <hi>reform</hi> this Government.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Laſtly, take the ſence of the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> how you pleaſe, it may be queried, <hi>whether you have not done your endeavour?</hi> after ſo long and ſtrenuous Endeavours againſt it almoſt 20 years before, and ſeveral years ſince the happy Reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; we find the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Peers</hi> and <hi>People</hi> of <hi>England</hi> in <hi>Parliament,</hi> have ſufficiently declared, that it ſhall not be <hi>extirpated?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that, to <hi>reaſon,</hi> there <hi>now</hi> appears no <hi>further hope</hi> of <hi>effecting</hi> our <hi>endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours;</hi> and conſequently the <hi>Obligation</hi> thereunto ceaſeth, by the Rule, <hi>Nemo Tenetur od impoſſibile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. Pardon this <hi>digreſſion</hi> ſo fairly oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned; and I now <hi>haſten</hi> to examine thoſe <hi>ſeveral Acts of Endeavour.</hi> which you have, in the Name of the <hi>Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> propoſed and <hi>Judged</hi> to be <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. Theological diſputation; ſubmiſs ſupplication; popular groans, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of grievantes by and under it; of them in Order.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:57726:103"/>
               <head>SECT. 3. <hi>Of</hi> Endeavour <hi>by popular groans and complaints.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. IN order to a true <hi>Judgement</hi> of the <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> of theſe <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Endeavour,</hi> let us take a <hi>glance</hi> of the <hi>object<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of them as you have <hi>propoſed</hi> it; you do not ſay the <hi>Government it ſelf,</hi> but <hi>grievances by</hi> and <hi>under</hi> it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Firſt, then, <hi>for grievances under it,</hi> they may be <hi>redreſſed,</hi> without the <hi>utter Extirpation</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi> it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Again, we are not required to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare</hi> that we are <hi>not bound</hi> to <hi>endeavour to remove them;</hi> it is a <hi>change of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> in the <hi>Act,</hi> and <hi>Extirpation,</hi> you ſay in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and notes a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> or Redreſs of <hi>grievances onely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Secondly, for <hi>grievances by it,</hi> I Ask, whether you intend <hi>ſuch</hi> grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as flow from the <hi>Nature,</hi> or <hi>ſuch one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> as happen upon the <hi>abuſe</hi> or <hi>Male-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration</hi> of <hi>this Government:</hi> if you ſay, <hi>ſuch</hi> as flow from the <hi>Nature</hi> of it, then you muſt prove <hi>Epiſcopal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> to be <hi>evil in Se;</hi> which I think <hi>you</hi> will not <hi>undertake;</hi> but if ſuch as flow from <hi>Abuſe</hi> onely, you are not
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:57726:104"/> 
                  <hi>held</hi> from Endeavouring againſt <hi>them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. If you yet <hi>doubt,</hi> whether you may not <hi>Endeavor</hi> againſt the <hi>Government it ſelf,</hi> let us proceed to Examine <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly</hi> the <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Endeavour</hi> ſpecified by you: <hi>Diſputation, ſupplication, groans,</hi> or <hi>complaints.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. For the laſt <hi>ſort, groans,</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints,</hi> I cannot underſtand, how <hi>theſe</hi> can be <hi>provoked,</hi> but where there is <hi>burden</hi> and <hi>grievance</hi> to be <hi>groaned</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or <hi>complained</hi> of.</p>
               <p n="7">7. That the Government <hi>it ſelf</hi> is <hi>ſo,</hi> you do not <hi>ſay,</hi> much leſs <hi>evince:</hi> if it be found <hi>ſo,</hi> by <hi>Male-adminiſtration, Complain</hi> for me, and <hi>ſpare not;</hi> ſo you do it <hi>regularly,</hi> and not <hi>tumultuouſly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Yet, I muſt needs obſerve, that <hi>groans</hi> and <hi>complaints</hi> under a <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> muſt carry <hi>ſedition</hi> in the <hi>manner</hi> of them, or elſe they cannot, <hi>properly,</hi> or without very much ſtraining, be called <hi>acts</hi> of <hi>Endeavor</hi> for the extirpation of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 4. <hi>Of</hi> Endeavour <hi>by diſputations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. A <hi>Second ſort</hi> of <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,</hi> ſpecified by you, are <hi>Theological Diſputations;</hi> but <hi>theſe,</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:57726:104"/> are <hi>Endeavours properly</hi> and direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo called, as to the <hi>end intended.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. For in <hi>ſuch Diſputations,</hi> who knows not, but, as <hi>Opponents,</hi> we may diſpute for <hi>Popery,</hi> or any other <hi>Hereſie:</hi> by ſuch <hi>ventilation,</hi> the <hi>truth</hi> believed in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> is <hi>intended</hi> to be <hi>vindicated,</hi> and not <hi>deſtroyed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Neither are <hi>ſuch diſputations</hi> any <hi>Motion</hi> towards the <hi>Extirpation</hi> of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy, with the <hi>perſons</hi> that have <hi>power</hi> to do it: ſeeing our <hi>Governours</hi> receive no <hi>Applications</hi> or <hi>Impreſſions</hi> by them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Neither, is it the <hi>proper Intention</hi> of <hi>ſuch</hi> Scholaſtick <hi>Diſputations,</hi> to work upon our <hi>Governours</hi> to <hi>that end,</hi> who are <hi>no way concerned</hi> to take notice of <hi>them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Yet, admit they <hi>were:</hi> let me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you to propoſe after <hi>what manner</hi> theſe publique Diſputations are to be managed, as <hi>Endeavours</hi> for this <hi>end.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Conſider, <hi>what</hi> will you diſpute <hi>againſt?</hi> the <hi>Lawfulneſs</hi> of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? I am confident you do <hi>not believe</hi> it to be <hi>unlawful;</hi> either, by the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> or the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land;</hi> for you ſay, you <hi>bear affection to Epiſcopacy,</hi> yea, <hi>ſuch affection</hi> to it, as <hi>that you would have paſſed by the Object of this Covenanted Act.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:57726:105"/>7. Give me leave <hi>again; what</hi> will you diſpute <hi>for?</hi> the <hi>Extirpation of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy?</hi> how can <hi>this</hi> Conſiſt with your <hi>Affection to it?</hi> or what <hi>Arguments,</hi> what <hi>weapons,</hi> will your <hi>Affection to it ſtrike it with,</hi> to Ruine and <hi>deſtroy</hi> it?</p>
               <p n="8">8. Beſides, when <hi>ſuch Diſputation</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to <hi>deſign</hi> and <hi>endeavour</hi> the <hi>Extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation</hi> of the <hi>Kings Eccleſiaſtical Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> who ſee's not <hi>Manifeſt Sedition</hi> in it? to ſay no <hi>Worſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Eſpecially, when the <hi>Supream Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> hath <hi>openly</hi> and <hi>freſhly,</hi> even <hi>juſt now,</hi> declared <hi>Their Will</hi> to the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,</hi> by <hi>Reſtoring</hi> this Government, in all <hi>it's Officers,</hi> to it's former <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Priviledges againſt all Endeavours for it's Extirpation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, would you diſpute onely for a <hi>Reformation</hi> of it: this is not a <hi>change</hi> or <hi>Extirpation:</hi> and not concern'd in the <hi>Declar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion,</hi> as I have <hi>often</hi> noted.</p>
               <p n="13">13. But you are ready to ſay, there is a <hi>Submiſs Supplication:</hi> and this is <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Endeavour,</hi> and <hi>ſui Juris</hi> to <hi>every Subject.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. Upon <hi>both</hi> theſe <hi>branches</hi> I muſt <hi>demur</hi> a little; for indeed, here lies the <hi>ſtreſs</hi> of this <hi>Controverſie,</hi> and the ſtrength
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:57726:105"/> 
                  <hi>Sampſon;</hi> but it muſt be better proved,</p>
               <p n="1">1. That <hi>Petition</hi> is <hi>Properly Endeavour,</hi> and in the <hi>ſence</hi> of the <hi>Act:</hi> and 2. That <hi>Petition</hi> to <hi>Extirpate Government</hi> is <hi>ſui Juris</hi> to <hi>every Subject.</hi> I ſhall Examine them <hi>diſtinctly</hi> and <hi>ſeriouſly:</hi> for if <hi>either</hi> of theſe <hi>fail,</hi> your <hi>hair is off.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 5. <hi>Whether to Petition be to</hi> Endeavour <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, and in the</hi> Act.</head>
               <p n="1">1. I Cannot ſo eaſily <hi>grant</hi> it, as you take it <hi>for granted,</hi> that to <hi>Petition another to do a thing</hi> is to <hi>endeavor to do it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. We know, that <hi>Petition</hi> or prayer to <hi>God</hi> is <hi>Ordinarily</hi> diſtinguiſh'd from <hi>Our own Endeavours</hi> for the <hi>ſame</hi> thing we pray for.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Neither, is there <hi>more reaſon</hi> to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found</hi> our <hi>Petitions</hi> or prayers to <hi>ſuch men,</hi> as are called <hi>Gods,</hi> with our <hi>Own Endeavours:</hi> eſpecially, conſidering, that the <hi>things</hi> we Ask of <hi>God,</hi> are <hi>capable</hi> of our <hi>Own Endeavours;</hi> yea, if it be for gaining or increaſing of <hi>grace</hi> or <hi>peace,</hi> our <hi>prayers,</hi> are a <hi>means</hi> not onely of <hi>ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> but of <hi>effecting</hi> the ſame; but to <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter law</hi> and <hi>government</hi> is a thing of that <hi>nature,</hi> that we can <hi>onely ask it;</hi> we can
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:57726:106"/> Act no further <hi>towards it:</hi> all the <hi>work</hi> for the <hi>effecting</hi> of it belongs to our <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours;</hi> put any <hi>Familiar Inſtance</hi> with your ſelves, and <hi>reſolve</hi> the <hi>double:</hi> will you ſay that the <hi>Childe deſiring</hi> his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> to <hi>wind up his Watch</hi> is the <hi>Childs Endeavouring the winding it up:</hi> or to <hi>wind it up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. I can eaſily <hi>Conſent,</hi> that <hi>Conatus</hi> is not <hi>effectus:</hi> yet you acknowledge it, is a <hi>motion towards the Effect:</hi> which you call a <hi>Natural power:</hi> and I doubt not we agree, that <hi>Conatus</hi> hath eſſentially in it a <hi>Natural tendency</hi> and operation towards the <hi>effect, Endeavoured.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Now ſimple and <hi>bare Petition</hi> or <hi>ſubmiſs ſupplication</hi> hath <hi>not ſo:</hi> it hath indeed a <hi>verbal motion</hi> for the thing <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired,</hi> but no <hi>real Operation</hi> or <hi>Natural Motion</hi> towards the <hi>effecting</hi> of it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The <hi>ſubject,</hi> by <hi>Petition,</hi> doth <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire</hi> it; but the <hi>Parliament</hi> in all thoſe <hi>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal methods</hi> of <hi>debating, veting, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, engroſſing,</hi> &amp;c. do properly <hi>endeavor</hi> the <hi>Abolition</hi> of any thing <hi>legally eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Truly, I ſoberly diſcern this diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Petition</hi> and <hi>Endeavour</hi> both in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and in the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="333" facs="tcp:57726:106"/>8. The <hi>Covenant</hi> ſaith, we ſhall <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour</hi> the <hi>Extirpation of Prelacy:</hi> not <hi>deſire,</hi> or perſwade, but <hi>Endeavour</hi> it: Neither can you poſſibly perſwade your ſelves, that ſuch as then <hi>impoſed</hi> and <hi>took</hi> the <hi>Covenant</hi> did at firſt intend ſuch <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavors</hi> as you mean, who took <hi>other</hi> cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, you well know, to <hi>effect</hi> the ſame.</p>
               <p n="9">9. It is added, <hi>Conſtantly</hi> and <hi>zealouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:</hi> muſt we be <hi>always zealous</hi> and hot in our <hi>Petitions:</hi> muſt we <hi>perpetually ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licite King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> with our <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications?</hi> this will hardly conſiſt with <hi>ſubmiſs Supplication.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. Indeed it is <hi>plainly Seditions</hi> in it ſelf, take <hi>Endeavour</hi> in your <hi>own ſence, publikely</hi> to engage by <hi>Covenant, zealouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and <hi>conſtantly</hi> to <hi>Petition the Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>Government:</hi> this is, to declare to the <hi>World,</hi> that we will <hi>never</hi> be <hi>quiet under</hi> it.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Thus, alſo, it is in the <hi>Act:</hi> we are to <hi>declare,</hi> there <hi>lies no Obligation to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour a change:</hi> it is not ſaid, that we ſhall not <hi>Petition</hi> that <hi>others</hi> may <hi>Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> it.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>Rational Endeavour</hi> implies, that the perſons endeavouring have <hi>probably</hi> a <hi>power</hi> to <hi>effect:</hi> but it is <hi>certain,</hi> before
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:57726:107"/> hand, that, without the <hi>Supream Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative Power,</hi> the <hi>Subjects</hi> cannot <hi>effect</hi> the Extirpation of <hi>Epiſcopacy:</hi> therefore they cannot <hi>rationally</hi> or <hi>lawfully endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> it: therefore if they promiſe or <hi>Covenant</hi> ſo to do, <hi>it is ſinful;</hi> and they may <hi>lawfully declare</hi> they are <hi>not obliged</hi> unto it, that is, to <hi>endeavour</hi> what they have <hi>no power</hi> by Law <hi>to do:</hi> neither can the <hi>Act</hi> be thought to intend any more: <hi>Stultum eſt Conari quod nequeas efficere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. Laſtly, If <hi>ſubmiſs ſupplication</hi> be yet thought to have any <hi>ſpice of endeavor</hi> in it, it cannot be <hi>rationally</hi> thought to be intended in the word, <hi>endeavour,</hi> in the <hi>Act;</hi> you obſerve that <hi>Endeavour</hi> in the <hi>Act</hi> and in the <hi>Covenant</hi> are of <hi>one mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> and it is too evident there was more in <hi>endeavour</hi> in the <hi>Covenant then meer Petition</hi> and ſubmiſs ſupplication, which <hi>ran</hi> us upon thoſe <hi>ſad conſequences</hi> that in <hi>all reaſon</hi> the <hi>Intention</hi> of <hi>this new Act</hi> is but to <hi>ſecure</hi> us <hi>from:</hi> you ſay to make <hi>Laws</hi> againſt <hi>ſimple Endeavor</hi> is certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>deſtructive</hi> to the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> and <hi>Priviledge</hi> of <hi>Parliament;</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks then, you ſhould not apprehend ſuch a <hi>ſimple</hi> and <hi>bare endeavour</hi> is to be diſclaimed, as is <hi>eſſential</hi> in your <hi>own</hi>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:57726:107"/> Judgements to the liberty of the <hi>Subject</hi> and <hi>priviledge of Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 6. <hi>Whether to endeavour,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>be at all times</hi> ſui Juris <hi>to every Subject,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <p n="1">1. I Cannot yet conſent, that to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to alter the overnment of the Church, is at <hi>all times,</hi> or at <hi>this time, ſui Juris</hi> to <hi>every,</hi> or to any, Subject; or indeed to any perſon in the Nation, to ſpeak home.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>King</hi> is the <hi>proper Judge</hi> of what <hi>Government</hi> is <hi>fitteſt</hi> for the <hi>Church,</hi> both as he is <hi>Supream Governour</hi> over it; and as he is the <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. As he is <hi>ſupream Governor</hi> over the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> he is <hi>ſupream Judge</hi> in all <hi>Cauſes;</hi> into whom the <hi>laſt Appeal</hi> reſolves: and conſequently, he is <hi>ſupream Judge</hi> in <hi>this</hi> of the <hi>fitneſs</hi> of the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> unto whom the <hi>laſt Appeal</hi> for a <hi>final</hi> &amp; definitive ſentence and <hi>determination</hi> is only to be made.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Again, as he is <hi>Head of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> he is <hi>no leſs.</hi> For though the 2 <hi>Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> be alſo <hi>Judges</hi> of the <hi>fitneſs</hi> of the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> yet ſtill, with <hi>ſubmiſſion</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation</hi> to the <hi>higheſt Judge</hi> thereof,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:57726:108"/> their <hi>Sovereign Lord</hi> the <hi>King;</hi> who hath a <hi>Negative upon both Houſes,</hi> and gives <hi>life</hi> or <hi>death,</hi> with his <hi>own word,</hi> to <hi>any Bill</hi> tendred to him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. So that in matters <hi>Legally exiſting,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> hath this <hi>great advantage</hi> above his 2 <hi>houſes:</hi> the <hi>King</hi> hath power of <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> to continue the exiſtence of any <hi>ſuch</hi> thing, <hi>without</hi> his <hi>two houſes,</hi> that is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they will or not: and they <hi>cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move</hi> or aboliſh any <hi>ſuch</hi> thing <hi>without</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> or whether <hi>he will or no.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Suppoſe it be granted, that the people may petition, &amp; <hi>both houſes</hi> may proceed ſo far as to <hi>frame a Bill</hi> againſt a Government abſolutely conſidered, and without reſpect to any Prior <hi>Obligations</hi> by <hi>Oath,</hi> or otherwiſe, upon the <hi>King;</hi> and tender this unto the <hi>King,</hi> in Order to the extirpation of the ſame: yet if the <hi>King</hi> refuſe to paſs the <hi>Bill,</hi> that <hi>Bill</hi> ſo once rejected cannot be revived, during <hi>that Parliament:</hi> neither may any perſon, in either <hi>houſe,</hi> ſo much as move it any more, by the <hi>laws</hi> of <hi>Parliament;</hi> which nothing can warrant againſt, but the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the things ſo to be revived up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. The ſame <hi>Reaſon</hi> perſwades me,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:57726:108"/> that when both <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> have, by freſh law, declared <hi>their diſſent</hi> to alter the Government againſt <hi>all en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours uſed to that end;</hi> (and ſo they have done by the late <hi>Statutes</hi> for its <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration)</hi> then, we the Subjects cannot be bound any longer to endeavour it, if we were bound before.</p>
               <p n="8">8. To be bound, ſtill to vex the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament</hi> with perpetual repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Petitions, to remove a Government which they have, &amp; ſtill do ſignifie they will not remove: yea, which <hi>they</hi> do <hi>ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally own</hi> and ratifie ſo much the <hi>more;</hi> is to be bound to go contrary to authority as well as Law, to trouble the peace of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> and the Government over us; and indeed, to endeavour or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in vain, all hopes of prevailing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken away: <hi>at poſtquam palam de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperata eſt, &amp; conſtat fieri non poſse, ceſſat obligatio, ex jam dicto fundamento, quod Nemo Teneatur ad impoſſibile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. This muſt needs paſs without all controll, if we add to the conſideration that the <hi>King</hi> is known to be <hi>born to,</hi> and <hi>bound</hi> to take an <hi>Oath,</hi> by the very <hi>conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom, to maintain and defend the Government iv queſtion, as he is King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:57726:109"/>10. It hence irreſiſtably follows, that the <hi>King</hi> cannot take a <hi>previous Oath</hi> contrary to his <hi>Coronation Oath,</hi> but he thereby violates the very <hi>conſtitution</hi> of this Kingdome; and there is an <hi>Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> upon him to defend, and to ſwear to defend, before any <hi>Covenant</hi> that may be taken by him to extirpate Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Yea, the <hi>King</hi> cannot be bound to endeavour to <hi>extirpate Epiſcopacy,</hi> by any ſuch <hi>previous Oath,</hi> ſeeing ſuch en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours cannot conſiſt with the Tenor of his <hi>Coronation Oath,</hi> to protect and defend the Biſhops: and if he ſhould be tempted to take <hi>ſuch</hi> an <hi>Oath, againſt</hi> the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> it is void <hi>ipſo facto;</hi> for as he was <hi>born Heir</hi> to the <hi>Crown</hi> he was <hi>born Heir to the Oath of the Crown,</hi> and <hi>bound</hi> as <hi>King</hi> to take it.</p>
               <p n="12">12. I need not ſay the <hi>Coronation oath</hi> is <hi>unalterable</hi> in this <hi>particular:</hi> it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, that it is not yet altered, and that it cannot be Legally altered, but by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament: I</hi> am ſure, you will not ſay the <hi>King,</hi> much leſs before he is Crowned, hath <hi>power of himſelf,</hi> or with any others beſides his <hi>Parlament,</hi> to <hi>make</hi> or diminiſh or alter any <hi>known Law,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:57726:109"/> 
                  <hi>that</hi> which ſo <hi>much concerns</hi> his <hi>peoples intereſt</hi> &amp; <hi>ſecurity,</hi> in the <hi>oath to be taken at his Coronation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. Pray, therefore, obſerve &amp; weigh <hi>this Conſequence;</hi> if an <hi>oath</hi> taken by the <hi>King</hi> to the contrary before hand, doth void the <hi>Coronation Oath,</hi> required by <hi>Law,</hi> then the <hi>King</hi> by a <hi>private Oa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> may equally bind himſelf to endeavour to deſtroy the <hi>priviledges</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> the <hi>liberty</hi> of the <hi>Subject,</hi> and the other great concerns of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> as well as to <hi>extirpate Epiſcopacy;</hi> and his <hi>Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation Oath</hi> taken afterwards, would <hi>not</hi> at all <hi>oblige</hi> him to <hi>govern</hi> by the <hi>Laws of the Land.</hi> I argue not, now, from the neceſſity of the things, but from the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation</hi> of the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Oaths</hi> taken by the King about them.</p>
               <p n="14">14. The <hi>Coronation Oath</hi> is part of the <hi>Inheritance</hi> of the Crown, and all the <hi>Subjects</hi> in their ſeveral capacities are equally concerned in every part of it, as Subjects: for if we allow its <hi>violation</hi> in <hi>any one</hi> part, we let go our ſecurity in <hi>all</hi> the reſt.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Moreover, 'tis certain, that though where the Conſcience judgeth the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a former Oath <hi>lawful,</hi> the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:57726:110"/> is <hi>bound</hi> againſt any future <hi>Oath</hi> to the contrary; yet if the Conſcience be convinced or fully perſwaded that the former <hi>oath</hi> was ſinful in the matter of it, and doth take <hi>upon it</hi> a <hi>new Oath</hi> to the contrary; in <hi>ſuch a caſe the latter oath hinds the conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. Now it is <hi>open</hi> and plain <hi>to all the world,</hi> that (ſeeing the <hi>King</hi> hath taken his <hi>Coronation Oath</hi> for to <hi>defend</hi> the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> &amp; paſſed thoſe <hi>Bills</hi> for the <hi>protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and preſervation of <hi>Epiſcopal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> and by his <hi>other proteſtations</hi> and <hi>practices</hi> of the like nature;) his Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will not ſuffer <hi>him</hi> to <hi>deſtroy Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy,</hi> but <hi>dictates</hi> to <hi>him</hi> that <hi>endeavours ſo to do</hi> are very ſinful.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Surely, the <hi>King</hi> cannot be <hi>bound</hi> to endeavour againſt his Conſcience, more then to <hi>you</hi> againſt <hi>yours;</hi> much leſs againſt his Conſcience <hi>bound</hi> by an <hi>Oath</hi> his <hi>ſolemn Coronation Oath;</hi> the bond of <hi>his Fidelity,</hi> and <hi>peoples ſecurity:</hi> this hath taken hold upon <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>invincibly</hi> ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him <hi>under ſuch conviction,</hi> to preſerve his Conſcience, and his <hi>oath,</hi> and <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal</hi> Government.</p>
               <p n="18">18. In all <hi>charity</hi> and <hi>duty</hi> we are <hi>bound</hi> to <hi>judge</hi> according to all this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance;
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:57726:110"/> and I cannot imagine that <hi>any man</hi> doth <hi>ſcruple</hi> whether the <hi>King</hi> be in <hi>His Judgment</hi> for <hi>Epiſcopal Government,</hi> againſt <hi>all the evidence</hi> He hath given us of it.</p>
               <p n="19">19. So that the <hi>Objection</hi> of the <hi>ſingle Perſon</hi> is removed beyond all ſuſpition; and ſeeing we are not to declare wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> things are in themſelves, but what <hi>we judg</hi> them to be, who can poſſibly ſtick to declare, That he holds the <hi>ſingle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> is not bound by—to <hi>endeavour</hi> the <hi>extirpation</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopal Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20. Now, for <hi>any other Perſon,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Lords or Commons</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> or <hi>inferiour Subjects,</hi> how can they, or any of them, be bound, think ye, to <hi>endeavour</hi> to make the <hi>King ſin,</hi> and in ſo <hi>high a manner</hi> as to violate His <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</hi> and His <hi>ſolemn ſacred Coronati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Oath?</hi> without which he cannot <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent</hi> (as His <hi>Royal Father proved</hi> with His <hi>Life)</hi> to the <hi>extirpation</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopal Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="21">21. <hi>Conſent,</hi> I ſay, much leſs <hi>Enact</hi> it; and yet without both it cannot be <hi>legally</hi> done; neither can any <hi>endeavour</hi> it in any <hi>lawful</hi> way, but by deſiring and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to perſwade the King thus to
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:57726:111"/> 
                  <hi>Conſent</hi> and <hi>Enact</hi> againſt <hi>Oath and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="22">22. But leſt it ſhould be <hi>doubted,</hi> whether the <hi>King</hi> doth <hi>ſwear</hi> to <hi>defend</hi> the <hi>Biſhops:</hi> give me leave to ſubjoyn an Account of that <hi>Solemn proceeding,</hi> at the Coronation; ſo far as it <hi>relates</hi> to our <hi>Argument,</hi> and I have done with this <hi>great part</hi> of my <hi>Task.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="23">23. I find the <hi>Account thus,</hi> wherein, I think I am not <hi>Miſ-informed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="24">24. After the many <hi>other gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes</hi> which the <hi>King</hi> makes to his <hi>People; One</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> reading to the <hi>King</hi> before the <hi>People,</hi> concerning the <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical priviledges</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching him that he would be the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and the Churches un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their <hi>Government;</hi> The <hi>King An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth</hi> in <hi>theſe words:</hi> with a <hi>willing</hi> and <hi>devout heart,</hi> I promiſe and grant my pardon, and that I will <hi>preſerve and maintain</hi> to <hi>you,</hi> and the Churches com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to your charge, <hi>All Canonical priviledges,</hi> and due <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Juſtice:</hi> and that I will be your <hi>Protector</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender,</hi> to my <hi>Power,</hi> by the <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> as every good <hi>King</hi> in his <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> in right, ought to <hi>Protect</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend</hi>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:57726:111"/> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> under their <hi>Government.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="25">25. Then the <hi>King</hi> ariſeth, and at the <hi>Communion Table</hi> makes a <hi>Solemn Oath</hi> in the <hi>preſence</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> to <hi>Obſerve</hi> the <hi>premiſes,</hi> and laying his hand upon the <hi>Book,</hi> ſaith, <hi>the things which I have before promiſed, I ſhall perform, and keep: So help me God, and the contents of this Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="26">26. Now, who can think <hi>himſelf,</hi> or any <hi>other perſon,</hi> bound by any <hi>Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whatſoever,</hi> to <hi>Neceſſitate</hi> (ſo far as in them lies) His <hi>Sacred Majeſty</hi> to <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> His <hi>Oath</hi> ſo <hi>Solemnly Sworn</hi> at His <hi>In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uguration?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="case">
            <head>CASE. XVI. <hi>Whether the Covenant be not againſt the Liberty of the Subject.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. I Muſt <hi>ſtill</hi> aſſert, the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the Subject was <hi>apparently violated</hi> by the <hi>Ordinance</hi> for <hi>the Covenant:</hi> ſeeing the <hi>Free-holds</hi> of ſo many <hi>Several per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> and <hi>famous Corporations</hi> were <hi>thus</hi> invaded; while the <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations</hi> ſo deeply concerned had <hi>none</hi> to <hi>Repreſent</hi> them in either houſe of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> when that Ordinance paſſed.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:57726:112"/>2. This was the <hi>Emphaſis</hi> of my Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, which you little <hi>obſerve,</hi> and much leſs <hi>anſwer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. I am <hi>ſtill</hi> of the mind, in my <hi>cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt blood,</hi> that <hi>without Reſpect</hi> to ſome <hi>proportionable demerit,</hi> it is not <hi>ſui Juris</hi> to the King, or <hi>Parliament,</hi> to <hi>deſtroy</hi> any <hi>perſon</hi> or publique <hi>Corporation;</hi> or to deprive them of their <hi>legal Freeholds,</hi> eſpecially whilſt their <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> are kept out of Parliament: it being againſt <hi>common Juſtice,</hi> and the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Subject,</hi> in <hi>Magna Charta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. To conclude, admit Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> do truly <hi>Recite</hi> the words in the <hi>Petition of Right, [whereas many of them have an Oath adminiſtred to them, not warrantable by the Laws and Statutes of this Realm]</hi> yet my Aſſertion <hi>ſtands firm</hi> enough, that the Covenant is againſt the <hi>Petition</hi> of <hi>Right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. For, it is not warrantable by the Laws and Statutes of this Realm, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you conſider the <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> and taking, or the very <hi>matter</hi> of it, as hath <hi>fully</hi> appeared <hi>before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. 'Tis true, <hi>Oaths</hi> are given by Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and Corporations: but are they not warrantable by the <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes</hi>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:57726:112"/> of the Realm? if not, I am not afraid to infer, that ſuch as impoſe them run, thereby into a premunire; if they are, then my <hi>argument</hi> paſſeth untouch'd</p>
            <p n="7">7. Indeed, theſe particular <hi>Oaths</hi> are not, in ſo many words, found in the <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes;</hi> yet who doubts, but that the <hi>King</hi> hath power by the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land, to grant ſuch <hi>Charters;</hi> and to give <hi>Authority</hi> to <hi>Colledges</hi> and <hi>Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> to <hi>Adminiſter</hi> ſuch <hi>Oaths?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Again, who <hi>can,</hi> or <hi>dare</hi> lay <hi>claim</hi> to <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>power,</hi> but the <hi>King:</hi> or <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter ſuch Oaths,</hi> without <hi>power</hi> from the <hi>King; much leſs</hi> againſt his <hi>Expreſs will</hi> and <hi>Proclamation?</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="case">
            <head>CASE XVII. <hi>Whether the Covenant be not againſt former Obligations.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. I Conclude it is <hi>ſo,</hi> and therefore, <hi>void:</hi> the <hi>force</hi> of the <hi>Conſequence</hi> cannot be <hi>reſiſted</hi> in <hi>thoſe</hi> excellent <hi>words</hi> of our great <hi>Caſuiſt. Obligation Antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens impedit effectum Juramenti Subſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentis, ne poſſit Obligare: Semper enim Obligatio prior praejudicat poſteriori, &amp; Irritum facit omnem Actum inductivum novae Obligationis ſibi Contrariae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:57726:113"/>2. I aſſume, there were three ſtrong Cords and bonds of <hi>God</hi> upon us, to the Contrary, before ever the Covenant was taken or thought of; to Obey Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: to keep our Oaths and promiſes: to Serve the Church in Our Generations; which we ſhal now <hi>review</hi> in their <hi>order.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 1. <hi>Whether the</hi> Covenant <hi>be not againſt the Law of Obedience to Authority.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. YOu would perſwade us, that I affirm this onely upon my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Principles, becauſe the Covenant is againſt the <hi>Rights</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> the <hi>Priviledge</hi> of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Subjects:</hi> which, you conceive, <hi>are all laid in the duſt</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Perhaps, you may find theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples more potent and vigorous in their Reſurrection: however, though I had a General Reflection upon theſe former Arguments; yet, I added a particular force to the preſent Argument, (which, having raiſed a <hi>Duſt,</hi> it ſeems you did not <hi>ſee,)</hi> in theſe words.</p>
               <p n="3">3. More particularly, God firſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligeth us to be <hi>Subject</hi> and to <hi>obey</hi> our Governours; and the Covenant would
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:57726:113"/> engage us to <hi>diſobey,</hi> diſown and <hi>deſtroy</hi> them: (I mean our Governours in the Church) the Covenant would <hi>diſcharge</hi> us of our <hi>obedience,</hi> and <hi>oblige</hi> us to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance,</hi> Contrary to <hi>Gods</hi> expreſs <hi>obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> upon us, which cannot be.</p>
               <p n="4">4. God doth immediately by his <hi>Word,</hi> and likewiſe by the <hi>Mediation</hi> and interpoſition of <hi>Civil Authority, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> us to <hi>obey,</hi> to be <hi>ſubject,</hi> and not to <hi>reſiſt</hi> our Spiritual Governours, the Covenant would engage to <hi>break all at once;</hi> and <hi>at once</hi> to violate the <hi>Laws</hi> of God, the King and the Church, and all Authority.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Our duty</hi> is <hi>poſitive,</hi> to be <hi>ſubject, 2. Negative, not</hi> to <hi>Reſiſt; whoſoever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God</hi>—Wherefore we muſt needs be <hi>ſubject</hi> for <hi>conſcience ſake.</hi> Rom. 13. Now both theſe are broken by the Covenant; the one by <hi>omiſſion,</hi> the other by <hi>commiſſion</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Our <hi>poſitive</hi> duty of <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> and ſubjection carrieth in it, by Univerſal Conſent, to defend, preſerve, to honour, obſerve, and to be faithful to our Governours; now how theſe are conſiſtent with <hi>Endeavours</hi> to <hi>Extirpate,</hi> I cannot ſee.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:57726:114"/>7. Again, Our <hi>Negative</hi> part, or <hi>Non-reſiſtance,</hi> is tranſgreſſed too: by the <hi>Apoſtles Logick,</hi> not to be ſubject, is to <hi>Reſiſt:</hi> whoſoever <hi>Reſiſteth</hi>—where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt needs be <hi>Subject:</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, to <hi>Endeavour</hi> to <hi>Extirpate,</hi> is too plainly to <hi>Reſiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. For <hi>Endeavours</hi> to <hi>Extirpate</hi> a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment are both far beyond the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs</hi> of <hi>Subjection,</hi> they being no part ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Active</hi> or <hi>Paſſive</hi> Obedience; and deep in the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>Reſiſtance,</hi> moſt properly taken.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Endeavours</hi> to <hi>Extirpate</hi> have <hi>Action</hi> in them, and are therefore more then <hi>paſſive</hi> Obedience: their <hi>Action</hi> alſo is Diametrically oppoſite to <hi>Active Obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. Again, <hi>Endeavours</hi> to <hi>Extirpate</hi> do formally carry <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> in them: yea, they are the <hi>formal Act</hi> of high Reſiſtance, not of the <hi>Law</hi> onely, but of the Government it ſelf: not in the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on onely, but in the very <hi>being</hi> of it: for <hi>Extirpation</hi> is the end and <hi>utmoſt</hi> of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance;</hi> and therefore, <hi>Endeavour</hi> to <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate</hi> is properly <hi>reſiſtance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. Pray, reſolve me, to what part of our <hi>Duty</hi> to our Parents will you reduce
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:57726:114"/> Endeavours to Extirpate their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment over us: or how can ſuch Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours ſquare and Conform to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of <hi>God,</hi> and-the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land,</hi> Not to <hi>Reſiſt,</hi> but to be <hi>Subject</hi> to our Governours, Eccleſiaſtical and Civil?</p>
               <p n="12">12. 'Tis <hi>vain</hi> to ſay, we are bound to obey he <hi>laws,</hi> yet we may Endeavour to have them changed: It is <hi>not ſafe</hi> to Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue from the <hi>Laws,</hi> which are but the <hi>Rule,</hi> to our Governours, who are the <hi>object</hi> of our <hi>obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. If <hi>this</hi> conſequence be <hi>Good;</hi> upon an <hi>Oath</hi> taken of the <hi>like Nature,</hi> againſt the <hi>civil power,</hi> we may hold our ſelves <hi>bound</hi> to <hi>Endeavour</hi> to <hi>Extirpate</hi> both <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. For <hi>Government</hi> by <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and the Conſtitution of <hi>Parliaments,</hi> you will not ſay, they are in <hi>themſelves Neceſſary</hi> to our <hi>civil</hi> State; and if, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Epiſcopacy is doubted to be <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> you conclude it <hi>lawful</hi> to <hi>ſwear</hi> againſt it; or having <hi>ſo ſworn,</hi> to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to Extirpate it, I dare not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to find a way for the <hi>civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> to eſcape the <hi>danger:</hi> the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference</hi> is <hi>eaſie,</hi> from <hi>Government</hi> to <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;</hi>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:57726:115"/> though the one be in the Church, and the other in the State; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially ſeeing we cannot <hi>reſiſt</hi> the <hi>one,</hi> and <hi>not diſobey</hi> the <hi>other.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether the</hi> Covenant <hi>be not againſt Former Oaths and Promiſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. THis I alſo affirm, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the <hi>Covenant</hi> was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented by ſuch <hi>Prior Obligations:</hi> the Caſe is fully ſtated in theſe words of our Reverend Caſuiſt. <hi>Si cui Juramentum ſuſcipiendum defereratur, continens ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid quod Obligationi priori ſive Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rali ſive adquiſitae adverſatur ut ſi adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetur officio, quod parenti debetur aut principi; vel ſi repugnet ei quod</hi> Ante lici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>è juratum <hi>fuit vel</hi> promiſſum <hi>ejusmodi Juramentum, non poteſt à quoquam ſalvâ conſcientiâ, vel praeſtari, vel praeſtitum ad impleri; qui utrumvis fecerit, pejeraverit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. I aſſume, that the <hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, Supremacy</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtation</hi> of <hi>May</hi> 5. 1641. were taken by the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, before any of the Nation took the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and that the <hi>Covenant</hi> in the <hi>Second Article</hi> is <hi>Repugnant</hi> to them <hi>all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. In all theſe, you ſay, I was fully
<pb n="351" facs="tcp:57726:115"/> prevented by Mr. <hi>Crofton;</hi> and ſeeing this is all you ſay againſt me in theſe particulars, I ſhall only return you to one, who in all of them did as fully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> many years agon.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He leads us on <hi>thus;</hi> as <hi>his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty hath ſworn</hi> expreſly <hi>to maintain and defend the Government of the Church, by Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. So have we his Subjects implicitely ſworn the <hi>ſame,</hi> as many of <hi>us</hi> as have taken the <hi>Oaths Supremacy,</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and the late <hi>Proteſtation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. For firſt, his Majeſty having ſworn ſo ſolemnly to <hi>maintain</hi> and preſerve this Government of the Church, if any Attempts or Conſpiracies ſhould be <hi>made</hi> againſt it we are bound by the <hi>Oath of Allegiance</hi> to maintain and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his Majeſty to the utmoſt of our power, in his endeavouring to make good that his <hi>oath</hi> of maintaining &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending that Government of the Church and the Rights and Priviledges of theſe Governours againſt all thoſe Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and Attempts.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Secondly, we have <hi>ſworn</hi> in our <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Supremacy,</hi> that the <hi>Kings High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> is the only <hi>Supream</hi> of this Realm,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:57726:116"/> as well in <hi>ſpiritual</hi> things and cauſes, as Temporal; and that we ſhall to our power aſſiſt and defend all Jurisdiction, Priviledge and Authority, granted or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Kings Highneſs: the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church being ſuch an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical thing,</hi> and Cauſe, as that, next to the Doctrine of the Church, there is not any <hi>Eccleſiaſtical thing</hi> or Cauſe of nearer concernment to the King, and whole Kingdome; and the <hi>Regulating</hi> and ordering thereof belonging to his <hi>Jurisdiction,</hi> Priviledge, Preheminence and Authority, we are obliged by <hi>that Oath,</hi> not only to acknowledge his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to be the <hi>Supream Governour</hi> in <hi>that thing</hi> and Cauſe, but alſo to our power <hi>aſſiſt</hi> and defend that <hi>Jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> Priviledge, Preheminence and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; and not to Aſſay, or <hi>Endeavour ought</hi> concerning the Altering, much leſs the <hi>rooting out</hi> of that Government, without the Kings Conſent and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Laſtly, we having ſworn in our <hi>late Proteſtation</hi> to maintain and defend the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> againſt Popery: and one Article of <hi>that Doctrine,</hi> which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> mainly Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:57726:116"/> 
                  <hi>viz.</hi> ſix and thirty, together with ſeveral other parts thereof, approving and Juſtifying the Government of this Church; it muſt be granted, that we are <hi>by this Oath</hi> bound ſo far to <hi>maintain</hi> and defend that Government, as to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and juſtifie the lawfulneſs thereof both <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> and in its Conſtitution here among us.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Beſides, we <hi>ſwore expreſly</hi> in the <hi>ſame Proteſtation</hi> to maintain and defend the <hi>lawful Rights</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of the <hi>Subject,</hi> and every perſon that made that Proteſtation; and therefore in that reſpect until we are convinced, either that Arch-<hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. are no <hi>Subjects;</hi> or that their <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning</hi> this Church is not <hi>lawful;</hi> we are bound by that <hi>Branch of the Oath,</hi> not only not to <hi>Endeavour</hi> the <hi>Extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of the Government of the Church by them, but to the utmoſt of our power to <hi>maintain</hi> and defend them in that their <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Government:</hi> and every perſon that took the Proteſtation in whatſoever he hath ſince done, or ſhall hereafter do in the maintenance and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thereof. Ante-confederacy, <hi>P.</hi> 51. 52. Printed 1644.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:57726:117"/>9. You believe Mr. <hi>Crofton</hi> will not ſtick to allow the <hi>Nationality</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtation:</hi> and then the <hi>whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> was under the Obligation of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation, before the <hi>Covenant</hi> was taken: and conſequently in thoſe <hi>things</hi> before recited, the Covenant was ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeded, and Maſter <hi>Croftons</hi> Imaginary <hi>Reality</hi> and <hi>Nationality</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> is thrown to the ground by Mr. <hi>Croftons Logick;</hi> his Poſition undermined by his Suppoſition.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Give me leave alſo to remember, that both in the <hi>Oath of Supremacy,</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> it was ſworn to <hi>main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> the <hi>Kings Honor,</hi> as well as his <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority:</hi> but the <hi>Covenant</hi> is to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to make the <hi>King break his Oath;</hi> which is plainly contrary to <hi>Endeavours</hi> to ſave his <hi>Honour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. The <hi>King</hi> hath <hi>ſworn</hi> to <hi>defend</hi> and maintain this <hi>Government.</hi> It is not a neceſſary Duty from the Word of God to deſtroy it: there is nothing more diſhonourable in a <hi>King,</hi> then to break his <hi>Faith</hi> with his <hi>Subjects,</hi> yea, his <hi>Oath</hi> to <hi>them,</hi> his <hi>Oath</hi> to defend and protect them, and in ſo deep a meaſure too, by his <hi>Extirpation</hi> and <hi>rooting</hi> them
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:57726:117"/> out. Laſtly, the <hi>Covenant</hi> is to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to prevail with the <hi>King</hi> thus, to break his <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Oath with his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> in a thing, in your own judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, not neceſſary upon him from the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Now avoid the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence if you can.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 3.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether the</hi> Covenant <hi>can oblige us to the laying down of our Miniſtery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. THirdly, I aſſert, we are firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to ſerve the <hi>Church</hi> in the work of the Miniſtery; and the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Covenant can no way diſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige us or diſcharge us of it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Argument in ſhort, is <hi>thus.</hi> No man hath power to put a <hi>Bar,</hi> by any <hi>ſelf-contracted</hi> Obligation, about a thing not neceſſary in the way of his <hi>duty,</hi> to <hi>God</hi> or his <hi>Church;</hi> the reaſon is, <hi>God hath firſt</hi> in <hi>Nature</hi> and Scripture obliged him to his <hi>duty. Eſt illicitum quicquid bono pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lico adverſatur, aut paci Eccleſiaſt. politicae Domeſticae. Sand. &amp; Actus unius non debet praejudicare juri alterius.</hi> Our own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate <hi>Act</hi> ought not to <hi>prejudice</hi> the <hi>right</hi> of <hi>another,</hi> much leſs <hi>God</hi> &amp; the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 But now to leave our Miniſterial <hi>office,</hi> becauſe we will not <hi>renounce</hi> this
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:57726:118"/> part of the <hi>Covenant</hi> as required by <hi>law</hi> is <hi>to put a Bar</hi> in the way of our <hi>duty</hi> to <hi>God</hi> and his Church, from a <hi>ſelf-contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted-obligation,</hi> about a <hi>thing</hi> in it ſelf not neceſſary.</p>
               <p n="4">4. I ſpent above 8. <hi>pag.</hi> in the <hi>book ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigh'd</hi> by you, in the <hi>proſecution</hi> of this <hi>Argument.</hi> Pray <hi>read</hi> them over <hi>again,</hi> &amp; judge whether you have <hi>ſoil'd,</hi> much leſs as you ſpeak of my other <hi>Arguments, laid it in the duſt;</hi> indeed you have not touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it with one of your fingers.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>This Argument</hi> may <hi>grant,</hi> or rather <hi>give, that it was lawful not to renounce the obligation of the</hi> Covenant, <hi>before this Act was made;</hi> but now <hi>the Act requires it</hi> as the <hi>condition</hi> of continuing in the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery;</hi> the <hi>Caſe</hi> is otherwiſe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. For the <hi>Covenant</hi> could not be taken in a <hi>matter not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>neceſſary,</hi> without <hi>ſuch a condition,</hi> that the <hi>performing</hi> of it or the <hi>non-renouncing</hi> of it do not <hi>afterwards prove a bar</hi> to our <hi>duty,</hi> be underſtood. The <hi>Rule</hi> is known, <hi>rebus ſic ſtantibw, vel ſi in eode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtatu res permanſerint,</hi> upon condition, that no ſin hereafter be to be committed, no injury done, no duty o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by keeping our <hi>Oath,</hi> or any <hi>thing</hi> truly conſequential thereunto.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:57726:118"/>7. There is a Caſe in <hi>Biſhop Sander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> that brings us very neer our own.</p>
               <p>Si Filius familias, &amp;c. <hi>If a Son,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſwear to do a thing that is in it ſelf lawful, and his father (not knowing what his ſon hath ſworn) commands him to do ſomething which hinders him from doing that which he had ſworn to do, (doth not for bid him to do it, but commands him to do that, quod impediat id fieri quod juratum eſt.)</hi> He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv's the caſe; <hi>filius non tenetur juramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to;</hi> his reaſon is, <hi>quia lege divina Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rali tenetur parere imperio Patris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Thus admit that you <hi>ſwore</hi> a <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing</hi> in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> your <hi>Civil Parent</hi> commands you to do that, which <hi>hinders</hi> the <hi>performing</hi> your Covenant; the <hi>Renouncing</hi> of the <hi>Obligation</hi> of it, in the <hi>Second Article.</hi> But, how much <hi>greater force</hi> is <hi>added</hi> to the <hi>Argument,</hi> if you conſider the <hi>effect</hi> of your <hi>diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> to this <hi>Command</hi> of <hi>Authority,</hi> your <hi>ceaſing to work any longer in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, and diſobedience</hi> to God <hi>that called you to it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>Cauſe Cauſae eſt Cauſa Cauſati,</hi> the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of your <hi>ceaſing</hi> to do your <hi>duty</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> the Law and the <hi>Church,</hi> is your <hi>Non-Subſeription,</hi> the <hi>cauſe</hi> of your <hi>Non</hi>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:57726:119"/> 
                  <hi>Subſcription,</hi> is the <hi>Covenant.</hi> Therefore the <hi>Covenant</hi> is the cauſe of <hi>ceaſing to do your duty;</hi> and therefore <hi>ſinful,</hi> and not <hi>obliging.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Supream Authority</hi> hath, doubtleſs, <hi>power</hi> to make <hi>any conditions</hi> of our <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Church</hi> within its <hi>Dominions,</hi> in things not <hi>ſinful,</hi> according to its <hi>own reaſon of State:</hi> the <hi>Covenant</hi> cannot hold us from performing <hi>ſuch condition;</hi> for then it <hi>hinders</hi> us from doing our <hi>duty,</hi> by hindering from performing the <hi>condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> upon which <hi>alone</hi> we <hi>are</hi> ſuffer'd to keep our <hi>places,</hi> and to <hi>ſerve the Church,</hi> and to which we have a <hi>pre-obligation of God</hi> upon us, not to be ſo <hi>eaſily broken</hi> by our <hi>own hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. Therefore, my <hi>dear Brethren,</hi> in the <hi>fear</hi> of the <hi>great God,</hi> whoſe <hi>Servants</hi> we <hi>all are,</hi> let me requeſt you <hi>once again, ſeriouſly to conſider:</hi> that though, for <hi>your oaths ſake</hi> you <hi>ought</hi> to quit your <hi>own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt;</hi> yet the <hi>Churches</hi> and the <hi>States</hi> you <hi>cannot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. Pray, enquire, who <hi>gave you power to expoſe</hi> your ſelves to an <hi>Incapacity</hi> of <hi>ſerving the Church,</hi> in the high and holy Calling of the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> (to which <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>called</hi> you, and for which he hath <hi>quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied)</hi>
                  <pb n="159" facs="tcp:57726:119"/> you, and in which, he expects you ſhould be <hi>conſtant and faithful</hi> by ſuch a <hi>Covenant</hi> as the <hi>renouncing thereof,</hi> is <hi>now made</hi> the <hi>condition</hi> of our <hi>ſtation,</hi> and the <hi>diſcharge</hi> of our <hi>Office.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. Ask your ſelves, was not the <hi>Law of God,</hi> requiring <hi>all</hi> that ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> to <hi>preach the Goſpel,</hi> to <hi>watch for ſouls,</hi> not to look back, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of <hi>force,</hi> before the <hi>Covenant?</hi> how then, can you <hi>plead</hi> the <hi>Covenant</hi> for the <hi>voiding</hi> of it? in <hi>ſuch things</hi> too, as are certainly no <hi>conditions</hi> of <hi>Gods Commands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. I do not well know, what you mean, by the <hi>laſt note</hi> of your <hi>Surveigh,</hi> which onely <hi>remains</hi> to be taken notice of; your words are theſe. <hi>We conceive the beſt of Actions may be as capable of an</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedit. boni <hi>by the intervenient inhibiting Decree of</hi> Caeſar: <hi>and we are to be ſatisfied that in that caſe the guilt of non-ſervice to the Church is chargable on our ſoul: We may not ſin that good ſhould come thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. So far as I apprehend this <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection,</hi> it is moſt eaſily anſwered.</p>
               <p n="17">17. Firſt, by yielding that the beſt of your <hi>Actions</hi> muſt be performed, whether <hi>Caeſar</hi> inh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bite or not.</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:57726:120"/>18. Secondly, by <hi>denying endeavours</hi> to <hi>extirpate Epiſcopal Government</hi> to be of the <hi>beſt ſort</hi> of your <hi>Actions:</hi> or the <hi>not endeavouring</hi> the <hi>ſame,</hi> or the <hi>renouncing</hi> the <hi>obligation</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi> ſo far, to be fin.</p>
               <p n="19">19. I have often ſaid, that <hi>thus</hi> to <hi>endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> the <hi>extirpation</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopal Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> is not <hi>in it ſelf a duty: many</hi> of your <hi>Actions</hi> are <hi>ſo,</hi> and particularly, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of your <hi>offices</hi> and <hi>places:</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if it ſo fal out, that, through the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> you cannot <hi>both</hi> diſcharg your <hi>neceſſary duties,</hi> and alſo <hi>hold</hi> your ſelves bound <hi>not to do a thing</hi> that in it ſelf, is <hi>not neceſſary,</hi> that which would <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige</hi> you <hi>not</hi> to perform ſuch condition of your <hi>duties,</hi> ceaſeth ſo far to <hi>oblige you;</hi> and that is the <hi>Covenant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20. Otherwiſe, by your <hi>own Act</hi> about an <hi>object</hi> not <hi>in it ſelf a duty,</hi> you would <hi>ſuperſede the Authority</hi> of <hi>Caeſar</hi> in <hi>things</hi> indifferent, &amp; <hi>clip</hi> the power which <hi>God</hi> hath <hi>given him;</hi> by <hi>extending</hi> the <hi>effect</hi> of your <hi>Covenant</hi> with <hi>God,</hi> to <hi>Caeſars</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury. <hi>Injuriam alteri facit, qui quaſi Jure ſuo ſtatuit de iis quae ſunt juris alieni.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Liberavi animam meam.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:57726:120"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
